<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Fidelis Achates, or, An Historical account of the most remarkable actions in the late reigns and the present revolution in heroick verse.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1699</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 188 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 89 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A41263</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing F847</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R29825</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11209579</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 11209579</idno>
            <idno type="VID">46801</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A41263)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 46801)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1441:67)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Fidelis Achates, or, An Historical account of the most remarkable actions in the late reigns and the present revolution in heroick verse.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>169 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for John Sprint ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1699.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Harvard University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Revolution of 1688 --  Poetry.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:46801:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:46801:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Fidelis Achates:</hi> OR, AN <hi>Hiſtorical Account</hi> Of the Moſt Remarkable Actions IN THE LATE REIGNS, AND THE Preſent Revolution.</p>
            <p>In Heroick Verſe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>John Sprint,</hi> at the <hi>Bell</hi> in <hi>Little Britain.</hi> 1699.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="account">
            <pb facs="tcp:46801:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:46801:2"/>
            <head>FIDELIS ACHATES.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>I Sing a Man renown'd as that of <hi>Troy,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Who from the Court retir'd himſelf t'enjoy;</l>
               <l>He's now retreated to his Calm Aboad,</l>
               <l>And awful reſteth like a Rural God;</l>
               <l>Leſs noiſie Buſineſs now does entertain,</l>
               <l>Till Fate, and Fame, provoke him forth again,</l>
               <l>To found a Nation, or to ſave a Land,</l>
               <l>Sure equal Spirits equal Powers command.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>His great and juſt Endowments flaſht too bright,</l>
               <l>The ſick'ning Court was dazzl'd with the Light;</l>
               <l>Ev'n Envy ſtagger'd, till freſh Furies joyn,</l>
               <l>And all againſt this mighty Man combine.</l>
               <l>The wrinkl'd <hi>Sanhedrim</hi> upon him frown'd,</l>
               <l>And when he grac'd a Throne, a Priſon found:</l>
               <l>Elaborate Votes imagin'd Faults declare,</l>
               <l>Oh! where they more than Humane, not to err!</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:46801:3"/>
               <l>A well-fram'd Church he from an early Youth</l>
               <l>Meek as its Maker, and as him all Truth,</l>
               <l>With Pious Zeal eſpous'd —</l>
               <l>No Foreign Gods tranſplanted he'd adore,</l>
               <l>He daſh'd the Pagan Idols from the Shore.</l>
               <l>He ſaw, and pitied, with a brave diſdain,</l>
               <l>Strange Altars built from ev'ry impious Brain:</l>
               <l>In ev'ry Grove Phanatic Domes were rear'd,</l>
               <l>Domeſtick <hi>Pagods</hi> every where appear'd;</l>
               <l>Polluted Off rings ſtain'd the Promis'd Land:</l>
               <l>Who cou'd like him in ſuch a Storm command?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Tell me, my Muſe, what angry Deity</l>
               <l>Sign'd ſuch Returns for ſo great Piety?</l>
               <l>Is Piety imputed for a Crime?</l>
               <l>Can Paſſion reign in Beings ſo ſublime?</l>
               <l>But who with Heav'n this Quarrel can maintain?</l>
               <l>The <hi>Heroe</hi> muſt be train'd, and diſciplin'd to Man.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>An Ancient Seat he held, a Noble Place,</l>
               <l>A Seat well worthy of ſo fam'd a Race.</l>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:46801:3"/>
               <l>What Worthies ſallied from that ſtately Pile?</l>
               <l>Friends to the Throne, and Patriots of the Iſle;</l>
               <l>Subſtantial Souls, not Minions of the Times,</l>
               <l>They never bluſh'd, becauſe they knew no Crime;</l>
               <l>Succeeding Reigns were with their Counſels bleſt,</l>
               <l>He more compleat, more finiſh'd than the reſt.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>On pleaſing Banks, by a large Rivers ſide,</l>
               <l>Where eaſie Waves in curl'd <hi>Meanders</hi> glide,</l>
               <l>With Columns grac'd, the Houſe erected high,</l>
               <l>A Reverend Proſpect gives the diſtant Eye;</l>
               <l>The Pines in artful Maſts their Turrets rear,</l>
               <l>The River now a Foreſt does appear;</l>
               <l>Ev'n <hi>Afric</hi>'s <hi>Nile,</hi> and <hi>Indian</hi> Rivers hide</l>
               <l>Their Heads, and bluſh, not boaſting ſuch a Pride</l>
               <l>The Decks expanded on the winged Air</l>
               <l>All <hi>Indias</hi> Odours cling and ſcatter far;</l>
               <l>The graceful Swans around the Veſſels throng,</l>
               <l>A Bird that only tunes a Dying Song,</l>
               <l>When Age, or Wounds, compel it to retire,</l>
               <l>Flags in the Ouze, &amp; ſings, &amp; on the Beach expires.</l>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:46801:4"/>
               <l>The Glebe, by Art and Nature fertile, bore</l>
               <l>For Man, and Beaſt, a glad luxurious Store.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Here, by a Court-prevailing Envy toſt,</l>
               <l>The <hi>Heroe</hi> reſts, in Contemplation loſt.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The Wiſe, the Juſt <hi>Achates</hi> ſet aſide,</l>
               <l>His Potent Foes at Court their Conqueſt pride;</l>
               <l>Level new Meaſures into <hi>Caeſar</hi>'s Ear,</l>
               <l>All with a new and alter'd Face appear;</l>
               <l>They whiſper Counſels foreign to the Throne,</l>
               <l>And ſlight its Intereſt, to ſecure their own.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Who rightly can of <hi>Caeſar</hi>'s Actions ſing?</l>
               <l>Or how divide the Father from the King?</l>
               <l>Oh! when in Crowds we cluſter'd on the Strand,</l>
               <l>And ſtood to ſee the Royal Exile land,</l>
               <l>What welcom Shouts redoubl'd from the Shore!</l>
               <l>The Dumb acquire a Speech unknown before.</l>
               <l>The ſubtile Nerves Seraphick Joys declare,</l>
               <l>Their Ports were open'd all to Tongue and Ear;</l>
               <l>Our willing Hands beneath his Feet we lay,</l>
               <l>And ſtrew'd our very Hearts to pave his Way;</l>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:46801:4"/>
               <l>We wait the King with glorious Triumph home,</l>
               <l>And all around Huzza'd, <hi>Our Caeſar's come.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Our <hi>Albion's</hi> Ports no longer Chains endure,</l>
               <l>They now are open'd all, the Sea ſecure;</l>
               <l>The friendly Crews are to each other kind,</l>
               <l>They know no Foes, but Rocks, &amp; Sands, &amp; Wind</l>
               <l>From late diſcover'd Countries Shipping come,</l>
               <l>And lave along, and bear their <hi>Cargoes</hi> home:</l>
               <l>Both <hi>Indies</hi> hoiſt their Treaſures on the Strands,</l>
               <l>And <hi>Peru</hi> courts us with its Golden Sands.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Neptune</hi> had now proclaim'd a general Peace,</l>
               <l>And <hi>Halcyon</hi> Murmurs calm the rufll'd Seas;</l>
               <l>The People all to peaceful Thoughts incline,</l>
               <l>Each Subject eaſie, ſtretch'd beneath his Vine;</l>
               <l>The very Sons of <hi>Mars</hi> forget their Jars,</l>
               <l>Complain of Battels, and repent their Scars.</l>
               <l>Religion now appear'd in Chriſtian Prime,</l>
               <l>Never more Primitive, or more Divine.</l>
               <l>Daily new pompous Embaſſies reſort,</l>
               <l>Diſplay their Foreign Glories at the Court:</l>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:46801:5"/>
               <l>And when the neighb'ring Princes rais'd freſh Jars,</l>
               <l>To <hi>Caeſar</hi> it's referr'd—</l>
               <l>For <hi>Caeſar</hi> holds the Scales of Peace and War.</l>
               <l>What cou'd a Prince or People more deſire?</l>
               <l>Or lov'd or fear'd, whilſt all the World admires.</l>
               <l>What Pen can tell what jarring Seeds aroſe,</l>
               <l>And urg'd the King and People to be Foes?</l>
               <l>Who can diſcloſe what Springs this Engine move?</l>
               <l>If from below they're form'd, or from above?</l>
               <l>They in obſcure and cloſe Receſſes lie.</l>
               <l>And bid a bold Defiance to the Eye.</l>
               <l>It's poſſible what's Humane to define;</l>
               <l>For what proceeds from Man, is ſhort of what's Divine.</l>
               <l>Why then let's trace theſe Cauſes to the Head;</l>
               <l>For every Cauſe will to another lead,</l>
               <l>Till by a ſtrict Enquiry we deſcry</l>
               <l>Where our invet'rate Foes relentleſs lie.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Proud conqu'ring <hi>Rome</hi> of old, with bold Alarms,</l>
               <l>Had forc'd the World a Vaſſal to its Arms;</l>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:46801:5"/>
               <l>Its tow'ring Eagles, in purſuit of Prey,</l>
               <l>Thro' vaſt extended Kingdoms cut their Way;</l>
               <l>Boundleſs its Aims, too covetous of Fame,</l>
               <l>Too awful Terrors wait the <hi>Roman</hi> Name;</l>
               <l>Ev'n dreadful <hi>Gaul</hi> did <hi>Caeſar</hi>'s Grace implore,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Britannia</hi> bears a Yoke unknown before.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>At length, beyond a common Compaſs grown,</l>
               <l>Th' unwieldy Bulk of Greatneſs tumbl'd down.</l>
               <l>Who can Eternal Deſtiny reſiſt?</l>
               <l>It fell, beneath its pond'rous Glories preſt:</l>
               <l>Complaining Nations take the quick Alarm,</l>
               <l>And, to regain their raviſh'd Freedoms, arm:</l>
               <l>For, <hi>Liberty's the Darling of Mankind,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>All Nature's Choice, the Canon of the Mind.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Their drooping Eagles now forbid the Shore,</l>
               <l>Our <hi>Albion</hi>'s Kings Paternal Scepters bore,</l>
               <l>Succeeding Princes their juſt Rights maintain,</l>
               <l>And know no more, they ſcorn'd the <hi>Roman</hi> Chain.</l>
               <l>Thus <hi>Rome,</hi> when <hi>Heathen,</hi> baffl'd, diſappears,</l>
               <l>Until the <hi>Chriſtian Pontiff</hi> mounts the Chair.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:46801:6"/>
               <l>He'll to the Rebel-World new Arts diſcloſe,</l>
               <l>Urge back to <hi>Rome</hi> its old revolted Foes;</l>
               <l>Once more he'll bid at Univerſal All,</l>
               <l>On the World's Ruins raiſe the <hi>Capitol.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Preceding <hi>Caeſars</hi> aim'd their Shafts not right,</l>
               <l>He, Eagle all, aſpires a loftier Flight,</l>
               <l>They only Tribute and Obedience claim'd,</l>
               <l>By him the Soul, and Body, both are damn'd:</l>
               <l>He'll have all Kingdoms at his rev'rend Beck,</l>
               <l>Let looſe the Reins of Pow'r, or curb, or check.</l>
               <l>It's true, cou'd he this large Commiſſion ſhow,</l>
               <l>The willing World wou'd to his Orders bow;</l>
               <l>Cou'd he by dint of Text demonſtrate this,</l>
               <l>Or by a clear allow'd <hi>Periphraſis,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>He then might boaſt the Univerſe his own,</l>
               <l>And ſit Deſpotic on a <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Throne.</l>
               <lg type="triplet">
                  <l>But if our God, imbody'd, did declare</l>
                  <l>No ſuch reveal'd Decrees, ſuch Statutes here,</l>
                  <l>Nor gave this large <hi>Mandamus</hi> to his Chair,</l>
               </lg>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:46801:6"/>
               <l>Which by our Learn'd Reformers is deny'd,</l>
               <l>Why does he in this Uſurpation pride?</l>
               <l>Let's give the Rev'rend Biſhop what's his Due,</l>
               <l>And yield to <hi>Albion's Caeſar</hi> all we owe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>Britannia</hi> long his Tyrannies did bear,</l>
               <l>A <hi>Bull</hi> was dreaded like a <hi>Roman</hi> Spear;</l>
               <l>How at a vain <hi>Indulgence</hi> we rejoyce,</l>
               <l>As if 't had been the Great Almighty's Voice!</l>
               <l>One Pardon all preceding Crimes controul,</l>
               <l>As ſure they're cancell'd, as our Sins were foul.</l>
               <lg type="triplet">
                  <l>Our Treaſures all were open'd by his Keys,</l>
                  <l>He, for our Gold, preſents us Toys to pleaſe,</l>
                  <l>Some uſeleſs Relicks, or as empty Praiſe.</l>
               </lg>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Flocks of devouring Orders now reſort</l>
               <l>Like <hi>Locuſts</hi> fly about, &amp; croak like <hi>Frogs</hi> at Court.</l>
               <l>Not ev'n the Chambers of our Princes free:</l>
               <l>What ſlender Awe they pay to Majeſty!</l>
               <lg type="triplet">
                  <l>We ſaw a Monarch raviſh'd from the Throne,</l>
                  <l>All his <hi>Regalio's</hi> from his Shoulders torn,</l>
                  <l>His Scepter levell'd, and his Crown laid down;</l>
               </lg>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:46801:7"/>
               <l>Whilſt impious Prieſts with flaming Whips appear,</l>
               <l>With Furrows gall his Back, with Taunts his Ear.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>In Common things our Senſes muſt not guide,</l>
               <l>A very Demonſtration is deny'd;</l>
               <l>For what we ſee, or hear, or taſte, or feel,</l>
               <l>Is falſe, becauſe our Senſes may beguile.</l>
               <l>Thus down at <hi>Romes</hi> proud Nod our Glories fell,</l>
               <l>Involv'd in Troubles unaccountable.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>At length the <hi>Britiſh</hi> Lion glares around,</l>
               <l>Proſtrate he lay, and trembling on the Ground;</l>
               <l>High o'er his Head the awful Laſh appears,</l>
               <l>Which his diſſected Sides with Gaſhes tears:</l>
               <l>Diſdain, Revenge, and noble Fury join,</l>
               <l>Theſe all to rouze the <hi>Heroe</hi> now combine:</l>
               <l>He recollected, with a Native Pride,</l>
               <l>How oft his Fortune had in Wars been try'd,</l>
               <l>How many bluſhing Nations loſt the Field,</l>
               <l>How many Countries to his Scepter yield.</l>
               <l>Beſides—</l>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:46801:7"/>
               <l>He ſaw with pious Ken the Mask remov'd,</l>
               <l>How little <hi>Rome</hi> the True Religion lov'd;</l>
               <l>What ſmall Regard ſhe paid to Things Divine;</l>
               <l>A Medley all the reſt, a meer Deſign:</l>
               <l>He ſaw his People plum'd, ſupine, and tame,</l>
               <l>And found a King a meer precarious Name.</l>
               <l>W<hi rend="sup">th</hi> bold Reſolves he from <hi>Romes</hi> Throne retires,</l>
               <l>Majeſtic ſtalks, whilſt neighb'ring Kings admire.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Now <hi>Romes</hi> approaching Ruine is at hand,</l>
               <l>A juſt Deſtruction rages thro' the Land,</l>
               <l>Keen Juſtice flaſhes in her Arms ſevere,</l>
               <l>As a deſtroying Angel does appear.</l>
               <l>Their Temples ruin'd, with their Mock-divine,</l>
               <l>The Structure levell'd, did entomb the Shrine:</l>
               <l>Down fell the Idol-Image at a Blow,</l>
               <l>Nor cou'd the gilded Saint repel the Foe.</l>
               <l>What impious Neſts of Wickedneſs were found</l>
               <l>In Cells conceal'd, and Cloyſter'd under Ground!</l>
               <l>A certain Signal of a coming Fall,</l>
               <l>Too weak the <hi>Baſis</hi> to ſupport the Wall:</l>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:46801:8"/>
               <l>The dark <hi>Alcoves</hi> their ſully'd Crimes diſplay:</l>
               <l>What Scenes of Holy Cheats are open'd to the Day!</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <lg type="triplet">
                  <l>In vain each Order did their Saints implore,</l>
                  <l>Like Sea-men in a Storm that crave the Shore,</l>
                  <l>They cannot hear, or can relieve no more.</l>
               </lg>
               <l>Each Idol ſenſeleſs as its Native Stone,</l>
               <l>Unmov'd by Pray'rs, relentleſs to their Groans,</l>
               <l>In wild Deſpair around they fiercely rage,</l>
               <l>And ſeem the <hi>Bacchanalians</hi> of the Age;</l>
               <l>With new Efforts they echo loud Alarms,</l>
               <l>And ſtrive to ſave their periſhing Gods by Arms.</l>
               <l>Enraged <hi>Caeſar</hi> preſſes on his Foes,</l>
               <l>And round the Field their ſlaughter'd Squadrons ſtrows:</l>
               <l>And now they curſe the Land, and quit the Shore,</l>
               <l>And bear thoſe Pains they did inflict before:</l>
               <l>So <hi>Moſes</hi> ſtretch'd o'er <hi>Egypts</hi> Coaſts his Wand,</l>
               <l>And ſtreight the <hi>Frogs</hi> and <hi>Locuſts</hi> left the Land.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>To <hi>Italy</hi> theſe ſtormy <hi>Novels</hi> come,</l>
               <l>The baniſh'd Prieſts bear the ſad Tidings home:</l>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:46801:8"/>
               <l>With what Amazement ſtartl'd <hi>Rome</hi> receives</l>
               <l>The News, declining Tyrants may conceive:</l>
               <l>What Pangs, what dreadful Horrors ſeiſe the Mind,</l>
               <l>Like diſmal Eddies, or tempeſtuous Wind.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>A Conclave ſummon'd, ſtrong Debates aroſe,</l>
               <l>How to retrive, or to rebuke their Foes:</l>
               <l>They cou'd not ſee with an indiff'rent Eye</l>
               <l>Fair <hi>Albion</hi> raviſh'd from the <hi>Roman</hi> See;</l>
               <l>Too well they knew the Value of her Coaſts,</l>
               <l>Too choice a Purchaſe to be cheaply loſt,</l>
               <l>Too ill a Pattern this to be allow'd,</l>
               <l>A Precedent not to be known abroad.</l>
               <l>This <hi>Omen</hi> threatn'd a worſe future Fall:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>A Breach neglected, fatal is to all.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>With <hi>Bulls</hi> they threaten fearful Things to come,</l>
               <l>And give loud Cautions to prevent the Doom.</l>
               <l>Their <hi>Bulls</hi> call other Furies to their Aid,</l>
               <l>To Death reſolv'd <hi>Britannia</hi> to invade;</l>
               <l>Each Subject free, muſt no Allegiance pay,</l>
               <l>He'll ſtreight be Saint, cou'd he his Sov'reign ſlay.</l>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:46801:9"/>
               <l>In vain their Home-attempts, in vain they found</l>
               <l>No Plot ſucceeds, ſtill baſſl'd, they loſe Ground;</l>
               <l>Their Hoſtile Fleets with bluſhing Loſs retire,</l>
               <l>Nor cou'd their Trains of Powder cheriſh Fire.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>With pain <hi>Rome</hi> ſees our well-form'd Church out-vie</l>
               <l>In Chriſtian Truths her vain Idolatry;</l>
               <l>Its Apoſtolick Luſter ſhone too bright,</l>
               <l>Its Beams were too Celeſtial for her Sight.</l>
               <l>To fruitleſs purpoſe long ſhe Arms had try'd,</l>
               <l>She'll now eſſay the <hi>Britans</hi> to divide;</l>
               <l>To Craft and Helliſh Arts ſh'as now recourſe,</l>
               <l>By Wiles ſhe'll compaſs where ſhe fail'd by Force.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>But who of <hi>Albions</hi> Off-ſpring can relate</l>
               <l>Our <hi>Albions</hi> Woes, and this Reverſe of Fate?</l>
               <l>What Eagl'd <hi>Rome</hi> cou'd not retain of old,</l>
               <l>Nor Miter'd <hi>Rome</hi> cou'd late with Force uphold,</l>
               <l>This cloſe Projection gains; we tamely yield,</l>
               <l>And quit the plunder'd Glories of the Field.</l>
               <l>Thoſe very Men who oft in Dangers try'd,</l>
               <l>Had ſeen wild Slaughter ghaſtly on their Side,</l>
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:46801:9"/>
               <l>When Cannons thunder'd, &amp; loud Deaths convey,</l>
               <l>They'd force the Paſs, and thither ſpur their Way:</l>
               <l>Theſe very Men to Noiſe and Rumour fall,</l>
               <l>Emaſculate they grow, enervate all.</l>
               <l>Our War-like Youth, who like a Bulwark ſtood,</l>
               <l>And Laurels cropp'd thro' many a Crimſon Flood,</l>
               <l>An <hi>Heroe</hi> each their daring Acts declare,</l>
               <l>Reſolv'd and Brave, and Strangers all to Fear;</l>
               <l>This Union broke, how reſty now they're grown!</l>
               <l>Falſe to themſelves, and Traytors to the Throne.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Now <hi>Loyala</hi>'s Sons their haughty Plumes do rear</l>
               <l>Aloft, and threaten Ruine in the Air;</l>
               <l>Like him, they're nurſt in bloody Strife and Jars,</l>
               <l>Religion is their Trade, and Gloſs for Wars.</l>
               <l>Our Chriſtian Points too eaſie are, and tame,</l>
               <l>Too ſoft a Subject, too ſubmiſs a Theme;</l>
               <l>What <hi>Jeſus</hi> taught, and his Apoſtles told,</l>
               <l>Like muſty Rolls, are ſlighted, ſtale, and old;</l>
               <l>They'll teach the World a Doctrine new and fine,</l>
               <l>A certain Standard theirs, tho' not Divine.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:46801:10"/>
               <l>In Swarms they put to Sea, and now appear</l>
               <l>Like Sons of Love, and peaceful Olives bear.</l>
               <l>How can <hi>Britannia</hi> this Effort reſiſt?</l>
               <l>A God's betray'd when fawning <hi>Judas</hi> kiſt.</l>
               <l>They ſcatter now prepar'd Enchantments round,</l>
               <l>As ſure as Fate the ſilent Magick wounds;</l>
               <l>Too many eaſie Subjects they diſcloſe,</l>
               <l>And liſt their Converts for their Countries Foes:</l>
               <l>They whiſper to the People monſtrous Things,</l>
               <l>And draw a diſmal Landskip of a King.</l>
               <l>They firſt their Int'reſt touch w<hi rend="sup">th</hi> loud Complaint,</l>
               <l>Th' expenſive Court reduc'd the Land to want;</l>
               <l>What needleſs Sums extravagantly thrown</l>
               <l>Away, to buoy the Quarrels of the Throne;</l>
               <l>Their large, luxurious, lazy Guards devour</l>
               <l>More than old <hi>Egypts</hi> meager Kine before;</l>
               <l>In Times of Peace why ſhou'd a Prince command</l>
               <l>An Army as a Scourge to curb the Land?</l>
               <l>There's ſomething ill deſign'd in ſuch a Train,</l>
               <l>A Boundleſs Pow'r he aims, an Arbitrary Reign.</l>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:46801:10"/>
               <l>Why ſhou'd a Prince be ſo divinely fear'd?</l>
               <l>Pray why this Deity ſo much rever'd?</l>
               <l>Why ſhou'd we tremble at his awful Nod?</l>
               <l>A Man is ſure diſtinguiſh'd from a God.</l>
               <l>Come, let's engage, and firſt the Court reform,</l>
               <l>Cut thro' that Wave, you'll quickly ſtem the Storm.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>This Cant prevails, the kindl'd Beacons blaze,</l>
               <l>A ſpecious <hi>Harangue</hi> ſpoken w<hi rend="sup">th</hi> a <hi>Patriots</hi> grace.</l>
               <l>But now a loftier Flight their Pinions ſoar,</l>
               <l>They'l claw their Conſcience, as their Cheſts before.</l>
               <l>How can the <hi>Chriſtians</hi> mute and ſtupid ſtand,</l>
               <l>View ſuch Pollutions ſtain the Holy Land?</l>
               <l>What uncouth Gods at Court they now adore!</l>
               <l>More hideous far than late at <hi>Rome</hi> before.</l>
               <l>They've laid a <hi>Baſis</hi> for a <hi>Babels</hi> Pile,</l>
               <l>And ſcatter ſad Confuſion thro' the Iſle.</l>
               <l>Was e'er Religion in Contempt like this?</l>
               <l>They've ſhot a Random-Bolt, and aim'd amiſs.</l>
               <l>With Grief the Land will this Devotion mourn,</l>
               <l>Already ev'n to <hi>Rome</hi> they now return.</l>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:46801:11"/>
               <l>The murm'ring Tribes of Deſart-Wilds complain,</l>
               <l>And covet <hi>Egypts</hi> Onyons once again;</l>
               <l>They backwards look with a relenting Eye,</l>
               <l>Once more deſirous of their Slavery.</l>
               <l>Some Pious Souls in this wild Breach muſt ſtand,</l>
               <l>And ſtop impending Ruine from the Land;</l>
               <l>They vainly of a Reformation boaſt,</l>
               <l>If we reform no more, the Nation's loſt;</l>
               <l>Their <hi>Hierarchy</hi>'s an undigeſted Thing,</l>
               <l>As looſe its <hi>Canons,</hi> as in Vice its King:</l>
               <l>Ah! where's its Purity, its Primitive Force?</l>
               <l>They're as before, or chang'd from bad to worſe;</l>
               <l>They're not enough from impious <hi>Rome</hi> remov'd;</l>
               <l>This Zeal by you muſt further be improv'd,</l>
               <l>Or <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Piety will ſoon decay,</l>
               <l>Or they'll to <hi>Antichriſt</hi> become an eaſie Prey.</l>
               <l>You as the Stars i'th' <hi>Galaxy</hi> muſt ſhine,</l>
               <l>You the true <hi>Puritans,</hi> you all Divine.</l>
               <l>Go to, let's ſet our Shoulders to the Lead,</l>
               <l>Let's cultivate this Vineyard of the Lord.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:46801:11"/>
               <l>It's ominous, they ſay, when Wolves unfold</l>
               <l>Strange Myſteries, and teach the trembling Fold.</l>
               <l>What will not Intereſt, with miſtaken Zeal,</l>
               <l>Affect, or dare? The Bait does ſeldom fail;</l>
               <l>This Holy Gloſs fair Entertainment finds,</l>
               <l>And ſows Diſſenting Seeds in wav'ring Minds;</l>
               <l>The baneful Hemlock ſcatters o'er the Shore,</l>
               <l>Which ſtill an impious Race of Fools devour;</l>
               <l>Their undiſcerning Heads begin to ſtray,</l>
               <l>And in Confuſion quit the beaten Way.</l>
               <l>Thus crafty Gen'rals, when they'd ſtorm a Town,</l>
               <l>And make the ſtubborn Citadel their own,</l>
               <l>With cunning Feints draw off the potent Foe,</l>
               <l>Divide their Arms, then give the conq'ring Blow.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Oh fooliſh <hi>Albion!</hi> whither doſt thou run?</l>
               <l>Eager for Fate, and hot to be undone,</l>
               <l>To thy Deſtruction and unguarded Tool,</l>
               <l>Cully'd to Foreign Streams thy Thirſt to cool?</l>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:46801:12"/>
               <lg type="triplet">
                  <l>Ev'n <hi>Manna</hi> cloys, and ſuch Celeſtial Food;</l>
                  <l>Thou tempt'ſt the very Patience of a God,</l>
                  <l>And into Serpents turn'ſt thy <hi>Moſes</hi> Rod.</l>
               </lg>
               <l>Shoals of unthinking Fry theſe Anglers caught,</l>
               <l>And reap an Harveſt larger than their Thought;</l>
               <l>They wave their Sickles in the burden'd Field,</l>
               <l>New Barns, and new Repoſitories build;</l>
               <l>They join their Voices with the giddy Crowd,</l>
               <l>And 'midſt the noiſie <hi>Mobb</hi> they bellow'd loud.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>This Game ſecur'd, ſublimer Flights they take;</l>
               <l>Our Gentry, and our Nobles they infect:</l>
               <l>Theſe, where a Court-Preferment is deny'd,</l>
               <l>Or any other Curb that checks their Pride,</l>
               <l>Diſguſts to Perſons, or in private Things,</l>
               <l>Turn them to Malecontents againſt the King;</l>
               <l>Beſides, of Parties to be ſtil'd an Head,</l>
               <l>Surnam'd a Champion, and their Force to lead,</l>
               <l>There's ſomething in't that courts ambitious Eye,</l>
               <l>A Shade or Emblem it's of Majeſty;</l>
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:46801:12"/>
               <l>Deſire of Rule's the Birthright of the Mind,</l>
               <l>The Load-ſtone that attracts all Humane Kind.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>They need no more; the Rockets mount the Air</l>
               <l>High as they fly, they build their Caſtles there;</l>
               <l>How quick theſe Machins with the Wyre-works move!</l>
               <l>They curſe the King with Blaſphemies to <hi>Jove:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Impiety and Treaſon now they bawl,</l>
               <l>The Goverment of Church and State muſt fall;</l>
               <l>There's no Reprieve, the Malefactors die,</l>
               <l>Severe enough their Crimes, no Remedy;</l>
               <l>Not <hi>Gileads</hi> Balm cou'd give Relief in this,</l>
               <l>Together both muſt ſuffer, both remiſs.</l>
               <l>For Arms the pregnant Multitude prepare,</l>
               <l>Diſſenting Nobles head the Beaſts to War;</l>
               <l>Alike their Cauſe, a woful Ruine comes;</l>
               <l>Alike they're both prepar'd to ſign each others Dooms.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And now <hi>Romes</hi> Muſick rattles thro' the Iſle,</l>
               <l>Our <hi>Albions</hi> Blood does <hi>Albions</hi> Fields defile;</l>
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:46801:13"/>
               <l>The <hi>Britans</hi> meet each other in the Field,</l>
               <l>Make Death familiar, but untaught to yield;</l>
               <l>The fertile Plains manur'd with <hi>Engliſh</hi> Gore,</l>
               <l>Produce a tinctur'd Crop unknown before;</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Heroes</hi> on either Side for War they ſtood,</l>
               <l>And bid Definance to each others Blood.</l>
               <l>Pity ſuch Souls reſolv'd ſhou'd thus engage:</l>
               <l>A Curſe on <hi>Rome</hi> for this, and this Phanatic Rage.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The Royal Party does at laſt retire,</l>
               <l>Makes its Retreat in Duſt, and Smoak, and Fire:</l>
               <l>So, after Twelve laborious noble Toils,</l>
               <l>Th' <hi>Olympic Heroe</hi> raves, and raving falls;</l>
               <l>On <hi>Oetas</hi> Mount his fatal Hour he found,</l>
               <l>He fell, with ruin'd Oaks, and ſtately Trees around.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <lg type="triplet">
                  <l>But ſtay, my Muſe, relate the blackeſt Scene</l>
                  <l>That yet the World e'er ſaw, or muſt again;</l>
                  <l>The Beſt of Kings, of Men ignobly ſlain.</l>
               </lg>
               <l>So the retreating Sun does diſappear,</l>
               <l>And gilds with bloody Streaks the Hemiſphere.</l>
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:46801:13"/>
               <l>The drowſie Poppy ſhrivel'd up his Head,</l>
               <l>Droop'd at the Sight, and in a Sleep fell dead:</l>
               <lg type="triplet">
                  <l>Th' aſtoniſh'd Herds o'er all the Plains did rove,</l>
                  <l>And in diſorder'd Terrors told their Love;</l>
                  <l>The Echo's moan'd and ſigh'd in ev'ry Grove.</l>
               </lg>
               <l>No Laurels now wou'd in <hi>Britannia</hi> ſtand,</l>
               <l>But Woods of Cypreſs crowd in ev'ry Hand:</l>
               <l>Heav'ns Eye, as tho' aſham'd to ſee the Sight,</l>
               <l>In Royal Azure mourn'd, and skreen'd the Light:</l>
               <l>The Chriſtian <hi>Heroe</hi> fell their Sacrifice;</l>
               <l>What Expiatory Off'ring can ſuffice?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>A Train of captiv'd Martyrs now ſucceed,</l>
               <l>A Loyal Guard does with their Sov'reign bleed:</l>
               <l>So Days bright Lord does from our Sight retire,</l>
               <l>Sinks in Abyſs of Night, and all its Beams expire.</l>
               <l>Too brave, too juſt for Crimes, theſe Nobles fall,</l>
               <l>And on that barb'rous Age a Bluſh entail.</l>
               <l>Our Prelates hurry'd to untimely End,</l>
               <l>Their injur'd Lord, and theſe great Minds attend,</l>
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:46801:14"/>
               <l>They ſtain with flowing Blood the guilty Stage,</l>
               <l>And, <hi>Stephen</hi>-like, forgive the impious Age.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>One Victim's ſlaughter'd from the Eagle's Neſt,</l>
               <l>Daring and as Heroick as the Beſt;</l>
               <l>Too noble Thoughts poſſeſs'd his Warlike Soul,</l>
               <l>To join the Scepter with the Brewer's Bowl:</l>
               <l>He fell bemoan'd in an unhallow'd Town,</l>
               <l>Like the Great Martyr he his Blood laid down.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>One Worthy let our Numbers recommend,</l>
               <l>True to his King, his Country, and his Friend.</l>
               <l>This <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Soldier in the Heat of War</l>
               <l>Was both to <hi>Mars,</hi> and to <hi>Apollo</hi> dear;</l>
               <l>His Learning and his Courage did afford</l>
               <l>An equal Aid, he fought with Pen and Sword.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Rome</hi> and <hi>Geneva</hi> were alike to him,</l>
               <l>The Foes were adequate, alike the Theme.</l>
               <l>Let <hi>Latham</hi> be a Witneſs of his Fame,</l>
               <l>And <hi>Bolton</hi> tremble at his awful Name.</l>
               <l>The ſurly Foe beſieg'd a Country-houſe,</l>
               <l>A <hi>Heroine</hi> and <hi>Heroe</hi> they encloſe:</l>
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:46801:14"/>
               <l>The Walls were ſlender, and the Works but young;</l>
               <l>But all within was Proof, and all was ſtrong:</l>
               <l>They ſhelter'd all beneath his Warlike Care,</l>
               <l>The Garriſon ne'er trembl'd at the War:</l>
               <l>The Soldiers few, yet faithful to their Head;</l>
               <l>They knew no Odds, when his great Conduct led.</l>
               <l>A noiſie Mortar did loud Ruine threat,</l>
               <l>And in the Air proclaim'd approaching Fate:</l>
               <l>No known Defence cou'd guard th' impending Blow,</l>
               <l>It ſcatter'd ſure Deſtruction all below.</l>
               <l>He ſallies, and the bold Invader flies,</l>
               <l>Within the Gates he bears the raviſh'd Prize;</l>
               <l>Succeeding actions ſtill advance his Fame,</l>
               <l>He in Immortal Annals bears a Name.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Who can diſtinguiſh what is Good or Ill,</l>
               <l>Where Law's eſtabliſh'd by a boundleſs Will?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Obſerve what Conſequences now attend:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Preceding Ills ſucceeding Faults ne'er mend.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>As only one Abſurdity allow'd,</l>
               <l>You'll ſtreight diſcloſe a long depending Crowd.</l>
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:46801:15"/>
               <l>Theſe <hi>Romiſh Tools</hi> now vaunt the Field their own,</l>
               <l>Their ſcatter'd <hi>Trophies</hi> are the Church &amp; Throne;</l>
               <l>Involv'd in Guilt, and all defil'd with Gore,</l>
               <l>They teach the World ſtrange Crimes, unlearn'd before:</l>
               <l>Mercy it ſelf cou'd no Forgiveneſs own,</l>
               <l>It bluſh'd a Pardon for ſuch Crimes unknown,</l>
               <l>Till then unknown, till thoſe unhappy Days,</l>
               <l>When Yew and Cypreſs juſtl'd out the Bays.</l>
               <l>No other Means their Counſels can propoſe</l>
               <l>Of Safety, but the Ruine of their Foes;</l>
               <l>A thorow Extirpation is decreed,</l>
               <l>Each Individual of the Whole muſt bleed.</l>
               <l>This Reformation muſt the Land atone,</l>
               <l>Stand ſtill, or to retreat, they're ſure to be undone.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>What cou'd Young <hi>Caeſar</hi> in this Juncture do?</l>
               <l>No Humane Strength cou'd match th'inſulting Foe;</l>
               <l>His Loyal Friends in ſad Effigie lay,</l>
               <l>The diſmal Ruins of a routed Day:</l>
               <l>Some faithful Few with him to Exile fly,</l>
               <l>And wait a more propitious Deſtiny;</l>
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:46801:15"/>
               <l>They leave the Iſle, and truſt to Seas and Wind,</l>
               <l>To Seas than Rebels were at home more kind.</l>
               <l>From this forc'd Flight we date ſucceeding Woes,</l>
               <l>Which Time in After-ages will diſcloſe.</l>
               <l>What dreaded Dangers theſe wild Zealots fear'd,</l>
               <l>And all the Brain-ſick <hi>Babels</hi> they had rear'd,</l>
               <l>Diſtracted Notions of returning <hi>Rome,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And how a boundleſs Sway deſign'd their Doom,</l>
               <l>Theſe Terrors all, by this ill Fact alone,</l>
               <l>They antidate, and make them all their own;</l>
               <l>On unborn Tribes th'entail a woful Fate,</l>
               <l>Their Teeth are edg'd w<hi rend="sup">th</hi> Grapes their Fathers eat.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>Achates</hi> now was in his Bloom of Years,</l>
               <l>Had run thro' all the Stages of the Wars;</l>
               <l>The Valiant Youth by daring <hi>Caeſar</hi>'s Side</l>
               <l>In Battels oft, and Sieges, had been try'd;</l>
               <l>By Land, or Sea, no Danger cou'd ſubdue;</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Achates</hi> faithful was, to <hi>Caeſar</hi>'s Intereſt true.</l>
               <l>He left the Iſle with his retreating Lord,</l>
               <l>And try'd more hoſpitable Coaſts abroad.</l>
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:46801:16"/>
               <l>The <hi>Genius</hi> quits the Land; a ſad Preſage,</l>
               <l>An <hi>Omen</hi> boading Ill unto the Age.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>With Joy tranſported, hateful <hi>Rome</hi> ſurveys</l>
               <l>Our Civil Broils, and bleſs'd th' inhumane Days:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Ignatius</hi> Brood was to their Maſter dear,</l>
               <l>Thoſe impious, tragick Inſtruments of War;</l>
               <l>An Order now eſtabliſh'd and enroll'd,</l>
               <l>Like Comets beaming Miſchief to the World:</l>
               <l>What Joys did not their Expectations yield,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Romes</hi> Granaries with <hi>Albions</hi> Harveſt fill'd!</l>
               <l>Already in <hi>Idea</hi> they embrace</l>
               <l>The Land, and re-aſſume their Ancient Place;</l>
               <l>'Twas nearer than a Poſſibility,</l>
               <l>They had the full Aſſurance in their Eye:</l>
               <l>They've now a Game of vaſt import to play,</l>
               <l>This Caſt well manag'd wins a glorious Day.</l>
               <l>What ſubtile Machins for this End combine!</l>
               <l>They muſter all their Force, and in one Body join.</l>
               <l>With equal Joy <hi>Rome</hi> and the Rebels ſaw</l>
               <l>The Monarch baniſh'd, and the Sword the Law:</l>
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:46801:16"/>
               <l>Yet diff'rent Aims theſe preſent Joys attend,</l>
               <l>Alike tho' pleas'd, yet oppoſite the End.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Ajax</hi> at home claims All to be his own,</l>
               <l>Profanes with vulgar Mud the raviſh'd Throne,</l>
               <l>Defies the Int'reſt of a wand'ring Prince,</l>
               <l>Bankrupt he's loſt, for ever baniſh'd thence;</l>
               <l>The <hi>Baſis</hi> deep, a daring Pile he rears,</l>
               <l>The Crown's Entail'd for endleſs rouling Years.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>But other Movements did <hi>Romes</hi> Joys create,</l>
               <l>She laughs at this Mock-Pageantry of State,</l>
               <l>Another Proſpect charms her roving Eye,</l>
               <l>She careleſs ſaw this mimick'd Majeſty,</l>
               <l>Already ſaw the bold Uſurper down,</l>
               <l>Foreſaw on <hi>Caeſar</hi>'s Head the rifl'd Crown;</l>
               <l>She ey'd the Prince forlorn on Foreign Coaſts,</l>
               <l>Ev'n to himſelf, and to his Country loſt,</l>
               <l>In Spring of Youth, and Bloſſom of his Years,</l>
               <l>Scarce early Down upon his Face appears;</l>
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:46801:17"/>
               <lg type="triplet">
                  <l>A proper Seaſon this to be embrac'd,</l>
                  <l>To ſtamp her Doctrines on his eaſie Breaſt,</l>
                  <l>And raze all other Principles impreſt:</l>
               </lg>
               <l>She view'd his Friends that round his Perſon ſtand,</l>
               <l>They're Nobles all, or Chiefs that rule the Land:</l>
               <l>This Goal ſhe aims, and this contended Prize,</l>
               <l>This Game the Thoughts of crafty <hi>Rome</hi> employs.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Her Temples now with gawdy Luſter ſhine,</l>
               <l>And ſplendid Beauties deck each artful Shrine;</l>
               <l>Her graceful Paint exalted Colours ſhew,</l>
               <l>By <hi>Titian</hi>'s Pencial drawn, or <hi>Angelo;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Her Altars all Imperial did appear,</l>
               <l>And Tuneful Lays invite the raviſh'd Ear;</l>
               <l>Her Prieſts in Robes beyond a <hi>Tyrian</hi> Dye</l>
               <l>Their Rites perform, and awful court the Eye;</l>
               <l>All that con'd pleaſe, or cou'd allure the Senſe,</l>
               <l>With utmoſt Pomp and Grandeur they diſpenſe.</l>
               <l>Her next Advance is to pervert his Mind,</l>
               <l>A <hi>Medium</hi> for the Project ſhe deſign'd;</l>
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:46801:17"/>
               <l>She whiſpers to his Thoughts his Countries Crimes</l>
               <l>And aggravates the Miſchiefs of the Times,</l>
               <l>The ſad Effects of Civil Broils runs o'er,</l>
               <l>Draws bluſhing Lines with his dead Father's Gore;</l>
               <l>She repreſents the <hi>Hydra</hi> of the Land</l>
               <l>A monſtrous Beaſt, untam'd to all Command;</l>
               <l>That daily new blaſphemous Heads appear,</l>
               <l>And all around with wild Deſtruction tear;</l>
               <l>Th' eſtabliſh'd Church enervate grown, and weak,</l>
               <l>A riſing Faction cou'd deſtroy, or break;</l>
               <l>Its <hi>Canons</hi> were not Proof againſt its Foes,</l>
               <l>Its <hi>Baſis</hi> mean, did the whole Work expoſe.</l>
               <l>Cou'd ſuch a Fabrick be from Wrongs ſecure?</l>
               <l>Cou'd it tempeſtuous Shocks of Storms endure?</l>
               <l>When its Foundation's not on Rock, but Sand,</l>
               <l>Its Fall was ſure, its Ruine now at Hand;</l>
               <l>Theſe Troubles from the firſt Reformers ſpring,</l>
               <l>They were but Tools to an incenſed King;</l>
               <l>From lawleſs Luſt the Quarrel firſt began,</l>
               <l>Succeeding Int'reſt now the War maintains.</l>
               <pb n="32" facs="tcp:46801:18"/>
               <l>They never can a Pious Union know,</l>
               <l>Whilſt Holy Church is treated as a Foe.</l>
               <l>Look round, obſerve our ſtrict Conformity;</l>
               <l>All Schiſm we and factious Zeal defie:</l>
               <l>In diſtant Regions the ſame Faith we own,</l>
               <l>One Mother-Church, and one Religion known.</l>
               <l>The <hi>Pope</hi> is not that Brute they repreſent,</l>
               <l>His Call is Sacred ſure, from Heav'n he's ſent;</l>
               <l>He does not make a King a Scepter'd Slave,</l>
               <l>He ne'er deſtroys the Right that Nature gave;</l>
               <l>The Civil Rights he leaves in Truſt with them,</l>
               <l>In Matters Sacred only he's Supreme.</l>
               <l>And this Commiſſion was tranſmitted down</l>
               <l>To him from <hi>Peter,</hi> by th' Almighty's Son.</l>
               <l>Come, injur'd Prince, return to us once more,</l>
               <l>Our alter'd Sons bring back, again reſtore</l>
               <l>Its ancient Rule to your revolted Land,</l>
               <l>And know your Pow'r again, and once again command.</l>
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:46801:18"/>
               <l>One People then in one known Faith you'll rule,</l>
               <l>And all your Rebels monſtrous Gods controul:</l>
               <l>A Train of Gods as num'rous they adore</l>
               <l>As all the Heathen <hi>Pagods</hi> were before;</l>
               <l>Their ſawcy Zeal will urge the King to yield,</l>
               <l>Command his Bow to ev'ry Form they build;</l>
               <l>Or elſe for Arms the jangling Beaſts prepare,</l>
               <l>And 'gainſt the Throne proclaim Confed'rate War.</l>
               <l>Our Treaſures ſhall aſſiſt you in your Cauſe,</l>
               <l>To gain your Native Rights, the blaſted Laws;</l>
               <l>Your <hi>Albion</hi> ſhall be famous as of old,</l>
               <l>And your Illuſtrious Acts in future Annals told.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>What cannot Words effect in youthful Minds,</l>
               <l>Where want of Power pleads, and promis'd Succor blinds?</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Rome</hi> knows how beſt to perfect Holineſs,</l>
               <l>When e'er ſhe finds a Monarch in diſtreſs:</l>
               <l>It is not Faith can reach St. <hi>Peter</hi>'s Key,</l>
               <l>Diſtreſs directs the Prince the narrow Way;</l>
               <l>For Kings with eaſe aſcend the Heav'nly Throne,</l>
               <l>Whilſt they poſſeſs and boldly keep their own.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb n="34" facs="tcp:46801:19"/>
               <l>Our <hi>Caeſar</hi> cou'd have anſwer'd every Head,</l>
               <l>Cou'd have retorted to each Plea they made:</l>
               <l>Their Doctrines were not, nor their Arts unknown,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Britannia</hi> had well taught her darling Son;</l>
               <l>She ſcorn'd like Muſhrom-births her Sons to breed,</l>
               <l>Confin'd to partial Authors as their <hi>Creed:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>A Latitude ſhe gives, a Noble Field,</l>
               <l>Inform your ſelf, and teach the Foe to yield.</l>
               <l>Her Truths in bright Meridian Luſter ſhine,</l>
               <l>Seek no Retreat, for Truth is all Divine:</l>
               <l>Howe'er reſolv'd, he wiſely ſhuns Debate,</l>
               <l>In pious Silence waits his alter'd Fate.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Yet neither to accuſe him, nor defend,</l>
               <l>Theſe Conſequences their ill Arts attend;</l>
               <l>He cou'd not but behold with youthful Fire</l>
               <l>Theſe luring Beams of Greatneſs, and admire;</l>
               <l>He does with equal Bent of Humane Kind</l>
               <l>Make ſtrict Enquiries to inform the Mind.</l>
               <l>The Humane Soul Variety purſues,</l>
               <l>We all, <hi>Athenian</hi>-like, ſtill ask for News:</l>
               <pb n="35" facs="tcp:46801:19"/>
               <l>Beſides the Pleaſures that enveagle Senſe,</l>
               <l>Their kind Deportments to an exil'd Prince,</l>
               <l>His preſſing Wants luxurious they ſupply,</l>
               <l>He cou'd not think to ask what they'd deny:</l>
               <l>Theſe things cou'd not with careleſs eyes be view'd,</l>
               <l>They muſt command a common Gratitude;</l>
               <l>Thus <hi>Caeſar</hi> ſtood not wholly loſt to <hi>Rome,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Yet cou'd not Conqueſt boaſt, nor was he overcom.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>But young <hi>Caeſario</hi> was of ſofter Make,</l>
               <l>Too ſoon, alas! th' envenom'd Bait he takes,</l>
               <l>Their ſoothing Arts upon his Youth impoſe,</l>
               <l>He falls a pity'd Victim to his Foes:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Rome</hi> eager hugs this Darling of a Prize,</l>
               <l>He falls an eaſie, innocent Sacrifice.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Britannia</hi>'s Hopes were blaſted in the Youth,</l>
               <l>Too lately learn'd, too ſoon he quits the Truth;</l>
               <l>For ever loſt to her, he's all their own,</l>
               <l>And dates ſucceeding Troubles on the Throne.</l>
               <l>She ſhak'd her Head at this unwelcome Day,</l>
               <l>And mourn'd to ſee the Royal Youth a Prey;</l>
               <pb n="36" facs="tcp:46801:20"/>
               <l>Foreſaw him mount, and tumble from his Throne,</l>
               <l>Foreſaw new bloody Broils amongſt her Sons;</l>
               <l>Beyond Prevention the Diſeaſe goes on,</l>
               <l>Nothing but <hi>Albious</hi> Blood can <hi>Abions</hi> Crimes atone.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>Rome</hi> with redoubl'd Crafts repeats her Blows,</l>
               <l>And ſtrange Infection all around ſhe throws:</l>
               <l>Juſt as <hi>Caeſario</hi> fell, ſome Nobles fall;</l>
               <l>The ſame Allurements them as him enthrall:</l>
               <l>But yet, to give <hi>Achates</hi> what's his Due,</l>
               <l>He ſaw, unſhaken, all this pompous Shew;</l>
               <l>In vain their ſly Temptations ſtorm his Mind,</l>
               <l>He was for greater Ends by Fate deſign'd;</l>
               <l>He was to give in greateſt Troubles Aid,</l>
               <l>When Ruine threatn'd, and loud Storms invade:</l>
               <l>He on theſe fixt Decrees compos'd above</l>
               <l>Still kept his Eye, and only courted <hi>Jove.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>At length the Stars, propitious all, combine,</l>
               <l>And for our <hi>Albion</hi>'s great Deliv'rance join;</l>
               <l>Their Influence drops a ſure approaching Fate,</l>
               <l>And to bold <hi>Ajax</hi>'s Rule conſigns a Date.</l>
               <pb n="37" facs="tcp:46801:20"/>
               <l>A poyſonous Guſt out of a gloomy Den,</l>
               <l>Where the Suns gilded Beams had never been;</l>
               <l>Scren'd all the Air in its Meridian Light,</l>
               <l>And turn'd the azure Day to ſable Night,</l>
               <lg type="triplet">
                  <l>On ratling Wings deſtructive Whirlwinds roar,</l>
                  <l>A Storm a Stranger to the Iſle before,</l>
                  <l>Bears the Uſurper to the <hi>Stygian</hi> Shore.</l>
               </lg>
               <l>Trees all around with kind'ling light'ning Fire,</l>
               <l>In Storms he liv'd, in Thunder he expires,</l>
               <l>Amaz'd his Party ſtood, th'aſtoniſh'd Iſle,</l>
               <l>In ſtrange Convulſions ſtagger'd for a while;</l>
               <l>Untaught diſtraction reigns in ev'ry Face,</l>
               <l>Their Eyes with wild diſtorted glowings blaze.</l>
               <l>Senſe cou'd not their diſorder'd Thoughts controul,</l>
               <l>The Chaos cou'd not be reduc'd to Rule;</l>
               <l>Their ſtrugling Atoms, like <hi>Lucretius</hi> World,</l>
               <l>For a long time into no Order whirl'd;</l>
               <l>At laſt they jump'd into a giddy Form,</l>
               <l>And mount a Soul that wants a Royal turn;</l>
               <pb n="38" facs="tcp:46801:21"/>
               <l>
                  <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lyſſes</hi> from the Northern Marſhes came,</l>
               <l>Fatigu'd his Squadrons, and unknown his Aim,</l>
               <l>He ſtems this Tide, and this impetuous Flood,</l>
               <l>Our hopes were anſwer'd all, the Man was good,</l>
               <l>They ſaw too late their Error in the choice,</l>
               <l>And call for <hi>Caeſar</hi> with a general Voice.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Ajax</hi>'s fierce Troops that knew not how to fly,</l>
               <l>Or us'd to Conqueſt, or were taught to die,</l>
               <l>Stun'd w<hi rend="sup">th</hi> their guilt, their <hi>weapons</hi> cou'd not weild,</l>
               <l>But quit their Trophies, and the boaſted Field,</l>
               <l>Unanimous for <hi>Caeſar</hi> all declare,</l>
               <l>Reflect with Grief on a diſhoneſt War.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Now <hi>Caeſar</hi> comes on Board, the <hi>Nereids</hi> play</l>
               <l>About the Ship, and wanton in the Sea;</l>
               <l>Young Cupids fan him with their Wings above,</l>
               <l>And with their Breezes whiſper Tales of Love;</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Neptune</hi> conducts the Veſſel to the Shore;</l>
               <l>He had confin'd the unruly Storms before,</l>
               <l>But ſends ſoft <hi>Zephyr</hi>'s Gales to wing his way,</l>
               <l>Curl on the Waves, and with the Streamers play.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb n="39" facs="tcp:46801:21"/>
               <l>The Hero now ſteps on th' expecting Strand,</l>
               <l>The Hearts of all his People he commands;</l>
               <l>Their grateful Shouts fill all the ambient Air,</l>
               <l>Redouble, and produce new Thunder there:</l>
               <l>An Army ready in a brave array,</l>
               <l>Their poliſh'd Arms add luſtre to the Day,</l>
               <l>They're faithful all, and fearleſs of a Foe,</l>
               <l>Where-ever <hi>Caeſar</hi> bids to March they go.</l>
               <l>Profuſe our Conduits run with ſparkling Wine,</l>
               <l>We almoſt quite exhauſt the gen'rous Vine;</l>
               <l>Eternal Healths compoſe an endleſs Ring,</l>
               <l>Perpetual Voices cry, <hi>God ſave the King.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>Caeſar</hi> does now with native Glories ſhine,</l>
               <l>No borrow'd Beams adorn the Royal Line;</l>
               <lg type="triplet">
                  <l>Beneath his Feet his proſtrate Rebels bow,</l>
                  <l>The Church and State in their old Channels flow,</l>
                  <l>And once again their lawful Sovereign know.</l>
               </lg>
               <l>So when loud Storms deſert the ruffl'd Seas,</l>
               <l>The raging Billows are again at peace,</l>
               <pb n="40" facs="tcp:46801:22"/>
               <l>They mildly ſettle as the Winds retreat,</l>
               <l>With weakned force the hardy Shores they beat,</l>
               <l>Serene the Trident Rules the pleaſant Main,</l>
               <l>The Surface all is Calm, and ſmiles again.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Cou'd Mankind pry into the Book of Fate,</l>
               <l>And in it here and there exchange a Date,</l>
               <l>This Happineſs had ſurely been entail'd</l>
               <l>On us, and ours, or Fate it ſelf had fail'd.</l>
               <l>As much of Bliſs as human Souls can know,</l>
               <l>As much as Organs can receive below,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Britannia</hi> now enjoys. —</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Tell me, my Muſe, where the Miſcarriage lies,</l>
               <l>Without the <hi>Codex</hi> of the diſtant Skies;</l>
               <l>Too obvious the Poyſon does appear,</l>
               <l>It ſcatters ſad Contagion thro' the Air;</l>
               <l>We need not dive too deep, nor ſoar too high,</l>
               <l>It ſhows it ſelf to each enquiring Eye.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>Caeſar</hi> was now to manly Vigour grown,</l>
               <l>And ſate unrival'd on his native Throne;</l>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:46801:22"/>
               <l>But in himſelf his Species was confin'd,</l>
               <l>No Propagation of a Royal Kind,</l>
               <l>Latent they reſt, as Seeds in Chaos lay,</l>
               <l>E're primitive Matter had produc'd a Day.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>In Cloſe Cabals <hi>Rome</hi> does her Meaſures take,</l>
               <l>How to direct, and manage well this Stake.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Caeſar</hi> at beſt a wavering Faith did ſhow,</l>
               <l>He neither was a certain Friend nor Foe;</l>
               <l>His Church was re-inſtated as before,</l>
               <l>But of <hi>Rome</hi>'s Claims he nothing did reſtore;</l>
               <l>The ſlowneſs of his Steps ſhe cou'd not bear,</l>
               <l>The young <hi>Caeſario</hi> now is all her Care;</l>
               <l>Was <hi>Caeſar</hi> rightly match'd, a coming Son,</l>
               <l>Wou'd quite exclude her ripening Hopes the Throne,</l>
               <l>She then might yield the Game, her Harveſt loſt,</l>
               <l>Like Veſſels daſh'd and Shipwrack'd on the Coaſt;</l>
               <l>She every Model tries, at length does rear,</l>
               <l>A riſing Fabrick anſwering all her Care;</l>
               <pb n="42" facs="tcp:46801:23"/>
               <l>Too ſtrong her Faction did at Court prevail,</l>
               <l>It was beyond <hi>Achates</hi> Power to heal.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The Royal Choice does on the Billows ride,</l>
               <l>And now to <hi>Caeſar</hi>'s Arms preſent the Bride:</l>
               <l>But ah! th' unhappy Soil was barren grown,</l>
               <l>Like fruitleſs <hi>Libya</hi> ſcorch'd by too much Sun.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Caeſar</hi>'s Endeavours and our Hopes were vain,</l>
               <l>The ungrateful Glebe makes no returns again.</l>
               <l>No pregnant Show'rs cou'd urge a ſmiling Bloom,</l>
               <l>No ripen'd Sheafs by all the Tillage come.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>But this defect was not on <hi>Caeſar</hi>'s ſide;</l>
               <l>'Twas not his Fault this Bleſſing was deny'd.</l>
               <l>For other Mothers did the Nation grace,</l>
               <l>With numerous Births and worthy <hi>Caeſar</hi>'s Race;</l>
               <l>One pity'd Son compos'd of too much flame,</l>
               <l>His Thoughts too Royal, too ſublime his Aim,</l>
               <l>With daring Pinions ſoar'd too nigh the Sun,</l>
               <l>Sing'd in his Beams, he fell and was undone.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>For young <hi>Caeſario</hi> a fit Mate was found,</l>
               <l>Ten Thouſand quiver'd Cupids learn to wound.</l>
               <pb n="43" facs="tcp:46801:23"/>
               <l>Tho' Royalty did in her Birth not ſhine,</l>
               <l>The Father ſtill enobles all the Line.</l>
               <l>And now <hi>Britannia</hi>'s hopes were center'd here,</l>
               <l>New dawning Joys to future Times appear,</l>
               <l>How vain are all th'Efforts of human kind!</l>
               <l>How many wild Projections are deſign'd!</l>
               <l>In Fates dark Legends how unread is Man,</l>
               <l>Loſt in the Dusk, he makes eſſays in vain,</l>
               <l>At her own Weapons worſted <hi>Rome</hi> falls down,</l>
               <l>Which after Generations will make known.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Prudent <hi>Achates</hi> with himſelf Debates,</l>
               <l>Wiſely to play this After-Game of State.</l>
               <lg type="triplet">
                  <l>The Royal Iſſue's his peculiar Care;</l>
                  <l>He was of all the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Wiles aware,</l>
                  <l>And with unerring Judgment ſcap'd the Snare.</l>
               </lg>
               <l>He urg'd the gen'ral Council of the Land,</l>
               <l>Early to conſtitute a faithful Band,</l>
               <l>A Guard reform'd might their young years improve</l>
               <l>And for th' eſtabliſh'd Church engage their Love;</l>
               <pb n="44" facs="tcp:46801:24"/>
               <l>Our Learned Prelates in the Task engage,</l>
               <l>And fence theſe tender Blooms from <hi>Romiſh</hi> Rage,</l>
               <l>Nor cou'd a Father's powerful Arts withdraw,</l>
               <l>Religion is above Paternal Awe;</l>
               <l>The Snakes thus periſh'd by <hi>Alcmena</hi>'s Boy,</l>
               <l>He in the Cradle <hi>Juno</hi>'s Rage deſtroys,</l>
               <l>So <hi>Rome</hi> was baffl'd, and her Projects croſt,</l>
               <l>And all her Hopes in theſe fair Bloſſoms loſt,</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>But ſhe's too reſty to be thus o'ercome,</l>
               <l>A bolder ſtroke ſhe bids a daring Doom,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Antaeus</hi> like, tho' foil'd, ſhe bounds from Earth,</l>
               <l>And with the Fall renews both ſtrength and breath.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The Jeſuits in Conſultation joyn,</l>
               <l>Dare they profane that Name with ſuch deſigns!</l>
               <l>Strait to their Aid they all the Furies call,</l>
               <l>T'aſſiſt them in the Ruine of the whole;</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Chameleon</hi> like in ev'ry Shape they're found,</l>
               <l>Lurking in cloſe diſguiſe they aim to wound.</l>
               <l>Flames, Envy, Murther, in their Breaſts recoil,</l>
               <l>In ev'ry Vein their furious Paſſions boil,</l>
               <pb n="45" facs="tcp:46801:24"/>
               <l>Eager they carry on this grand Debate,</l>
               <l>How to ſecure themſelves and fix a Seat.</l>
               <l>Then thus they argue —</l>
               <l>If e'er our Arts for Mother Church prevail,</l>
               <l>We muſt their whole united Pow'rs aſſail;</l>
               <l>For if we ſpare a part, the ſtubborn Crew,</l>
               <l>Like <hi>Hydra</hi>'s Heads, ſtill as they're lop'd will grow.</l>
               <lg type="triplet">
                  <l>High as the Pyramids let's raiſe each Pile,</l>
                  <l>On which the baneful Hereticks muſt broil;</l>
                  <l>And with theſe cover all <hi>Britannia</hi>'s Iſle,</l>
               </lg>
               <lg type="triplet">
                  <l>No other Clouds ſhall darken then the Skies,</l>
                  <l>But thoſe which from our hallow'd Fires ariſe,</l>
                  <l>This only will compleat the Sacrifice.</l>
               </lg>
               <l>Were theſe the Doctrines <hi>Jeſus</hi> did declare?</l>
               <l>Or recommended to th' Apoſtles here?</l>
               <l>Sure all he Taught was more Divine and Good,</l>
               <l>His Tenets never were defil'd with Blood,</l>
               <l>His Blood ſufficient for more World's than theſe,</l>
               <l>It did for Sin th' Almighty's Wrath appeaſe;</l>
               <pb n="46" facs="tcp:46801:25"/>
               <l>For loſt Mankind his ſacred Drops ſuffice,</l>
               <l>A Chriſtians Blood to him's an Impious Sacrifice.</l>
               <l>But they defie all Laws of God and Man,</l>
               <l>A contradictory <hi>Theſis</hi> they maintain.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>They caſt their Eyes on their moſt Chriſtian Son,</l>
               <l>A Bigot he by Birth, he's all their own,</l>
               <l>He had not Will or Pow'r to retreat,</l>
               <l>From <hi>Rome</hi>'s proud Laſh, 'twas not decreed by Fate;</l>
               <l>Some weak Endeavours by his Subjects try'd,</l>
               <l>Were baffl'd all, they fell the weaker ſide,</l>
               <l>How can the People act without a King?</l>
               <l>Their giddy Thoughts a vaſt diſorder bring;</l>
               <l>They found him all Imperial for their Aim,</l>
               <l>A warlike Soul he bore and courted Fame.</l>
               <l>His zeal for Mother-Church was ſtrong and good,</l>
               <l>His Youth was ripen'd with his Subjects Blood.</l>
               <l>Rough Perſecution thro' his Kingdom flies,</l>
               <l>Whoe'er's a Foe to <hi>Rome</hi> muſt turn or die;</l>
               <l>His wandring Vaſſals leave their cruel Home,</l>
               <l>And all around to neighbouring Countries roam,</l>
               <pb n="47" facs="tcp:46801:25"/>
               <l>Such bloody Decalogues he does declare,</l>
               <l>More terrible than <hi>Sinai</hi>'s Thunders were.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Their Aims were now this Champion to eſpouſe,</l>
               <l>Confirm him ſtrong, to Rival all their Foes;</l>
               <l>And when their Projects had acquir'd an Head,</l>
               <l>And mighty <hi>Caeſar</hi> number'd with the Dead,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Caeſario</hi> might a potent Succour find,</l>
               <l>For all the Revolutions he deſign'd:</l>
               <l>They by their Force united might deſtroy,</l>
               <l>The hated, ſtubborn, Northern Hereſie.</l>
               <l>Too eaſie Means they found to gain their Ends,</l>
               <l>Some <hi>Britains</hi> falſe to us, to them were Friends;</l>
               <l>Their ready Tools prepar'd aſſiſtance bring,</l>
               <l>Falſe to their Faith, their Country, and their King.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>We held a Bulwark near the briny Tide,</l>
               <l>Our <hi>Albion</hi>'s Strength, her Glory, and her Pride;</l>
               <l>This Fortreſs curb'd the Pow'r of <hi>Gallic</hi> Kings,</l>
               <l>A certain refuge for our Canvas Wings.</l>
               <l>Here mighty Piles of <hi>Britiſh</hi> Bones you ſee,</l>
               <l>High as the Pyramids in <hi>Egypt</hi> be,</l>
               <pb n="48" facs="tcp:46801:26"/>
               <l>Which our bold Soldiers for their Country loſt,</l>
               <l>And joyn'd the Continent to <hi>Albion</hi>'s Coaſt.</l>
               <l>The <hi>Gauls</hi> cou'd never, were this Hold our own,</l>
               <l>Inſult the Ocean with their <hi>Riſing-Sun:</hi>
               </l>
               <lg type="triplet">
                  <l>We then unrival'd might Command the Main,</l>
                  <l>Old hoary <hi>Neptune</hi> and his Sea-born Train,</l>
                  <l>Wou'd court no Friend but the <hi>Royal-Sovereign.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <l>Their trembling Ports might hear our Cannon roar,</l>
               <l>Rage thro' the Land, and reach the frighted Loure.</l>
               <l>This Bulwark's yielded to the aſpiring Foe,</l>
               <l>For a ſinall Cargo brought from <hi>Mexico.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>This raviſh'd Prize from large <hi>Iberia</hi> torn,</l>
               <l>Does now the <hi>Gallick</hi> Diadem adorn.</l>
               <l>What Man cou'd do <hi>Achates</hi> did perform,</l>
               <l>Prov'd all his Int'reſt to divert the Storm.</l>
               <l>He repreſented to the Court the Shame,</l>
               <l>Of Injur'd Honour, and our tarniſh'd Fame;</l>
               <l>How little it wou'd look to Foreign Kings,</l>
               <l>Beſides the preſent Miſchief that it brings.</l>
               <pb n="49" facs="tcp:46801:26"/>
               <lg type="triplet">
                  <l>What Folly 'twas to Arm, ſo near, a Foe,</l>
                  <l>This certain, this well-manag'd Game to throw</l>
                  <l>Away, diſtracted Conduct it wou'd ſhow.</l>
               </lg>
               <l>If in the <hi>Gallic</hi> Scale this Weight we lay,</l>
               <l>It wou'd <hi>Britannia</hi>'s Ballance quite out-weigh.</l>
               <l>The Diſadvantage doubles on our ſide,</l>
               <l>Our Strength is weaken'd, and the Foe ſupply'd.</l>
               <l>All Arguments he urg'd the Theme cou'd bear,</l>
               <l>He urg'd in vain, for <hi>Caeſar</hi> wou'd not hear.</l>
               <l>Ah! who can dive into the Faults of Kings?</l>
               <l>But Ruine ſurely from ſuch Conduct ſprings.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Now, what returns can recompence this Day?</l>
               <l>This blooming Fortune, this auſpicious Prey?</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Gallia</hi> as grateful for this Point appears,</l>
               <l>As thoſe that pay a gratitude thro' fear,</l>
               <l>What e'er they give, th' Intentions to deſtroy,</l>
               <l>And ſend a Preſent with a baſe Alloy.</l>
               <l>Fair <hi>Julia</hi> comes, ſurrounded all with Charms,</l>
               <l>Ten Thouſand Cupids wait her with their Arms:</l>
               <pb n="50" facs="tcp:46801:27"/>
               <l>So <hi>Venus</hi> entertains the God of War,</l>
               <l>And all his Martial Terrors diſappear;</l>
               <l>This finiſh'd piece of Beauty and of Parts,</l>
               <l>Was worthy <hi>Caeſar</hi>'s Joys, and <hi>Gallia</hi>'s Arts.</l>
               <l>So <hi>Thracian</hi> Planets with deſtructive Beams,</l>
               <l>From gloomy Caves invite the Rural Swains,</l>
               <l>Whilſt they admire their Aſpects and Grandeur,</l>
               <l>Each Star becomes their Executioner.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>Rome</hi> now in Triumph bounds it o'er the Field,</l>
               <l>New ripening Joys ſucceeding Projects yield.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Caeſario</hi> is the ſole aſcendant grown,</l>
               <l>And points determin'd Meaſures to the Throne;</l>
               <l>To cloſe Cabals his active Friends reſort,</l>
               <l>They palm unjuſt Decrees upon the Court;</l>
               <l>Through all the Land their wild Chimera's fly,</l>
               <l>And court each lift'ning Ear, each eager Eye.</l>
               <l>Luxurious Vice corrupts the Fountain head,</l>
               <l>O'er all the Plains the troubl'd Waters ſpread.</l>
               <l>Nature with Largeſs gives abundant Store,</l>
               <l>We with voracious Luſts the Stock devour;</l>
               <pb n="51" facs="tcp:46801:27"/>
               <l>Affront the very Bleſſings Heav'n beſtows,</l>
               <l>Preſs on, and Sin, and antidate our Woes.</l>
               <l>No thoughts of Native Greatneſs court the Mind,</l>
               <l>Alter'd, we're grown a ſtrange degenerate kind,</l>
               <l>In bold Debauch contending to outvie,</l>
               <l>Whilſt uſeful Arts and Arms neglected lie.</l>
               <l>So Vice and Ruine rag'd thro' <hi>Iſrael</hi>'s Sons,</l>
               <l>Till <hi>Phinchas</hi> with bold Juſtice did atone.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>Achates</hi> ey'd the Miſchiefs of the Times,</l>
               <l>A Friend to <hi>Caeſar</hi> he, a Foe to Crimes.</l>
               <l>He did not tamely with the Torrent glide,</l>
               <l>But with wiſe Conduct bore againſt the Tide.</l>
               <l>He now well read in all the Crafts of State,</l>
               <l>Eſſays <hi>Rome</hi>'s Inundation to divert,</l>
               <l>And like a careful Pilot ſteady Steers;</l>
               <l>The Sails are manag'd with each Gale to veer;</l>
               <l>And tho' oppos'd by Storms, he's diſtant bore,</l>
               <l>He aims his Port, and urges to the Shore.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>He ſaw how <hi>Caeſar</hi> was diſſolv'd in Eaſe;</l>
               <l>No other but <hi>Caeſario</hi>'s Counſels pleaſe.</l>
               <pb n="52" facs="tcp:46801:28"/>
               <l>The Land compleat in Libertiniſm grown,</l>
               <l>Drew aukard Patterns from the erring Throne,</l>
               <l>That ev'ry Day our Rival's gather head,</l>
               <l>And by our own Contrivance potent made.</l>
               <l>The <hi>Gallic</hi> ſtrength to an amazing height</l>
               <l>Of Greatneſs grown, deſpis'd each neighbouring State,</l>
               <l>At pleaſure ſtoop'd and ſeiz'd th' unequal Prey,</l>
               <l>Thro' many conquer'd Countries cut its way.</l>
               <l>The Kingdom to unruly Ferment's grown,</l>
               <l>Forms different Parties ev'ry where at home,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Caeſario</hi>'s courted as the riſing Sun;</l>
               <l>By his, all other Factions were outdone:</l>
               <l>He ſaw a <hi>Belgic</hi> War ſeverely rage,</l>
               <l>Knew on what ſlender Grounds we did engage;</l>
               <l>Too well he knew the origine and riſe,</l>
               <l>To <hi>Rome</hi> and <hi>Gaul</hi> a grateful Sacrifice.</l>
               <l>The latter plays an <hi>Ambodexter</hi>'s Game,</l>
               <l>Yet ſeems t'eſpouſe the Quarrel on the Main,</l>
               <l>Views our Engagements, and retreats again.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb n="53" facs="tcp:46801:28"/>
               <l>Now Wars abroad, and Peſtilence at home,</l>
               <l>Rage, as if Heav'n it ſelf had ſign'd our Doom.</l>
               <l>Heaps upon heaps of putrid Corps lay dead,</l>
               <l>In ev'ry Street a gaſtly Landskip ſpread;</l>
               <l>Malignant Atoms in the Air abound,</l>
               <l>Inviſible the Fates, they ſilent wound;</l>
               <l>Yet angry Vengeance does purſue us higher,</l>
               <l>Puniſh'd by Sickneſs firſt, and then by Fire.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>A Tawny'd Light enfſam'd the kindl'd Air,</l>
               <l>And all the Stars in Bluſhes did appear;</l>
               <l>Vaſt Globes of rowling Flame aſcend on high,</l>
               <l>You'd think the Cyclops had engag'd the Sky,</l>
               <l>And from their ſcalding loud <hi>Aetnaean</hi> Forge,</l>
               <l>Did all their large Artillery diſgorge.</l>
               <l>An Heap confus'd the City now appear'd,</l>
               <l>Not e'en the Temples with their Altars ſpar'd;</l>
               <l>But once again more ſtately it revives,</l>
               <l>And from its Aſhes <hi>Phoenix</hi> like it lives.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb n="54" facs="tcp:46801:29"/>
               <l>
                  <hi>Achates</hi> to the War procures a Date,</l>
               <l>And ſtrives by Leagues to buttreſs up the State,</l>
               <l>To check the Grandeur of inſulting <hi>Gaul;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>For this he founds and rearsa triple Wall.</l>
               <l>Now <hi>Rome</hi> it ſelf in Politicks outdone,</l>
               <l>Curſes the Day, and this ſtrong Union mourns.</l>
               <l>Too well ſhe knew her darling Son too weak,</l>
               <l>By force of Arms this ſolemn Pact to break,</l>
               <l>Nor he, nor ſhe, nor her <hi>Caeſario</hi> more,</l>
               <l>Cou'd with dilated Pinions farther ſoar.</l>
               <l>This <hi>Gordian</hi> Knot, too firm and cloſely ty'd,</l>
               <l>She cou'd not looſe, nor knew ſhe to divide.</l>
               <l>She curſt the ſubtile Authors of this League,</l>
               <l>The cloſe Projectors of this dark Intrigue.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Now ev'ry Head was ſill'd with large employ,</l>
               <l>Vaſt were their Aims this Union to deſtroy:</l>
               <l>This Triple League they ſludy to confound;</l>
               <l>This League cemented with ſo ſtrict a Bond.</l>
               <l>Cloſe were theſe Arts of <hi>Rome,</hi> and deeply laid'</l>
               <l>If e'er Infallible in this, ſhe's made.</l>
               <pb n="55" facs="tcp:46801:29"/>
               <l>She to <hi>Caeſario</hi> comes, and ſummons all</l>
               <l>Her Miſſionaries to a dark Cabal:</l>
               <l>Then thus began —</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Too well, my Pious Son, you know the Fate,</l>
               <l>That calls us hither to this grand Debate.</l>
               <l>Too well the ſubtile Machines we diſcloſe,</l>
               <l>That thwart our Ends, and our Deſigns oppoſe.</l>
               <l>Thus far our great Endeavours have been vain,</l>
               <l>To bring loſt <hi>Albion</hi> to our ſelves again.</l>
               <l>The Hereticks out-wing us with Deſign,</l>
               <l>And with their impious Force Confederate join.</l>
               <l>A Triple Bulwark of the <hi>Northern</hi> Crowns,</l>
               <l>Checks all the Holy Meaſures we laid down.</l>
               <l>Who knows how ſoon Invaſion may be made?</l>
               <l>Encourag'd with Succeſs they will proceed;</l>
               <l>Urge <hi>Caeſar</hi> to revoke the Prize they've won,</l>
               <l>Or you, and I, and <hi>Gallia</hi> are undone.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>Caeſario</hi> anſwers with a Stateſman's Smile,</l>
               <l>Their Steps I will obſtruct, their Arts beguile.</l>
               <pb n="56" facs="tcp:46801:30"/>
               <l>Let <hi>Caeſar</hi>'s Change be my peculiar Care,</l>
               <l>I'll whiſper new Inſtructions in his Ear:</l>
               <l>And ſince the <hi>Britain</hi>'s raſhly ſtem my Aim,</l>
               <l>I'll own, and will avow for <hi>Rome</hi> my flame.</l>
               <l>Thro' <hi>Neptune</hi>'s wide Commands our <hi>Fleets</hi> ſhall go,</l>
               <l>And ferret our Confederate <hi>Northern</hi> Foe:</l>
               <l>And when theſe Pow'rs thus twiſted are deſtroy'd,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Albion</hi> can ne'er her dated Doom avoid;</l>
               <l>Thro' theſe forbidden Alps we'll cut our way,</l>
               <l>And late Poſterity ſhall bleſs the Day.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>They riſe, and to their Dividends reſort,</l>
               <l>Try all prevailing Parties at the Court,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Achates</hi> was eſſay'd, too juſt to yield,</l>
               <l>He cou'd not be perſwaded, nor compel'd,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Caeſario</hi> courts, <hi>Achates</hi> he denies;</l>
               <l>From hence his Indignation did ariſe.</l>
               <l>They're baffl'd, and ignobly quit the Ground,</l>
               <l>Their vain Efforts but ſmall Impreſſion found.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Caeſar</hi> unmov'd wou'd no Remonſtrance hear,</l>
               <l>To Winds they argu'd all, and courted Air.</l>
               <pb n="57" facs="tcp:46801:30"/>
               <l>Oh! had he but his Honour thus maintain'd,</l>
               <l>His Name ſucceeding Errors ne'er had ſtain'd;</l>
               <l>His wond'rous Deeds all Pandects wou'd rehearſe,</l>
               <l>He'd challeng'd an Eternity in Verſe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>But one important Caſt they've yet to play,</l>
               <l>A ſtrong reſerve remains to win the Day.</l>
               <l>A ſplendid Feaſt prepar'd adorns the Board,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Julia</hi> to this invites her Captiv'd Lord.</l>
               <l>Nature and Art, profuſely met, combine,</l>
               <l>To manage well this laſt and great Deſign.</l>
               <l>All Delicacies brought by Land or Seas,</l>
               <l>Or Air, invite each Senſe, and learn to pleaſe.</l>
               <l>They raviſh cluſters from the generous Vine,</l>
               <l>And preſs the bluſhing Grapes to yield their Wine.</l>
               <l>All <hi>India</hi>'s Aromaticks grace the Feaſt;</l>
               <l>And Odours gather'd from remoteſt <hi>Eaſt:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>The Minſtrels with ſoft Muſick ſtrike the Ear,</l>
               <l>Melodious Lays reſound in trembling Air.</l>
               <l>Now <hi>Julia</hi> enters, all adorn'd with Gem,</l>
               <l>A Fabrick worthy the World's Diadem.</l>
               <pb n="58" facs="tcp:46801:31"/>
               <l>If Beauty was the Birthright of a Throne,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Julia</hi> might challenge all the World her own:</l>
               <l>If Conduct be to Government a Pride,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Julia</hi> had that ſecurely on her ſide:</l>
               <l>Her Arts ſucceeded where the Stateſmen fail'd,</l>
               <l>Where they deſpair'd, her crafty Lures prevail'd.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Caeſar</hi> Reſolves her conquering Graces quell,</l>
               <l>For Beauty is a Charm invincible:</l>
               <l>It's only hers to think, to Ask and have:</l>
               <l>She leads the eaſie Monarch as her Slave.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Roxana</hi>'s wonderous Charms did thus conſpire,</l>
               <l>To ſet the fam'd <hi>Perſepolis</hi> on Fire:</l>
               <l>Thus <hi>Anthony</hi> the ſlighted World defies,</l>
               <l>A Martyr falls to <hi>Cleopatra</hi>'s Eyes.</l>
               <l>Thus <hi>Judah</hi>'s Champion in th'unequal Strife,</l>
               <l>Loſes his Hair, and Strength, and Eyes, and Life.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>Achates</hi> found his toil'd Endeavours vain,</l>
               <l>The Structure he had rear'd deſtroy'd again.</l>
               <l>A thouſand wild Diſorders now come on,</l>
               <l>A ſtrange confuſion rattles round the Throne:</l>
               <pb n="59" facs="tcp:46801:31"/>
               <l>Contemn'd abroad, and hated here at home,</l>
               <l>It threatens like an univerſal Doom:</l>
               <l>He ſaw it was in vain to ſtem the Flood,</l>
               <l>No Counſels cou'd be heard for <hi>Albion</hi>'s Good:</l>
               <l>The preſent Age he now reſigns to Fate,</l>
               <l>But makes proviſion for a future Date.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>Caeſario</hi>'s eldeſt Hopes to ripeneſs grown,</l>
               <l>At Court like ſome bright Conſtellation ſhone;</l>
               <l>A dawning Star that promis'd Succour near</l>
               <l>To the diſtreſs'd deſpairing Mariner.</l>
               <l>He ſaw <hi>Auguſtus</hi> as a riſing Sun,</l>
               <l>Had in his <hi>Eaſt</hi> a glorious Courſe begun,</l>
               <l>Purſuing Honour with an eager chace,</l>
               <l>His Actions worthy his Illuſtrious Race:</l>
               <l>A Curb to Tyrants he, and <hi>Gallic</hi> Pride,</l>
               <l>Fortune he kept impriſon'd on his ſide.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>This Match he for <hi>Auguſta</hi> does propoſe,</l>
               <l>His Sentiments well-meaning Friends eſpouſe.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Caeſar</hi> aſſents, and does approve the Choice,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Caeſario</hi> with Reluctance gives his Voice.</l>
               <pb n="60" facs="tcp:46801:32"/>
               <l>Happy the Day that ſaw <hi>Auguſta</hi> Bride!</l>
               <l>Nearer by Virtues both, than Birth, ally'd.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Britannia</hi> hence foreſees a dawning Morn,</l>
               <l>And <hi>Rome</hi>'s, and <hi>Gaul</hi>'s Imperious Inſults ſcorn.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The Jeſuits are here again outdone,</l>
               <l>As far as twinkling Tapers by the Sun.</l>
               <l>They clog'd with Plenty, dreaded no decay,</l>
               <l>Nor fear'd ſucceeding Darkneſs to the Day.</l>
               <l>The full poſſeſſion of their preſent Joy,</l>
               <l>They thought no Human Agents cou'd deſtroy.</l>
               <l>But <hi>Rome</hi> impatient grown with dull delays,</l>
               <l>Like Miſers ſtill deſirous of encreaſe;</l>
               <l>Aiming at new Additions to their Store,</l>
               <l>And in the midſt of Luxury craving more.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Caeſar</hi> is now an envy'd hindrance grown,</l>
               <l>He ſits too long unactive on the Throne:</l>
               <l>They'd all their Ends they cou'd expect from him:</l>
               <l>Now Life it ſelf becomes the only Crime.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Caeſario</hi> ripe, and finiſh'd up for Rule;</l>
               <l>All Oppoſition <hi>Gallia</hi> wou'd controul.</l>
               <pb n="61" facs="tcp:46801:32"/>
               <l>Their Tools prepar'd at home did ready ſtand,</l>
               <l>For any Revolution of the Land.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Hibernia</hi> eager for a change of State,</l>
               <l>Provokes, as once of old, an haſty Fate.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>Achates</hi> was not ſilent in this Storm,</l>
               <l>Did what an active Stateſman cou'd perform.</l>
               <l>Their dark Cabals his Emiſſaries find,</l>
               <l>And tell him all the Miſchiefs they deſign'd.</l>
               <l>Intelligence a certain ſafety brings,</l>
               <l>The Guardian of an Army and a King.</l>
               <l>He cheriſh'd more regard for <hi>Caeſar</hi>'s Life,</l>
               <l>He cou'd not ſee him fall in ſuch a ſtrife.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Th' Infernal Conſult now does open lye,</l>
               <l>The bloody Scheme expos'd to ev'ry Eye;</l>
               <l>The Plot, the Machines, and the Actors ſhown,</l>
               <l>The whole Contrivance open laid and known;</l>
               <l>A numerous Scrowl of ſeveral Ranks expire,</l>
               <l>On Gibbets Gaſp, and expiate in Fire.</l>
               <l>Some on the Scaffolds trembling Trunks extend,</l>
               <l>Diſgorge their Blood, and in Convulſions end.</l>
               <pb n="62" facs="tcp:46801:33"/>
               <l>This Storm blown o'er, ſtrange Prodigies ariſe,</l>
               <l>A new <hi>Parhelia</hi> glitters in the Skies;</l>
               <l>This does ſome giddy Proſelytes amaze,</l>
               <l>They ſtand, and glare, and kindle into blaze.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <lg type="triplet">
                  <l>To ſumm its numerous Votaries in our Iſle,</l>
                  <l>And how they're cloſely center'd to beguile,</l>
                  <l>Unworthy Verſe it is, or any Muſes toil.</l>
               </lg>
               <l>In few, let's all their little Arts diſcloſe,</l>
               <l>Show how to <hi>Rome</hi> they're Friends, to <hi>Albion</hi> Foes.</l>
               <l>One impious Doctrine, worſe than <hi>Rome,</hi> they teach,</l>
               <l>A parity of Governors they preach.</l>
               <l>Are no Superiors the Apoſtles Theme?</l>
               <l>Muſt all Coequal be, and all Supreme?</l>
               <l>All are Inferior to th'Almighty Head,</l>
               <l>But ſure Commanding Officers muſt Lead.</l>
               <l>Th' Apoſtles taught us thus, this Goſpel told,</l>
               <l>This Doctrine Primitive Fathers have enroll'd.</l>
               <l>Great <hi>Pearſon</hi> clearly does demonſtrate this,</l>
               <l>Till he is anſwer'd, let them acquieſce.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb n="63" facs="tcp:46801:33"/>
               <l>From dark Oblivion let one Inſtance paſs,</l>
               <l>And be beyond the power of Time to raſe;</l>
               <l>Common Diſtempers they for Devils take,</l>
               <l>Or with confederate Tricks their Project make,</l>
               <l>What will not be effected by this Cheat!</l>
               <l>Theſe to be thought Religious, Wiſe, and Great,</l>
               <l>Invoke th' Almighty to their impious ſhow,</l>
               <l>And crowd up Hell with Imprecations too.</l>
               <l>The <hi>Lapland</hi> Saint with eaſie Toil can gueſs,</l>
               <l>When to fix <hi>Lucifer,</hi> when diſpoſſeſs.</l>
               <l>Driveling and yawning with a foul Grimace,</l>
               <l>Like Spouts conveying Rain from Carved Face,</l>
               <l>Now Prays, now Groans, now Curſes, all in Cant;</l>
               <l>Out-flies the Devil, to avoid the Saint:</l>
               <l>But ſure ſuch Cant wou'd rather <hi>Daemons</hi> raiſe,</l>
               <l>They're Blaſphemy ſuch Offerings as theſe:</l>
               <l>Are theſe the Chriſtian Principles they give?</l>
               <l>They teach what they themſelves do disbelieve.</l>
               <l>Can Acts like theſe proceed from what is good?</l>
               <l>Theſe Frogs may croak, but cannot pray in Mud.</l>
               <pb n="64" facs="tcp:46801:34"/>
               <l>One Inſtance more let's Regiſter in Verſe,</l>
               <l>One more opprobrious Parallel rehearſe;</l>
               <l>Their Proſelytes they equally Devour,</l>
               <l>They preach 'em Heav'n, but graſp at all their Store,</l>
               <l>In this unerring Maxim they agree,</l>
               <l>Inſatiate as the Grave, or craving Sea,</l>
               <l>When Pains invade, and fierce Diſeaſes meet,</l>
               <l>To hurry Mortals to a future State;</l>
               <l>When heavy Groans proclaim their Fate is near,</l>
               <l>No ſigns of coming Health or Life appear,</l>
               <l>Then on frail Nature eager they preſs on,</l>
               <l>And Cant, for Intereſt, in a Saint-like Tone;</l>
               <l>Their Prey by their unhallow'd Prayers they ſeize,</l>
               <l>And fleece them in their dying Agonies.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>Achates</hi> had to each a like regard,</l>
               <l>And either ſide receives a like Reward,</l>
               <l>As others fell, ſo theſe expiring lie,</l>
               <l>And finiſh this laſt Scene of Tragedy.</l>
               <l>Like two defeated Bodies either ſtood,</l>
               <l>The Ferment was allay'd by Letting blood;</l>
               <pb n="65" facs="tcp:46801:34"/>
               <l>But <hi>Rome</hi> in this might an advantage boaſt;</l>
               <l>The Latter-Game by th' other Party loſt,</l>
               <l>Diverts the Hunt, and does the Chace divide,</l>
               <l>Reverts the Cry on the Diſſenters ſide.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>All that <hi>Achates</hi> cou'd perform was vain,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Caeſario</hi> is with Smiles receiv'd again;</l>
               <l>He claims ſucceſſive Right to <hi>Albion</hi>'s Rule,</l>
               <l>Nor was there any Law that did controul;</l>
               <l>No Votes Excluſive of his Claim wou'd down,</l>
               <l>Nor wou'd he weigh his Faith againſt a Crown;</l>
               <l>Too deep Impreſſions had his Youth receiv'd,</l>
               <l>For what he then imbib'd he ſtill believ'd.</l>
               <l>In vain the Doctors of our Church engage,</l>
               <l>In vain they did eſſay t'reform his Age;</l>
               <l>What e'er was urg'd on the Reformers ſide,</l>
               <l>Was but t'oppoſe the Winds or preſſing Tide.</l>
               <l>And thus Affairs in Church and State appear'd,</l>
               <l>When news of <hi>Caeſar</hi>'s ſudden Fate was heard;</l>
               <l>The news like Thunder ſhook the aſtoniſh'd Land,</l>
               <l>Like <hi>Niobes</hi> we metamorphoz'd ſtand;</l>
               <pb n="66" facs="tcp:46801:35"/>
               <l>Divided 'twixt our Love and future Fears,</l>
               <l>A wild diſorder'd harmony appears;</l>
               <l>If <hi>Caeſar</hi> had not ſteer'd a proſperous Courſe,</l>
               <l>The preſent Proſpect did augment it worſe;</l>
               <lg type="triplet">
                  <l>Eddies, and Rocks, and Shelves are all behind,</l>
                  <l>Rough Storms ariſe, w<hi rend="sup">th</hi> thunder wing'd on wind,</l>
                  <l>Sad Entertainments of a troubl'd Mind.</l>
               </lg>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Delays howe'er were dangerous to be try'd,</l>
               <l>The vacant Throne demands to be ſupply'd:</l>
               <l>A ſtubborn People careleſs of a Sway,</l>
               <l>They muſt be check'd by Law, and taught t'obey;</l>
               <l>No Titles yet diſputable oppoſe,</l>
               <l>Nor jarring Acts as yet contracted Foes.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>Caeſario</hi> is proclaim'd, the willing Land</l>
               <l>Eſpouſe his Claim, and yield to his Command:</l>
               <l>As much of Grace as Majeſty cou'd ſhow,</l>
               <l>As much as Subjects ought from Kings to know,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Caeſario</hi> promis'd to th'expecting Iſle,</l>
               <l>And all our Hopes depended on his Smile.</l>
               <pb n="67" facs="tcp:46801:35"/>
               <l>Oh! had he center'd in this pleaſing Sphere,</l>
               <l>Not urg'd with rapid force his Courſe too far;</l>
               <l>He like the Sun retreating from his Noon,</l>
               <l>An eaſie and a wonderous Race had run;</l>
               <l>We then had bask'd in ev'ry ſplendid Ray,</l>
               <l>Nor had one envy'd Cloud obſcur'd the Day;</l>
               <l>At his own Altars here he might have bow'd,</l>
               <l>And offer'd Incenſe curling in a Cloud.</l>
               <l>Ah! why wou'd he with <hi>Syren</hi> Notes beguile!</l>
               <l>Why was their Venom mingl'd with the Smile!</l>
               <l>He promis'd Bleſſings on his own accord,</l>
               <l>He might with the ſame eaſe have kept his Word;</l>
               <l>Unhappy Faith that gives this Latitude!</l>
               <l>And does an univerſal Bond exclude.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Yet for a time on eaſie Waves we play,</l>
               <l>And <hi>Halcyon</hi> Gales the fleeting Bark convey;</l>
               <l>No preſent Storm did threaten from afar,</l>
               <l>No thickening Cloud ſpread o'er our Hemiſphere.</l>
               <l>In his own Mode his Piety he ſhow'd,</l>
               <l>We in the Church eſtabliſh'd ſerv'd our God.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb n="68" facs="tcp:46801:36"/>
               <l>When ſtrait the old Reformers of the Times,</l>
               <l>Who mend Defaults by acting greater Crimes;</l>
               <l>When whatſoe'er is Sacred is profan'd,</l>
               <l>It's then a thorow Reformation nam'd.</l>
               <l>When Civil Rights a woful ruine bear,</l>
               <l>It's but the Harveſt of Religious War:</l>
               <l>Theſe forward Zealots of a barren Cauſe,</l>
               <l>Theſe Enemies to Order and the Laws,</l>
               <l>With the <hi>Parrhelia</hi> in the Weſt appear,</l>
               <l>Warm in his Beams and kindle into War;</l>
               <l>Preſs on like haſty Floods with impious Rage,</l>
               <l>The Folly and the wonder of the Age:</l>
               <l>With untaught Troops they raſhly ventur'd on,</l>
               <l>And fought like ſtubborn Fools to be undone.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>What can be argu'd to excuſe theſe Men?</l>
               <l>Who can for them a juſt defence maintain?</l>
               <l>Are theſe the Champions of <hi>Britannia</hi>'s Fate?</l>
               <l>Muſt ſhe from them her great Deliverance date?</l>
               <l>What cou'd theſe deſperate Engines thus inſpire?</l>
               <l>What kindle this Enthuſiaſtick Fire?</l>
               <pb n="69" facs="tcp:46801:36"/>
               <l>It's plain, the Movement lies before our Eyes,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Rome</hi> gives the Machines Motion, and Supplies.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>If ever People wou'd receive Advice,</l>
               <l>And Wiſdom really know without diſguiſe,</l>
               <l>Dear bought Experience ſure wou'd teach them more,</l>
               <l>Than all their dull fallacious Guides before:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Albion</hi> has other Hero's for her Guard,</l>
               <l>Souls worthy <hi>Albion</hi>'s Race, and vaſt Reward:</l>
               <l>Not puny Emmets of a Muſhrome Birth,</l>
               <l>Like theſe meer Inſects crawling out of Earth:</l>
               <l>A few revolving Suns will ſpeak their Names,</l>
               <l>In Annals pregnant with unuſual Fame.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The Mock Sun vaniſh'd like a wandring Fire,</l>
               <l>In Blood he Set, his purpl'd Beams expire.</l>
               <l>The Weſtern Fields were ſtrew'd with guilty Seed;</l>
               <l>May no proliſic Crop indulge the breed!</l>
               <l>If future Faults provoke the angry Throne,</l>
               <l>Theirs be the Guilt, the Blood be all their own.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb n="70" facs="tcp:46801:37"/>
               <l>What happier Scene for <hi>Rome</hi> can be diſplay'd!</l>
               <l>The Rebels routed, and her Rival dead;</l>
               <l>Her open Foes in Battel overthrown,</l>
               <l>Cou'd give no more diſturbance to the Throne,</l>
               <l>'Twas ſure the Terror of this Rival's force,</l>
               <l>Check'd in its full career the <hi>Roman</hi> Courſe:</l>
               <l>Or ſure ſhe thought <hi>Caeſario</hi>'s potent Seat,</l>
               <l>Was now above the Rage of Men and Fate,</l>
               <l>Or that the Church eſtabliſh'd ne'er wou'd ſwerve,</l>
               <l>But beyond all extreams of Duty ſerve.</l>
               <lg type="triplet">
                  <l>With this aſſurance buoy'd away ſhe flies,</l>
                  <l>Her tow'ring Plumes aſpire the very Skies,</l>
                  <l>Sure of the Goal, ſhe aims to graſp the Prize.</l>
               </lg>
               <l>Storms after Storms wing'd on deſtructive Wind,</l>
               <l>Now rage, and in no compaſs are confin'd;</l>
               <l>So <hi>Boreas</hi> bluſters o'er the troubl'd Main,</l>
               <l>And with each Billow does a War maintain,</l>
               <l>Thunders attend him with a noiſie Crowd,</l>
               <l>And pointed Light'nings flaſh from every Cloud.</l>
               <pb n="71" facs="tcp:46801:37"/>
               <l>The Surges riſe and preſs with waving Trains,</l>
               <l>But on the Rocks expend their Force in vain.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <lg type="triplet">
                  <l>
                     <hi>Rome</hi> now a bare-fac'd open Game does play,</l>
                  <l>Her bold, defying, bloody Flag diſplay,</l>
                  <l>In earneſt ſtrives at an unbounded Sway.</l>
               </lg>
               <l>No huddl'd Projects longer are kept cloſe,</l>
               <l>She does a large expanded Scene diſcloſe;</l>
               <l>To compaſs this, ſhe gives a certain Blow,</l>
               <l>At once all <hi>Albions Baſis</hi> to o'erthrow.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Twelve Ermin'd Judges are prepar'd to give</l>
               <l>Away our Rights, to grace Prerogative:</l>
               <l>Free, as they are requir'd, they all reſign,</l>
               <l>And prodigally aid this black Deſign.</l>
               <l>In Ages paſt, what our Forefathers toil'd</l>
               <l>With vaſt Efforts and Induſtry to build,</l>
               <l>What They with Sweat and Blood, &amp; endleſs Care,</l>
               <l>Upon a ſtrong Foundation ſtrove to rear,</l>
               <l>The very Guardians of our Beings all,</l>
               <l>Before theſe Twelve Apoſtate <hi>Britans</hi> fall.</l>
               <pb n="72" facs="tcp:46801:38"/>
               <l>Unhappy Men! too forward taught in Crimes!</l>
               <l>The very Ignominy of the Times!</l>
               <lg type="triplet">
                  <l>How cou'd they this to after Years convey?</l>
                  <l>Or how engage their Sons to curſe the Day?</l>
                  <l>Why ſhou'd they late Poſterity betray?</l>
               </lg>
               <l>Their native Rights be raviſh'd from their Claim,</l>
               <l>Tranſmit them down, a barren empty Name,</l>
               <l>Who conſtituted theſe twelve Men ſupreme?</l>
               <l>How came this Pow'r to be aſſum'd by them?</l>
               <l>Grant that they muſt expound the Text of Law,</l>
               <l>Whence do they thence this wild Concluſion draw?</l>
               <l>Is Expoſition to repeal an Act?</l>
               <l>What Parliaments enforce, can they retract?</l>
               <l>This true, their Pow'r is more capacious grown,</l>
               <l>Than all our General Council, and the Crown:</l>
               <l>But that's abſurd, and ſo their Grants were vain,</l>
               <l>They give a Privilege they can't maintain,</l>
               <l>Howe'er it ſerves to buttreſs up their Cauſe,</l>
               <l>And gives a colour to clude the Laws.</l>
               <pb n="73" facs="tcp:46801:38"/>
               <l>Which are diſpenc'd withal without controul,</l>
               <l>The King's the Repreſentative o'th' whole.</l>
               <l>Through this wide Breach the Inundation flows,</l>
               <l>Which all our Mounds of ſafety overthrows:</l>
               <l>Nothing but boundleſs Pow'r now courts the Ear,</l>
               <l>As <hi>Eaſtern</hi> Kings, or <hi>Perſian</hi> Sophi's are;</l>
               <l>A Will coercive, as eſtabliſh'd Law,</l>
               <l>Flaſh'd thro' the Land, and all the Nation awes;</l>
               <l>Nor this large Doctrine muſt we disbelieve,</l>
               <l>This Stamp in early Youth we muſt receive,</l>
               <l>Sacred as is our Faith, and Canons this,</l>
               <l>We muſt in this entirely acquieſce:</l>
               <l>This ev'ry Bard, and ev'ry Druid told,</l>
               <l>And every Penman of the Iſle enroll'd.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>But now let's caſt on either ſide an Eye,</l>
               <l>Not byaſs'd with a Partiality.</l>
               <l>Let's ſee what ſtrength of Senſe does this maintain,</l>
               <l>The Tares and Chaff let's ſeparate from the Grain;</l>
               <l>Let's hear how firſt they Government define;</l>
               <l>Why, it's Paternal all, and all Divine;</l>
               <pb n="74" facs="tcp:46801:39"/>
               <l>From <hi>Adam</hi> this Deſpotic Claim began,</l>
               <l>To <hi>Noah</hi> down ſucceſſive Titles ran,</l>
               <l>He to his Sons tranſmits this General Rule,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>We muſt Obedience pay without Controul.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>A free Aſſertion this, and very clear,</l>
               <l>Cou'd it a Demonſtration but appear;</l>
               <l>But if a Suppoſition is allow'd,</l>
               <l>Then Suppoſitions on each Side muſt crowd,</l>
               <l>And Arguments as endleſs as at firſt,</l>
               <l>Both run in vain, for neither Party loſt.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Before the Flood imperfect Rolls are known;</l>
               <l>What Actions in thoſe num'rous Years were done,</l>
               <l>The Sacred Writ has not divulg'd to Man,</l>
               <l>Who can a <hi>Theſis</hi> oppoſite maintain?</l>
               <l>We read of <hi>Patriarchs,</hi> how the rolling Spheres</l>
               <l>Oft whirl'd around in many tedious Years,</l>
               <l>And found them ſtill in Youth, no rip'ning Snow</l>
               <l>Adorn'd their Heads, nor Wrinkles grac't the Brow;</l>
               <l>The very Planets wonder'd at the Race,</l>
               <l>They ſtill appear'd in Prime, with blooming Grace.</l>
               <pb n="75" facs="tcp:46801:39"/>
               <l>Now ſcarce one Revolution they compleat,</l>
               <l>But ſee Mankind deſtroy'd by angry Fate:</l>
               <l>Life's but a Thought, we're now of ſhorter Breath,</l>
               <l>And claim an earlier Kindred with the Earth.</l>
               <l>What mention is there made of Kingly Rule?</l>
               <l>Or who e'er ſhew'd th'Oeconomy o'th' Whole?</l>
               <l>Of their long Lives a clear Account is writ,</l>
               <l>Not who were Kings, or who to them ſubmit.</l>
               <l>Why then ſhou'd this a <hi>Canon</hi> be to Man?</l>
               <l>It's but a bare Opinion they maintain.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>But <hi>Noah</hi> falls in a ſucceſſive Line</l>
               <l>From <hi>Adam,</hi> and divulg'd his great Deſign,</l>
               <l>To raiſe a Fabrick that cou'd ſtem the Main,</l>
               <l>When Heav'n deſtroy'd the World with future Rain.</l>
               <l>This as a Prophet, not as King he told,</l>
               <l>This Title in the Sacred Writ's enroll'd:</l>
               <l>For <hi>Noah</hi>'s Sermon did continue long,</l>
               <l>He preach'd a quick Repentance all along:</l>
               <l>Had he been King, they'd more Allegiance paid,</l>
               <l>They'd ſurely known their Orders, and obey'd.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb n="76" facs="tcp:46801:40"/>
               <l>But o'er his Houſe a Regal ſway he bore;</l>
               <l>So Fathers ſince, and doubtleſs did before:</l>
               <l>But he of many others had a Care,</l>
               <l>He was to many Tribes a Royal Heir;</l>
               <l>Before the Flood he bore extended Sway,</l>
               <l>And taught a numerous People to Obey:</l>
               <l>That's but, perhaps, a Controverſial Throne,</l>
               <l>For ever thus we argue <hi>Pro</hi> and <hi>Con:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Why then i'th' Ark did he not more include,</l>
               <l>Out of that univerſal Multitude?</l>
               <l>He was regardleſs of his Subjects good,</l>
               <l>He let them fall unpity'd in the Flood;</l>
               <l>To this they Anſwer —</l>
               <l>That great Command convey'd to him from <hi>Heav'n,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Was only by th' Almighty's Order given.</l>
               <l>This then Conducts us to another Theme,</l>
               <l>Let's ask how Ages govern'd after him;</l>
               <l>For if from Heav'ns bright Throne all Orders come,</l>
               <l>And Nations wait from <hi>Jove</hi>'s great date their <hi>doom,</hi>
               </l>
               <pb n="77" facs="tcp:46801:40"/>
               <l>Or we are left to Reaſon's dictates here,</l>
               <l>Or Revelation muſt new Kings declare.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>It's plain from <hi>Noah,</hi> to fam'd <hi>Abraham</hi>'s Race,</l>
               <l>No Calendars of Kings the Hiſtory Grace;</l>
               <l>Nor are ſucceſſive Monarchs there expreſt,</l>
               <l>It's but a meer Conjecture at the beſt.</l>
               <l>The Records no Paternal Titles name,</l>
               <l>Nor Crown ſucceeding Sons with Regal Fame;</l>
               <l>But they averr, —</l>
               <l>When <hi>Iſrael</hi>'s Sons poſſeſt the Promis'd Land,</l>
               <l>Then Kings were pointed out by God's Command.</l>
               <l>It's true, and wou'd he pleaſe to do it now,</l>
               <l>Who then diſputed Titles durſt allow;</l>
               <l>But ſince his Wiſdom Infinite denies</l>
               <l>This Gift to Man, our Reaſon muſt ſupply;</l>
               <l>Reaſon diſdains relation to the Earth,</l>
               <l>For with the Soul it claims Celeſtial Birth;</l>
               <l>Reaſon's the Pole-Star of the World's great ſway,</l>
               <l>By it the Monarch Rules, and we Obey.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb n="78" facs="tcp:46801:41"/>
               <l>This then allow'd, the Muſe proceeds to tell</l>
               <l>The Wonders of our Days, and what befell,</l>
               <l>Our Actions be to coming Ages known;</l>
               <l>And let us vindicate what we have done.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>But by the bye, let's take a ſhort ſurvey,</l>
               <l>How the known Globe is govern'd at this Day,</l>
               <l>What Conſtitutions different Kingdoms claim,</l>
               <l>How each exerts its Pow'r, and wins a Fame.</l>
               <l>Then <hi>Albion</hi>'s Sons may with a general Voice,</l>
               <l>Conſider all diſtinct, and take their choice:</l>
               <l>If then they'll alter what their Fathers rear'd,</l>
               <l>They'll bring a worſe Deſtruction than they fear'd.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Firſt to the <hi>Eaſtern</hi> Climes let's wing our way,</l>
               <l>There take a view of Arbitrary Sway:</l>
               <l>Here Princes abſolute as Heav'n appear,</l>
               <l>As awful as the mighty Thunderer:</l>
               <l>Unbounded Terrors here ſurround the Throne,</l>
               <l>And trembling Subjects at a Beck fall down:</l>
               <l>No Law ſecures them but the Monarch's Will,</l>
               <l>He's only judge of what is Good or Ill,</l>
               <pb n="79" facs="tcp:46801:41"/>
               <l>It's he diſpenſes Edicts thro' the Land,</l>
               <l>The paſſive People yield to each Command:</l>
               <l>No Charters there, or Property they claim,</l>
               <l>A Subject's Freedom's but an airy Name.</l>
               <l>They know no Right that they can call their own,</l>
               <l>Or to Poſterity tranſmit it down.</l>
               <l>Their Lives, Eſtates, and all their numerous Race,</l>
               <l>One angry Nod deſtroys, or does deface;</l>
               <l>Rivers of Blood muſt expiation make,</l>
               <l>For every little Pique the Monarch takes:</l>
               <l>Like a Majeſtick Savage he bears Rule,</l>
               <l>Nor dare his trembling Herds his Will controul.</l>
               <l>Can common Senſe this brutal Sway maintain?</l>
               <l>For Beaſts more proper ſure than God-like Man,</l>
               <l>Whoſe Appetites do covet ſuch a Feaſt,</l>
               <l>May be at <hi>India</hi>'s bloody Boards a Gueſt.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Three Parts in Four of the whole Globe we find</l>
               <l>Such Sanguinary Laws and Statutes bind:</l>
               <l>But Chriſtian Kingdoms other Rulers know;</l>
               <l>This is the next ſucceeding Point to ſhow:</l>
               <pb n="80" facs="tcp:46801:42"/>
               <l>To clear this Head, let's ſearch the ſacred Page,</l>
               <l>And ſee what Doctrines Jeſus taught his Age;</l>
               <l>Let's learn the Records of th'Almighty's Son,</l>
               <l>What on this Subject he deliver'd down.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Thro' all his Courſe he did Obedience preach</l>
               <l>To Kings, the very ſame th' Apoſtles teach;</l>
               <l>They pay ſubmiſſion to the Powers they find,</l>
               <l>And ſtamp that Law on ev'ry Chriſtian's Mind;</l>
               <l>But what's all this to form a Kingdom by?</l>
               <l>And many bring to one Society?</l>
               <l>What's this to Human Laws and Precepts here?</l>
               <l>When Government in <hi>Embryo</hi> did appear,</l>
               <l>When Policy erected high its Throne,</l>
               <l>And taught excentrick Crowds its Power to own;</l>
               <l>Our Saviour never touch'd upon that Theme,</l>
               <l>But left diſtinctive Lands in that Supream;</l>
               <l>He never did <hi>Auguſtus</hi> Right diſpute,</l>
               <l>Whether by Law he's bound, or Abſolute;</l>
               <l>Nor who proclaim'd him Emperor at <hi>Rome,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>When Amorous <hi>Anthony</hi> was Overcome;</l>
               <pb n="81" facs="tcp:46801:42"/>
               <l>Nor why he did aſſume a Sov'reign Pow'r,</l>
               <l>Which in the Senate was compriz'd before:</l>
               <l>His willing Tribute he to <hi>Caeſar</hi> paid,</l>
               <l>Call'd not in queſtion any Act he made:</l>
               <l>The <hi>Roman</hi> Edicts thorow <hi>Canaan</hi> fly,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Chriſt</hi> no Objection makes, but does comply.</l>
               <l>Hence ev'ry Scepter may new Laws command,</l>
               <l>As Exigencies of the State demand;</l>
               <l>And from each preſent Conſtitution's Frame</l>
               <l>The Prince and People both may Juſtice claim.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>This granted, more Enquiries were but vain,</l>
               <l>How other Lands eſtabliſh'd Rules maintain;</l>
               <l>Let it ſuffice us, that we know our own,</l>
               <l>What's ours to ask, and what to pay the Throne.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Now to the laſt deciſive Head we're come,</l>
               <l>Of all alledg'd before the Total Sum:</l>
               <l>If Government be by the Laws confin'd,</l>
               <l>Which Prince and People equally do bind,</l>
               <l>Why, in the Name of Goodneſs, may not Crimes</l>
               <l>On either Side diſturb the peaceful Times?</l>
               <pb n="82" facs="tcp:46801:43"/>
               <l>And Violence by Juſtice be compell'd</l>
               <l>Or to abſcond, or, when it ſtirs, to yield?</l>
               <l>This Equal Rule brings on a glorious Day,</l>
               <l>And will illuſtrate all we have to ſay:</l>
               <l>This Revolution at this Bar be try'd,</l>
               <l>And be a future Standard, and a Guide.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>Caeſario</hi> makes the Laws of Cobweb-force,</l>
               <l>Burſts thro' them all in his impetuous Courſe,</l>
               <l>Thro' all the Land imperious Edicts fly,</l>
               <l>The People muſt implicitly comply:</l>
               <l>Not Turbant-Precepts ſpeak with louder Strain,</l>
               <l>Nor Eaſtern Kings with greater Terrors reign.</l>
               <l>Whatever Oppoſitions did appear,</l>
               <l>Were levell'd all by the Court-Pioneers;</l>
               <l>Thoſe thoughtleſs Tools of a Tyrannick Power</l>
               <l>Were to have been the laſt it did devour;</l>
               <l>The <hi>Cyclops</hi> Kindneſs their Reward had been,</l>
               <l>They'd been the laſt in that deſtructive Scene.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>O'er the Tranſactions let us caſt an Eye,</l>
               <l>Let's take of all the Ills a ſhort Survey.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb n="83" facs="tcp:46801:43"/>
               <l>He had no more Domeſtick Foes to fear,</l>
               <l>'Twas now high time his other Aims to dare:</l>
               <l>Thoſe very Men whoſe Loyalty was known</l>
               <l>A ſtrong ſubſtantial Guardian of the Throne,</l>
               <l>Inur'd to War, all Perils they abide,</l>
               <l>And ſlighted Death and Danger on their Side;</l>
               <l>Whoſe bold Reſolves wou'd all Encounters meet,</l>
               <l>To bend their haughty Foes beneath their Feet;</l>
               <l>Theſe very Men are ey'd with half Regard,</l>
               <l>Scarce empty Praiſe allow'd for their Reward;</l>
               <l>Their very Lawrels raviſh'd from their Brow,</l>
               <l>Which Foreigners and <hi>Romiſh</hi> Courtiers know.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Our faithful <hi>Stateſmen</hi> who the <hi>Crown</hi> had ſerv'd,</l>
               <l>And never from a Prudent Conduct ſwerv'd,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Britannia</hi>'s Aid, and great Supporters, they</l>
               <l>Now from the alter'd Throne are urg'd away;</l>
               <l>Their Places fill'd by callow untaught Tools,</l>
               <l>Monſtrous Effects produce, and worthy Fools.</l>
               <l>The juſt Expounders of the Law are laid</l>
               <l>Aſide, the very Law it ſelf betray'd.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb n="84" facs="tcp:46801:44"/>
               <l>Ten thouſand Bribes engage the partial Bar</l>
               <l>'Gainſt Equity to manage well the War;</l>
               <l>Things thus prepar'd, they preſs it fiercely on,</l>
               <l>And with exalted Steps their Race they run.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Th'Eſtabliſh'd Church is now the Object grown</l>
               <l>Of all their Hate, the Envy of the Throne;</l>
               <l>That very Church who like a Fortreſs ſtood,</l>
               <l>And ſtemm'd the Rage of each Fanatick Flood,</l>
               <l>Whoſe blaſted. Laurels with the Martyr fell</l>
               <l>A Sacrifice to a diſtracted Zeal;</l>
               <l>That Church which long with <hi>Caeſar</hi>'s Fortune mourn'd,</l>
               <l>With him it ſuffer'd, and with him return'd;</l>
               <l>That very Church to whom <hi>Caeſario</hi> owes</l>
               <l>The Royalties that now adorn his Brows,</l>
               <l>Who plac'd the King on his Imperial Seat,</l>
               <l>In ſpite of Storms, and each oppoſing Fate;</l>
               <l>Whoſe juſt Defence he promis'd to eſpouſe,</l>
               <l>'Gainſt all th' Efforts and Inſults of its Foes;</l>
               <pb n="85" facs="tcp:46801:44"/>
               <l>That Church muſt now receive its dated Doom;</l>
               <l>It's order'd thus at <hi>Court,</hi> it's ſo decreed at <hi>Rome.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>To compaſs this, he courts his baffl'd Foes,</l>
               <l>On them redundant Favours he beſtows;</l>
               <l>No Acts of Grace theſe Minions are deny'd,</l>
               <l>Darlings at Court, <hi>Caeſario</hi>'s Joy and Pride.</l>
               <l>How ſoon they'd cancell'd all their guilty Score!</l>
               <l>How chang'd this <hi>Landskip</hi> from the <hi>Weſtern</hi> ſhore!</l>
               <l>From Gaols &amp; Gibbets freed, they ſpread the Land,</l>
               <l>And Places of the higheſt Truſt command;</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Diſſenters</hi> were the Nations Curſe before,</l>
               <l>Still <hi>Romiſh</hi> Tools, <hi>Romes</hi> Idols to reſtore;</l>
               <l>They hugg'd themſelves, and thought this ſmiling Sun</l>
               <l>Diſpens'd its Beams to cheriſh them alone.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>Achates</hi> was from Bus'neſs baniſh'd far,</l>
               <l>His goodly Beams abſcond, and diſappear;</l>
               <l>He, like a Star of the Firſt Magnitude,</l>
               <l>Is ſhadow'd by an interpoſing Cloud.</l>
               <l>How diff'rent now the Days from <hi>Caeſar</hi>'s Time!</l>
               <l>To be <hi>Caeſario</hi>'s Friend was then a Crime;</l>
               <pb n="86" facs="tcp:46801:45"/>
               <l>Unjuſtly then the Stateſman was confin'd,</l>
               <l>Becauſe they thought him to his Int'reſt kind:</l>
               <l>A num'rous Train of Articles they form,</l>
               <l>Their Shafts purſue him like a winged Storm;</l>
               <l>His ſteady Innocence of Proof was found,</l>
               <l>Invulnerable he, they cou'd not wound.</l>
               <l>When ſix revolving Suns the <hi>Zodiack</hi> paſt,</l>
               <l>Return'd, yet ſaw the <hi>Heroe</hi> unreleaſt;</l>
               <l>But all his Counſels were for <hi>Albion</hi>'s Good,</l>
               <l>He always firm to Honours Dictates ſtood.</l>
               <l>Let's leave <hi>Achates</hi> in his ancient Seat,</l>
               <l>Awaiting there a more indulgent Fate;</l>
               <l>Tho' ſilent there he lay, his open Ear</l>
               <l>Heard all the News, his Thoughts employ'd with Care.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Now ſev'ral Orders of their Prieſts appear,</l>
               <l>And in our Towns and Cities Altars rear;</l>
               <l>They crowd upon us in a num'rous Throng,</l>
               <l>Traverſe the Land, and bring their Gods along.</l>
               <pb n="87" facs="tcp:46801:45"/>
               <l>They gilded well their florid Harangues o'er,</l>
               <l>And ſlily teach, It was miſtake before;</l>
               <l>They held no Doctrines Impious, as we're told;</l>
               <l>Our Prelates mingl'd Tinſel with their Gold:</l>
               <l>But, after all, few Proſelytes they win,</l>
               <l>Their Chappels crowded, but their Vot'ries thin.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Stripes upon Stripes <hi>Caeſario</hi>'s Fury lays,</l>
               <l>He gives the Word, the Subjects muſt obey,</l>
               <l>There's no Excuſe muſt plead their guilty Cauſe,</l>
               <l>In vain they challenge, and appeal to Laws;</l>
               <l>Himſelf the Law does their Inſtruction bring,</l>
               <l>Or they muſt find the Terror of a King.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The Muſes Seats his Mandates firſt invade,</l>
               <l>He'll make his chief Attack at th' Fountains Head:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Apollo</hi>'s Sons unite, the Tempeſt ſtand,</l>
               <l>They truckle not to an unjuſt Command;</l>
               <l>Illegal Orders no Impreſſions made,</l>
               <l>More deference they to Oaths and Conſcience paid:</l>
               <l>Their College Statutes were to them a Rule,</l>
               <l>Nor cou'd an Arbitrary Word controul.</l>
               <pb n="88" facs="tcp:46801:46"/>
               <lg type="triplet">
                  <l>Since <hi>Thunder</hi> cou'd not, <hi>Lightning</hi> muſt perform;</l>
                  <l>From theſe <hi>brave Souls</hi> their <hi>Honors</hi> all were torn,</l>
                  <l>They'r <hi>wounded,</hi> tho' not <hi>vanquiſh'd</hi> by the <hi>Storm.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>That <hi>Count of High Commiſſion</hi> did appear</l>
               <l>Juſt like a Comet blazing in the Air,</l>
               <l>That Death and Ruine all around does throw,</l>
               <l>And fills with teeming Ills the World below.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>But now a Maſter-piece of <hi>Romiſh</hi> Rage</l>
               <l>And Folly comes, and ſtartles all the Age;</l>
               <lg type="triplet">
                  <l>Sev'n Living <hi>Martyrs</hi> from their Temples tore,</l>
                  <l>In Priſon thrown, unuſual Fetters bore,</l>
                  <l>Becauſe <hi>Rome</hi>'s Idols they cou'd not adore:</l>
               </lg>
               <l>Such Contradictions they cou'd not maintain</l>
               <l>As render'd all Religion dull and vain;</l>
               <l>They cou'd not think that an Eternal Mind,</l>
               <l>That rules the various Fates of Humane Kind,</l>
               <l>To whom the Heavens bow, at whoſe Command</l>
               <l>Man, like himſelf, cou'd think, and upright ſtand,</l>
               <l>Form'd from a wild Abyſs:</l>
               <pb n="89" facs="tcp:46801:46"/>
               <l>They cou'd not think this mighty Deity</l>
               <l>On his own Altar cou'd entombed lie;</l>
               <l>They cou'd not think that <hi>Jeſus</hi> dy'd before</l>
               <l>He on the curſed Tree thoſe Tortures bore:</l>
               <l>For when he ſpoke thoſe gen'ral Words, it's plain.</l>
               <l>The ſenſeleſs Bread did not the God contain.</l>
               <l>They cou'd not think he was deſign'd a Feaſt,</l>
               <l>To be devoured by an impious Prieſt;</l>
               <l>Or that thoſe Viands were deliver'd down</l>
               <l>As the Identick Fleſh of the Almighty's Son.</l>
               <l>Howe'er, the Scandal of the Bar they bear,</l>
               <l>Which makes their Innocence the more appear;</l>
               <l>Their Innocence their rigid Judges awes,</l>
               <l>They turn'd their Advocates, &amp; plead their Cauſe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>All Heads at work to bring the People o'er</l>
               <l>To chuſe ſuch Members as wou'd all devour;</l>
               <l>Such Men our awful Council muſt compoſe</l>
               <l>As were before prepar'd the Kingdoms Foes;</l>
               <l>Their Actions all Illegal fill the Land;</l>
               <l>Where they cou'd not cajole, they did command:</l>
               <pb n="90" facs="tcp:46801:47"/>
               <l>Had they proceeded thus their Prize to gain,</l>
               <l>The Law it ſelf had by a Law been ſlain.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Theſe loud Alarms thro' all the Nation fly,</l>
               <l>They cou'd no longer look with partial Eyes;</l>
               <l>Thoſe very People who indulg'd the Throne,</l>
               <l>And repreſented well whate'er was done,</l>
               <l>Now ſtunn'd with Horror, can excuſe no more,</l>
               <l>They cannot vindicate it, as before.</l>
               <l>If e'er Religion did or cou'd invite</l>
               <l>Its Proſelytes in its juſt Cauſe to fight;</l>
               <l>If ever <hi>Chriſtians</hi> were to wear the Sword,</l>
               <l>And draw it to defend the Sacred Word,</l>
               <l>As a familiar Text ſeems t' intimate,</l>
               <l>To guard their Doctrines from the <hi>Pagan</hi> Hate,</l>
               <l>No ſhriller Cries cou'd call us forth to Arms,</l>
               <l>Our Foes cou'd never give more bold Alarms.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>We rather ſtill on Pray'rs than War intent,</l>
               <l>Our Hopes were ſtretch'd e'en to the laſt extent;</l>
               <l>From humble Minds our offer'd Incenſe flies,</l>
               <l>With holy Violence we ſtorm the Skies;</l>
               <pb n="91" facs="tcp:46801:47"/>
               <l>With meek Addreſſes ſupplicate the King:</l>
               <l>Petitions no Redreſs nor Succour bring;</l>
               <l>From <hi>Rome</hi>'s Cabals ſtill further Inſults come,</l>
               <l>Too ſure, alas! we ſaw approaching Doom.</l>
               <l>So when the thickning Clouds obſcure the Air,</l>
               <l>And dusky Curtains skreen the Hemiſphere,</l>
               <l>The Swains their conſcious trembling Herds infold,</l>
               <l>And guard them all ſecurely in the Hold.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>But to conclude, and perfect the Deſign,</l>
               <l>In one uncommon Project they combine</l>
               <l>To give the laſt great Stroke to all they've done,</l>
               <l>And boldly finiſh what was thus begun.</l>
               <l>Now let the Muſe by Reaſon's Dictates ſteer,</l>
               <l>And let the Caſe be ſtated plain and clear;</l>
               <l>Let's make a Search with an unerring Eye,</l>
               <l>View each Retreat of this deep Myſtery:</l>
               <l>Ten thouſand Joys the pregnant Queen proclaim,</l>
               <l>It almoſt burſts the Cheeks of lab'ring Fame;</l>
               <l>Seraphick Hymns ſound loud in ev'ry Ear,</l>
               <l>And ſuming Incenſe covers all the Air.</l>
               <pb n="92" facs="tcp:46801:48"/>
               <l>
                  <hi>The Queen's conceiv'd,</hi> was ev'ry Courtier's Theme;</l>
               <l>The News is ſtill repeated, ſtill the ſame.</l>
               <l>Theſe wondrous Tidings eager they devour,</l>
               <l>Wait with impatient Zeal the future Hour.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Yet this Report did diff'rent Impreſs make</l>
               <l>In various Minds, the quick Alarm they take;</l>
               <l>With curious Ken behind the Veil they pry,</l>
               <l>This queſtion'd Truth ſearch out with careful Eye.</l>
               <l>This Rumour ſoon to great <hi>Auguſta</hi> came,</l>
               <l>It flagg'd not long upon the Wings of Fame;</l>
               <l>It found the Princeſs all retir'd, alone,</l>
               <l>Penſive and anxious for her <hi>Albion:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Too ſure, alas! her Countries Ills ſhe knew,</l>
               <l>She ſaw what Trains of Ruine did purſue,</l>
               <l>She oft in vain had to <hi>Caeſario</hi> mourn'd,</l>
               <l>But no Paternal Graces were return'd.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Auguſta</hi> did this Novel entertain</l>
               <l>Meek as became her Greatneſs, all Serene,</l>
               <l>To Heav'n ſtill ready to ſubmit her Mind,</l>
               <l>To its Decrees ſtill piouſly inclin'd;</l>
               <pb n="93" facs="tcp:46801:48"/>
               <l>Her Prudence was not yet deficient here,</l>
               <l>She ſhew'd true Conduct in this great Affair:</l>
               <l>Two worthy Matrons, of unqueſtion'd Fame,</l>
               <l>By her Commiſſion'd, into <hi>Albion</hi> came;</l>
               <l>She in their juſt Relations wou'd confide,</l>
               <l>And what ſeem'd doubtful ſhou'd by them be try'd.</l>
               <l>The Civil Law this Juſtice may demand,</l>
               <l>The Right of Nations this, and ev'ry Land,</l>
               <l>This Juſtice for a gen'ral Good deſign'd,</l>
               <l>Eſtabliſh'd as the Cement of Mankind:</l>
               <l>This Privilege debarr'd, the Birth-right's loſt,</l>
               <l>Nor can the Off-ſpring any Profit boaſt.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Th' expected Hour is paſt, a gen'ral Joy</l>
               <l>Rings thro' the Court, and gratulates the Boy:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>A Prince is born,</hi> was ev'ry Courtier's Cry,</l>
               <l>And Fire-works burſt, and rattle in the Sky.</l>
               <l>The King all Satisfaction did receive</l>
               <l>That Man cou'd covet, or that Fate cou'd give.</l>
               <l>He was above the Terror of his Foes,</l>
               <l>Nor did he fear a Storm wou'd interpoſe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb n="94" facs="tcp:46801:49"/>
               <l>But now for Arms <hi>Britannia</hi>'s Youth prepare,</l>
               <l>They cou'd no longer fence impending War;</l>
               <l>Ev'n Hope it ſelf forbids a dawning Day,</l>
               <l>It diſappear'd, and vaniſh'd quite away.</l>
               <l>A woful Med'cine War, a ſad Retreat;</l>
               <l>To Man it's Hazard, and the Game of Fate.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>Achates</hi> now appears upon the Stage,</l>
               <l>And with him brings the Nobles of the Age:</l>
               <l>Harangues were needleſs, and a formal Tale,</l>
               <l>Which often with unthinking Heads prevail;</l>
               <l>Theſe Worthies knew too well their Countries State,</l>
               <l>Too conſcious of its Woes, and coming Fate;</l>
               <l>Their Aims, their Thoughts were how to ſave the Land,</l>
               <l>And in the Breach of threatning Danger ſtand.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Unto <hi>Auguſtus,</hi> now reſolv'd, they ſend,</l>
               <l>T'engage him for their Champion, and their Friend:</l>
               <l>They repreſented plain the State of Things,</l>
               <l>What crowding Miſchiefs dull Delays wou'd bring;</l>
               <pb n="95" facs="tcp:46801:49"/>
               <l>Their Lives &amp; Fortunes with his Arms wou'd join,</l>
               <l>To carry on this Great and Juſt Deſign.</l>
               <l>Beſides his Honour, Int'reſt did engage</l>
               <l>Him to eſpouſe their Wrongs, and aid the Age;</l>
               <l>His Princeſs's Claim lay bleeding, and his own,</l>
               <l>For he was near ally'd to <hi>Albion</hi>'s Throne;</l>
               <l>That yet no Satisfaction did appear</l>
               <l>Relating to the Birthright of an Heir;</l>
               <l>But ſtrong Suſpicions of a form'd Deſign</l>
               <l>Did thro' the whole Intrigue too clearly ſhine.</l>
               <l>Thoſe very Perſons whom the Laws require,</l>
               <l>Or abſent were, or order'd to retire;</l>
               <l>Thoſe, not by Chance, but by Contrivance ſo,</l>
               <l>And theſe forbidden with a wrinkl'd Brow.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Divided Paſſions crowd <hi>Auguſtus</hi> Soul,</l>
               <l>A Filial Duty, and his Royal All;</l>
               <l>Too great his Mind to bear <hi>Caeſario</hi> Hate,</l>
               <l>Yet with himſelf does thus expoſtulate:</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The <hi>Britains</hi> all complain, a Lawleſs Son</l>
               <l>Is now entail'd on injur'd <hi>Albion</hi>'s Throne:</l>
               <pb n="96" facs="tcp:46801:50"/>
               <l>Sure by the fix'd Decrees of Civil Law</l>
               <l>I may demand to make him Legal now,</l>
               <l>Or tamely I undoubted Right reſign,</l>
               <l>And by my Silence they may queſtion mine:</l>
               <l>Our Claims diſputeleſs by theſe Ties are bound;</l>
               <l>They periſh all, if we deſtroy this Mound.</l>
               <l>The haughty <hi>Court</hi> deny'd the <hi>Nymphs</hi> their Claim,</l>
               <l>That from <hi>Auguſta</hi> on that Errand came:</l>
               <l>Beſides, I ne'er cou'd hear the Royal Breaſt</l>
               <l>In Milky Streams cou'd court the Infant's Reſt;</l>
               <l>Tho' Mortals vary'd, Nature fix'd ſtill ſtood,</l>
               <l>And ne'er gave Infant, but afforded Food:</l>
               <l>As we may ſee the ſhining <hi>Galaxy</hi>
               </l>
               <l>In Milky Paths deſcribes its Progeny.</l>
               <l>Sure ſomething more than Flights of Common Fame</l>
               <l>Muſt break thoſe <hi>Laws</hi> by which all <hi>Monarchs</hi> claim</l>
               <l>Their Right to Crowns.</l>
               <l>Since Man and Nature both conſent to join,</l>
               <l>To call me hence, I'll paſs for <hi>Albion;</hi>
               </l>
               <pb n="97" facs="tcp:46801:50"/>
               <l>A General Council ſhall decide the Cauſe,</l>
               <l>For, <hi>Juſtice is the Parent of the Laws.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>It's pleaſant ſure when into Port we come,</l>
               <l>And caſt out Anchor at our Native Home;</l>
               <l>When we can bid Defiance to the Wave</l>
               <l>That challeng'd Life, and form'd it ſelf a Grave;</l>
               <l>When we can reſt ſecurely on the Shore,</l>
               <l>And laugh at Storms that made us pale before;</l>
               <l>When we can ſit and tell of Dangers paſt,</l>
               <l>And lengthen out our Stories not in haſte.</l>
               <l>The <hi>Graecian</hi> Bard cou'd ſing the <hi>Trojan</hi>'s Doom,</l>
               <l>When <hi>Agamemnon</hi> did in Triumph come;</l>
               <l>When conq'ring <hi>Greeks</hi> review'd their ancient Soil,</l>
               <l>He then cou'd tell of Battels, and their Toil:</l>
               <lg type="triplet">
                  <l>Their Swords had cut out Subjects for his Pen,</l>
                  <l>And he at large diſplay'd the Warlike Scene,</l>
                  <l>Renew'd, and fought their Battels o'er again.</l>
               </lg>
               <l>So <hi>Maro</hi> cou'd, in Great <hi>Auguſtus</hi> Days,</l>
               <l>When all the World enjoy'd a general Peace,</l>
               <pb n="98" facs="tcp:46801:51"/>
               <l>He then cou'd ſing his <hi>Heroe,</hi> and Alarms,</l>
               <l>And brought <hi>Aeneas</hi> to <hi>Lavinia</hi>'s Arms;</l>
               <l>From burning <hi>Troy</hi> the pious Youth he brings,</l>
               <l>And ſeats him on the Throne of <hi>Latium</hi>'s Kings.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>As large a Subject courts the Muſes Eye,</l>
               <l>As e'er was found in <hi>Italy,</hi> or <hi>Troy:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Oh! had our <hi>Engliſh Virgil</hi> tun'd his Lyre,</l>
               <l>The God of Verſe wou'd ev'ry Strain inſpire:</l>
               <l>The Bard unto <hi>Apollo</hi> does belong,</l>
               <l>For <hi>Dryden,</hi> taught by him, compos'd a wondrous Song:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Cowley</hi> and he new Conqueſts made in Verſe;</l>
               <l>Their mighty Numbers, mighty Things rehearſe:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Blackmore</hi> eſſay'd it in a lofty Strain,</l>
               <l>'Twas he conducted <hi>Arthur</hi> to his Reign;</l>
               <l>He ſang of <hi>Arthur,</hi> and his proſp'rous War,</l>
               <l>The Parallel is in <hi>Auguſtus</hi> here.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Here are <hi>Ideas</hi> that inform the Mind,</l>
               <l>As Complex all as Learned <hi>Lock</hi> deſign'd;</l>
               <pb n="99" facs="tcp:46801:51"/>
               <l>All Images which <hi>Epicurus</hi> taught,</l>
               <l>All that can entertain and teach the Thought.</l>
               <l>Great are the Deeds as e'er were done by Men,</l>
               <l>Worthy their Labours, and a Muſes Pen.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>No more at <hi>Plutarch's Heroes</hi> let's admire,</l>
               <l>Thoſe Martial Souls that ſet the World on Fire,</l>
               <l>That carry'd on the Bus'neſs of their Days,</l>
               <l>And wreath'd their Temples with Immortal Bays:</l>
               <l>Let <hi>Greece,</hi> and <hi>Rome,</hi> and other Nations hear</l>
               <l>Our Feats of Arms, and learn new Arts of War.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>Achates</hi> and the Nobles did receive</l>
               <l>As full Aſſurance as the Prince cou'd give;</l>
               <l>He with a Force prepar'd wou'd aid the State,</l>
               <l>Join with their Arms, and leave the reſt to Fate.</l>
               <l>The Stateſman and the Soldier here combine</l>
               <l>By Strength and Wit to manage the Deſign.</l>
               <l>'Twas ſure the Common Danger did prepare</l>
               <l>Their Minds, and prov'd the Cement of the War:</l>
               <l>For never Project of ſo high Concern</l>
               <l>So many diff'rent Breaſts did entertain;</l>
               <pb n="100" facs="tcp:46801:52"/>
               <l>Of all Degrees and Ranks a num'rous Crowd</l>
               <l>In this important Buſineſs were employ'd;</l>
               <l>Yet not one Whiſper did a Thought make known</l>
               <l>To raiſe Suſpicion in the Jealous Throne:</l>
               <l>Not <hi>Gallia</hi>'s Ken, renown'd ſo much of late,</l>
               <l>That knew to pry int' all Affairs of State,</l>
               <l>That cou'd diſplay at her own Council-board</l>
               <l>What other Princes did project abroad;</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Europe</hi>'s Debates all at <hi>Verſails</hi> were known,</l>
               <l>There all the embryo'd Thoughts of Kings were ſhown;</l>
               <l>So quick, ſo ſure Intelligence did fly,</l>
               <l>You'd think each <hi>Daemon</hi> were for <hi>France</hi> a Spy.</l>
               <l>Yet this Intrigue was carry'd on ſo cloſe,</l>
               <l>It ſlipp'd 'em, and aſtoniſh'd all the Foes.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>Auguſtus</hi> buſied in this great Affair,</l>
               <l>Makes vaſt and pow'rful Levies for the War;</l>
               <l>Nature his Handmaid did convey her Store</l>
               <l>From Foreign Coaſts, and ev'ry diſtant Shore;</l>
               <pb n="101" facs="tcp:46801:52"/>
               <l>Strong Oaks were levell'd by the lab'ring Swain,</l>
               <l>Large Foreſts turn'd into a verdant Plain;</l>
               <l>They ſhape the Ribs &amp; Planks, &amp; Structures build,</l>
               <l>To plow the Seas, untaught to Storms to yield;</l>
               <l>Materials from remoteſt North they bear,</l>
               <l>And Pines to form high Maſts, to mount in Air;</l>
               <l>They ſearch the Bowels of the injur'd Earth,</l>
               <l>Dig deep, and give to ſhining Metals birth;</l>
               <l>They force a Rape upon their Mother Clay,</l>
               <l>And urge her Treaſures all conceal'd to Day;</l>
               <l>The ſturdy Oars run down in hollow Moulds,</l>
               <l>Large Engines frame, that noiſie Fates unfold;</l>
               <l>Deaths wing'd on Flame as quick as Lightning fly,</l>
               <l>And ſhew a ghaſtly Ruine to the Eye;</l>
               <l>To Sulph'rous Mines for center'd Flame they go,</l>
               <l>And ſearch Ingredients in vaſt Caves below.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And now the Fleet is rigg'd, well trimm'd, and mann'd,</l>
               <l>Commanders round the great <hi>Auguſtus</hi> ſtand,</l>
               <pb n="102" facs="tcp:46801:53"/>
               <l>And their laſt Orders wait from him to know,</l>
               <l>For they are ready where he points to go.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Let's leave him there a while, &amp; croſs the Flood,</l>
               <l>And view how our Affairs in <hi>Albion</hi> ſtood:</l>
               <l>Theſe Preparations were too great to lie</l>
               <l>For ever hid, from each enquiring Eye;</l>
               <l>The Bus'neſs now was to a Ripeneſs grown,</l>
               <l>He valu'd not if his Reſolves were known.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Soon to <hi>Caeſario</hi> comes the loud Report,</l>
               <l>It alter'd all the Meaſures of the Court:</l>
               <l>So <hi>Rome</hi>'s proud Monarch, that did Heav'n defie,</l>
               <l>And wou'd himſelf appear a Deity,</l>
               <l>When Thunder echo'd in the Air above,</l>
               <l>Wou'd hide his Head, and then confeſs'd a <hi>Jove.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>The little Flatterers, that the King miſled</l>
               <l>By Paths uncouth, uncommon to be trod,</l>
               <l>Thoſe that did buoy him up w<hi rend="sup">th</hi> Flights unknown,</l>
               <l>Tremble, grow pale, &amp; ſhiver round the Throne;</l>
               <l>The boldeſt He, ſeiz'd with unwonted Fear,</l>
               <l>Preſents a rueful Image of Deſpair.</l>
               <pb n="103" facs="tcp:46801:53"/>
               <l>So weak a Fence is Guilt in all Mankind,</l>
               <l>A very Sting and Poyſon to the Mind.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>Caeſario</hi> now, who late ſo high did ſoar,</l>
               <l>Beyond his Predeceſſors all before,</l>
               <l>Who paſs'd all Bounds of Reaſon, and of Law,</l>
               <l>And govern'd with an univerſal Awe,</l>
               <l>The very Engines of his Court he ſends</l>
               <l>To reconcile his Subjects for his Friends;</l>
               <l>Their ancient Rights and Freedoms he'll reſtore,</l>
               <l>He promis'd Juſtice, as of old before;</l>
               <l>Th' Impriſon'd Guides, whom late he did deſpiſe,</l>
               <l>Are call'd to Court again, and ask'd Advice:</l>
               <l>He all things promis'd that were thought to pleaſe,</l>
               <l>As Liberty, and Property, and Eaſe:</l>
               <l>When ſtreight the welcom News ſalutes his Ear,</l>
               <l>No Dread of Danger now, no Ground of Fear;</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Auguſtus</hi>'s Fleet was by the Storms repell'd,</l>
               <l>The Winds had o'er his pregnant Ships prevail'd;</l>
               <l>That Heav'n it ſelf his Quarrel did eſpouſe,</l>
               <l>Had ſhew'd its ſignal Juſtice on his Foes,</l>
               <pb n="104" facs="tcp:46801:54"/>
               <l>Their impious Veſſels daſh'd upon the Shore,</l>
               <l>Had ſilenc'd e'en the <hi>Belgick</hi> Lion's Roar.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Auguſtus</hi> wiſely ſpreads this grateful News,</l>
               <l>Refits, and his Deſcent once more purſues:</l>
               <l>Mean time <hi>Caeſario</hi> once again re-claims,</l>
               <l>He's ſtill inconſtant, found in that the ſame;</l>
               <l>His Smiles were vary'd to an angry Brow,</l>
               <l>And ev'ry Subject ſeems the Monarch's Foe:</l>
               <l>Thoſe very Rights we now aſſur'd our own,</l>
               <l>Are all revok'd, and all again's undone.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>But Heav'n no longer wou'd a Neuter ſtand,</l>
               <l>Each Wind obeys th' Almighty's great Command,</l>
               <l>He ſends his awful Orders from above,</l>
               <l>The Blaſts in murm'ring Controverſies ſtrove;</l>
               <l>Each ſtrove to be the firſt to fill the Sails,</l>
               <l>To complement <hi>Auguſtus</hi> with their Gales:</l>
               <l>Thoſe very Winds that forward ſmoothly bore</l>
               <l>His Fleet, confin'd <hi>Caeſario</hi>'s to the Shore;</l>
               <l>They, like a Train of Magick Caſtles, ſtood,</l>
               <l>And cou'd not ſteer an Helm to ſtem the Flood;</l>
               <pb n="105" facs="tcp:46801:54"/>
               <l>As if Enchantment had poſſeſs'd each Keel,</l>
               <l>They cou'd not hand a Cord to ſtretch a Sail.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>Auguſtus</hi> Fleet now ſpooms it o'er the Sea,</l>
               <l>And ſafely Anchors in a welcome Bay;</l>
               <l>Now other Breezes ſwell his Canvas Wings,</l>
               <l>From Shouts that on the crowded Beaches ring;</l>
               <lg type="triplet">
                  <l>His Guns return Salutes with grateful Cheer,</l>
                  <l>Oppoſing Echoes ſtrike the ſounding Air,</l>
                  <l>The Warlike Muſick's void of Death or Fear.</l>
               </lg>
               <l>He orders on the Shore his Martial Bands,</l>
               <l>Their poliſh'd Arms reflected on the Strands;</l>
               <l>The Horſes upwards hois'd, did hang in Air,</l>
               <l>And like unuſual Machins they appear;</l>
               <l>Th' Artillery's landed in a dreadful Train,</l>
               <l>Offenſive Arms by Land, and on the Main;</l>
               <l>The Carriages in order load the Strand,</l>
               <l>In Ranks, like a defenſive Rampart, ſtand:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Auguſtus</hi> draws his Forces tow'rds the Hills,</l>
               <l>His Army all the Mounts and Valleys fills:</l>
               <pb n="106" facs="tcp:46801:55"/>
               <l>Such Order here, ſuch Readineſs did ſhine,</l>
               <l>And ſuch exact, exalted Diſcipline,</l>
               <l>Not Ancient Generals ever Headed Men</l>
               <l>That did more cloſe and ſilent Ranks maintain;</l>
               <l>Not <hi>Caeſar</hi>'s Troops more ready were to die,</l>
               <l>Ne'er put off Life with more facility;</l>
               <l>Not <hi>Perſia</hi>'s Scourge cou'd greater Odds engage,</l>
               <l>Nor war with more unequal Numbers wage:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Carthage,</hi> and <hi>Rome</hi>'s, and <hi>Graecian</hi> Captains here</l>
               <l>Seem from their Shades to riſe, and breath again in Air.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>Achates</hi> active to his Power had been,</l>
               <l>Of <hi>Britiſh</hi> Youth he leads a valiant Train;</l>
               <l>The Nobles join him as he march'd along,</l>
               <l>And now they make a large extended Throng.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>Britannia</hi>'s Youth in ſhining Arms behold,</l>
               <l>As Lovely Dreadful as their Sires of old.</l>
               <l>If ever Fate cou'd be receiv'd with eaſe,</l>
               <l>It ſure muſt be from Inſtruments like theſe:</l>
               <pb n="107" facs="tcp:46801:55"/>
               <lg type="triplet">
                  <l>If ever Beauty did appear in War,</l>
                  <l>Its awful Charms are only center'd here,</l>
                  <l>As fierce as <hi>Mars,</hi> and as <hi>Minerva</hi> fair.</l>
               </lg>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Such were the Youth when <hi>Edward</hi> took the Field,</l>
               <l>And forc'd the ſtubborn <hi>Gaul</hi> ſubmiſs to yield;</l>
               <l>When on the Mount the dreadful Monarch ſate,</l>
               <l>And ſaw his Troops diſpute <hi>Britannia</hi>'s Fate;</l>
               <l>When bravely he refus'd to aid his Son,</l>
               <l>But bid him pluck thoſe Laurels all his own;</l>
               <l>Such were the Youth when that great Son advanc'd,</l>
               <l>And with an Handful routs the Pow'r of <hi>France;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Their Captiv'd King his Triumphs did adorn,</l>
               <l>Whilſt he's on Vict'rys Wings ſublimely born;</l>
               <l>Furniſh'd our <hi>Annals</hi> with Illuſtrious Deeds,</l>
               <l>Which only can from <hi>Britiſh</hi> Arms proceed.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Such were the Youth when <hi>Henry</hi> did prepare</l>
               <l>To teach proud <hi>Gaul</hi> new Stratagems of War;</l>
               <l>When <hi>Agencourt</hi> did regiſter the Day,</l>
               <l>And ſounding Heralds loud proclaim'd his Sway.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb n="108" facs="tcp:46801:56"/>
               <l>And ſuch are now the Youth, which from a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ar</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Gallia</hi> beholds, and trembles at the War;</l>
               <l>Theſe the Battalions that with grand Alarms</l>
               <l>Muſt rowſe all <hi>Europe</hi> to Confed'rate Arms;</l>
               <l>Muſt <hi>Gallia</hi>'s proud luxurious Pow'r pull down,</l>
               <l>And on <hi>Auguſtus</hi> Head confirm the Crown.</l>
               <l>Let's leave them moving with ſlow March along,</l>
               <l>Augmented by an adventitious Throng:</l>
               <l>Our City Gates fly open to receive</l>
               <l>Their Regiments, and Entertainments give.</l>
               <l>Let's view <hi>Caeſario</hi>'s Court, and how Affairs</l>
               <l>Preſent themſelves in this rough Face of Wars.</l>
               <l>Too late he faw the Error of his Cauſe:</l>
               <l>How weak's the Monarch that abandons Laws!</l>
               <l>Too late he ſaw his Paraſites had laid</l>
               <l>Rules for their Int'reſt all, and his betray'd:</l>
               <l>Too late he wiſh'd his ſlighted Friends his own,</l>
               <l>Too late indeed, forbid his Sight, they're gone.</l>
               <l>Pardons were now proclaim'd to call them o'er;</l>
               <l>A Pardon's needleſs where no Crime's before.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb n="109" facs="tcp:46801:56"/>
               <l>
                  <hi>Caeſario</hi> takes the Field, and Heads his Force,</l>
               <l>To ſtop the bold <hi>Auguſtus</hi> in his Courſe;</l>
               <l>His Army's num'rous, were their Minds the ſame,</l>
               <l>Did equal Ardour kindle up their Flame.</l>
               <l>Can <hi>Britans, Rome,</hi> and old <hi>Hybernian</hi> Foes,</l>
               <l>An adequate Affection each eſpouſe?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The Officers of higheſt Fame decline,</l>
               <l>Deſert the War, and with <hi>Auguſtus</hi> join.</l>
               <l>The Royal Branches to his Arms come o'er;</l>
               <l>Such Conduct they, and ſuch a Cauſe, abhor.</l>
               <l>Decrees unalterable are above;</l>
               <l>Theſe Scenes can then proceed from none but <hi>Jove.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>Caeſario</hi> ſaw it was in vain to ſtrive,</l>
               <l>His wavering Forces cou'd no Succour give;</l>
               <l>Unto what purpoſe was it to oppoſe,</l>
               <l>Or ſacrifice his Troops to ſtronger Foes?</l>
               <l>He orders all his Army to disband;</l>
               <l>They quit their Poſts, &amp; know no more Command.</l>
               <l>He's now diſtreſs'd, forſaken, and alone,</l>
               <l>Looks round, and views a naked, empty Throne.</l>
               <pb n="110" facs="tcp:46801:57"/>
               <l>Of all the Charms of Greatneſs now bereft,</l>
               <l>Not one of all his ſoothing Minions left;</l>
               <l>Thoſe Strains of Pow'r which late the <hi>Romans</hi> taught,</l>
               <l>Strains that employ'd their Tongues, and ev'ry Thought;</l>
               <l>Thoſe Draughts of Grandeur, &amp; that vaſt Renown,</l>
               <l>They all before his dazzl'd Eyes laid down;</l>
               <l>Like fleeting Clouds, they diſſipate in Air,</l>
               <l>Forſake the Sight, are fled, and diſappear.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Precarious <hi>Rome,</hi> that crowch'd before this Sun,</l>
               <l>When he in a Meridian Solſtice ſhone;</l>
               <l>That cheriſh'd all her Orders in his Beams,</l>
               <l>And urg'd his Counſels to ſuch wild Extremes;</l>
               <l>With alter'd Sails another Courſe ſhe ſteers,</l>
               <l>As faſt as Seas and haſty Winds can bear;</l>
               <l>Loaded with guilty Spoils, ſhe poſts away,</l>
               <l>Juſt like a Vulture with a raviſh'd Prey.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The Court the Council in diſorder leave,</l>
               <l>Advice they cou'd not hear, nor any give;</l>
               <pb n="111" facs="tcp:46801:57"/>
               <l>Confus'd, diſtracted, in Deſpair they run,</l>
               <l>And any Shelter ſeek, the Foe to ſhun:</l>
               <l>So when the Chariot of the Sun does riſe,</l>
               <l>And ſcatters Darkneſs from the ſhining Skies,</l>
               <l>The Birds of Night to Coverts wing away,</l>
               <l>Confounded with the Luſtre of the Day.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>Caeſario</hi> now encompaſs'd with Alarms,</l>
               <l>A Pris'ner falls to Great <hi>Auguſtus</hi> Arms;</l>
               <l>He falls a Captive, not a Victim here,</l>
               <l>More Mercy in his Conduct did appear;</l>
               <l>Mercy, to <hi>Rome</hi> a very Stranger grown,</l>
               <l>They know no Kindred, no Acquaintance own;</l>
               <l>Her Fiery Trials have excluded quite</l>
               <l>That Attribute, and urg'd it to a Flight.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Now Muſe proceed, and other Actions tell,</l>
               <l>That in this wond'rous Turn of State befell;</l>
               <l>If ever Wonders were convey'd to Men,</l>
               <l>If we'll but credit what our Eyes have ſeen,</l>
               <l>Great as of old they were, when <hi>Aegypt</hi>'s Land</l>
               <l>Provok'd the Weight of an Almighty Hand;</l>
               <pb n="112" facs="tcp:46801:58"/>
               <l>When Miracle on Miracle did crowd,</l>
               <l>And Great <hi>Jehovah</hi> ſpoke by <hi>Moſes</hi> loud;</l>
               <l>Who can to th' Height of Heav'ns high Conduct ſoar?</l>
               <l>Can feeble Man thoſe Starry Realms explore?</l>
               <l>Our Reaſon cannot antidate the Doom,</l>
               <l>But we can tell of Bleſſings when they come.</l>
               <l>Cou'd ever People ſuch Deliv'rance boaſt?</l>
               <l>No purple Rivers of our Blood were loſt;</l>
               <l>The Land with no polluted Streams was ſtain'd,</l>
               <l>An eaſie, bloodleſs Victory we gain'd;</l>
               <l>Their guilty Cauſe cou'd not the Teſt abide,</l>
               <l>They had not Heav'n nor Juſtice on their Side.</l>
               <l>Let <hi>Rome</hi> eſſay to interrupt no more,</l>
               <l>For Heav'n has other Vengeance yet in ſtore;</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Britannia</hi>'s Church is its peculiar Care,</l>
               <l>She needs not <hi>Rome</hi>'s inſulting <hi>Bulls</hi> to fear.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>Caeſario</hi>'s Strength disbanded all by Land,</l>
               <l>Now in the Fleet his Admirals loſe Command;</l>
               <pb n="113" facs="tcp:46801:58"/>
               <l>The ſtubborn Crews wou'd no Obedience pay,</l>
               <l>An Anchor wou'd not weigh to put to Sea;</l>
               <l>They wou'd not fight at <hi>Rome</hi>'s imperious Call,</l>
               <l>Nor be the Inſtruments of <hi>Albion</hi>'s Fall:</l>
               <l>Silent each Gun within the Port-hole ſtood,</l>
               <l>They wou'd not launch a Veſſel to the Flood.</l>
               <l>In this Diſtreſs, in dead of ſilent Night,</l>
               <l>When twinkling Stars ſupply'd Defect of Light,</l>
               <l>A Barque <hi>Caeſario</hi> boards with ſecret Friends,</l>
               <l>And ſtreight to <hi>Gallia</hi>'s Coaſts his Courſe he bends.</l>
               <l>So <hi>Perſia</hi>'s Monarch, when to <hi>Greece</hi> he came,</l>
               <l>And led on Millions by his powerful Name,</l>
               <l>Yet in a trifling Boat is forc'd away,</l>
               <l>So ſmall a Veſſel <hi>Xerxes</hi> did convey.</l>
               <l>The riſing Winds his Voyage did oppoſe,</l>
               <l>The very Elements proclaim'd his Foes;</l>
               <l>The Weather forc'd him back on <hi>Albion</hi>'s Shore,</l>
               <l>And he becomes a Pris'ner, as before.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Impartial Readers let their Judgments give,</l>
               <l>And future Times Intelligence receive;</l>
               <pb n="114" facs="tcp:46801:59"/>
               <l>And let the Tenets of our Church be ſhown,</l>
               <l>Blood is an Off'ring to her Rules unknown:</l>
               <l>Let <hi>Rome,</hi> and let <hi>Geneva</hi> bluſh for ſhame,</l>
               <l>To raiſe by their Unchriſtian Acts a Fame.</l>
               <l>Review the Revolutions of our State,</l>
               <l>Since <hi>Normans</hi> to our <hi>Annals</hi> gave a Date,</l>
               <l>And tell me where a Captiv'd Monarch's found,</l>
               <l>That periſh'd not by ſome untimely Wound:</l>
               <l>Too true we read their Deaths in ev'ry Shape,</l>
               <l>None e'er permitted were to make Eſcape.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>Caeſario</hi> has his Freedom once again,</l>
               <l>On Board he goes, puts forth upon the Main;</l>
               <l>He flies to <hi>Gallia</hi>'s Monarch for Supply,</l>
               <l>As an <hi>Aſylum</hi> in Extremity.</l>
               <l>What can he from the treach'rous <hi>Franks</hi> expect?</l>
               <l>They'll not for his, but their own Ends project;</l>
               <l>They'll play the Game, for their Advantage, high,</l>
               <l>And reap the fatteſt Spoils of Victory.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>At home the Nobles in Convention met,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Achates</hi> firſt in that Great Council ſate;</l>
               <pb n="115" facs="tcp:46801:59"/>
               <l>The Common Cauſe oblig'd to chuſe a Chief,</l>
               <l>To give to the diſorder'd State Relief:</l>
               <l>The Head-ſtrong People, to Confuſion bent,</l>
               <l>Wou'd raze the Principles of Government,</l>
               <l>Or wou'd all Reaſon, as of old, decry,</l>
               <l>Precipitate into an <hi>Anarchy:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>A future War impending on the Land,</l>
               <l>A quick Diſpatch of Bus'neſs did command.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Hybernia</hi> all diſarm'd, nor Sword, nor Spear,</l>
               <l>Was with our <hi>Albion</hi>'s Sons permitted there;</l>
               <l>Like <hi>Iſrael</hi>'s Tribes, for Tillage-tools they go,</l>
               <l>And court Convenience from a dangerous Foe.</l>
               <l>That <hi>Gallia</hi> Potent was by Land and Sea,</l>
               <l>A Pow'rful, Active, Vig'lant Enemy;</l>
               <l>Her Force more ſtrong, more num'rous than of old,</l>
               <l>Than any former Chronicle enroll'd;</l>
               <l>That her New Conqueſts were themſelves a State,</l>
               <l>Realms large enough for any Potentate;</l>
               <l>For certain ſhe wou'd with <hi>Caeſario</hi> join,</l>
               <l>With Intereſts cloſe united both combine.</l>
               <pb n="116" facs="tcp:46801:60"/>
               <l>That <hi>Europe</hi>'s Eyes did on our Counſels wait,</l>
               <l>To take their Meaſures all from this Debate:</l>
               <l>In ſhort, all Contradiction overcome,</l>
               <l>A Settlement muſt be diſpatch'd at home:</l>
               <l>Here lay the Difficulty of the Cauſe,</l>
               <l>It muſt be done agreeable to Laws.</l>
               <l>And now Debates upon Debates ariſe,</l>
               <l>One Argument another ſtill ſupplies:</l>
               <l>From Government in general, they come</l>
               <l>To what's our Conſtitution here at home;</l>
               <l>And thence on ſeveral Topicks they enlarge,</l>
               <l>And briskly round they one another charge.</l>
               <l>Who can <hi>Britannia</hi>'s vacant Throne ſuppoſe?</l>
               <l>Who e'er an <hi>Interregnum</hi> did diſcloſe?</l>
               <l>It's granted, when th' Incumbent Monarch dies,</l>
               <l>That very Minute the next Heir ſupplies;</l>
               <l>And thus the Chain continu'd Links ſecure,</l>
               <l>For endleſs Generations to endure.</l>
               <l>Again—</l>
               <pb n="117" facs="tcp:46801:60"/>
               <l>Was ever Forfeit of the Scepter made?</l>
               <l>Or can the Crown be by the Prince betray'd?</l>
               <l>What Judge their Sovereign's Errors can inſpect?</l>
               <l>Or who preſumes his Actions to direct?</l>
               <l>The People all muſt paſſively comply,</l>
               <l>And not into th' Imperial Archives pry;</l>
               <l>But if a Subject has a Pow'r to make</l>
               <l>Enquiries, ev'ry Subject muſt partake;</l>
               <l>The Judges then are num'rous as the Crowd,</l>
               <l>By which a Train of Nonſenſe is allow'd.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>To theſe <hi>Achates</hi> wiſely makes reply,</l>
               <l>Let's firſt digeſt how our Foundations lie;</l>
               <l>Let's ſearch the <hi>Baſis</hi> of the Pile we rear,</l>
               <l>That will demonſtrate all we argue clear.</l>
               <l>'Twou'd tedious be paſt Actions to unfold,</l>
               <l>And to review the Managements of old;</l>
               <l>In ſev'ral Reigns what various Turns were found,</l>
               <l>How King &amp; People danc'd the wond'rous Round:</l>
               <l>Th' Employment of our preſent Thoughts is, how</l>
               <l>We find the State, and rightly that to know;</l>
               <pb n="118" facs="tcp:46801:61"/>
               <l>How in theſe Days it is tranſmitted down,</l>
               <l>How Subjects are engag'd, and how the Crown;</l>
               <l>Few Propoſitions will explain the Thing,</l>
               <l>And true, and regulated Notions bring;</l>
               <l>The Legiſlative Pow'r, we'll firſt enquire,</l>
               <l>Who't is to this Dominion does aſpire:</l>
               <l>That, firſt diſclos'd, will other Heads diſplay,</l>
               <l>And tell what it's to Govern, what Obey.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Why it's allow'd Three ſev'ral Ranks are found,</l>
               <l>That give to Law its Reins, and fix its Bound;</l>
               <l>Not any Two of theſe diſtinct can frame</l>
               <l>An Act Coercive, or give Law a Name:</l>
               <l>But when all Three Unite with joint Conſent,</l>
               <l>We're all oblig'd, it's <hi>Act of Parliament.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Nor any of theſe Orders can make void</l>
               <l>What was before eſtabliſh'd and allow'd.</l>
               <l>Well then, the King and People both are bound,</l>
               <l>And neither ought to paſs this Sacred Mound:</l>
               <l>The King's beyond the Peoples Rage ſecure,</l>
               <l>They neither can a Yoke from each endure.</l>
               <pb n="119" facs="tcp:46801:61"/>
               <l>This Privilege we find is thus entail'd,</l>
               <l>And it won'd be Our Fault if now it fail'd:</l>
               <l>It's plain, <hi>What's Humane poſſible may err,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And from this Gen'ral then we thus infer,</l>
               <l>Whoe'er's the firſt Tranſgreſſor of this Rule,</l>
               <l>Without a Law he lives, without Controul,</l>
               <l>Till he within due Compaſs is compell'd,</l>
               <l>And to the Laws preceding forc'd to yield.</l>
               <l>Since only Two Tranſgreſſors are the All,</l>
               <l>Or Prince, or People, muſt be Criminal.</l>
               <l>We too too many Inſtances do find</l>
               <l>Of Popular Commiſſions in this kind,</l>
               <l>Whilſt each Offender hurries on his Fate,</l>
               <l>And falls a Victim to th' incenſed State.</l>
               <l>And if a Prince will beyond Compaſs fly,</l>
               <l>And own no Obligations to this Tie,</l>
               <l>He moves excentrick, and defies all Pow'r,</l>
               <l>Till Fate and Fortune preſs his haſty Hour.</l>
               <l>This granted then—</l>
               <pb n="120" facs="tcp:46801:62"/>
               <l>Why ſhou'd we farther in Debate proceed?</l>
               <l>Important Bus'neſs urges on our Speed;</l>
               <l>We muſt not long in this Affair ſit ſtill,</l>
               <l>But with a Prince the vacant Throne muſt fill.</l>
               <l>He ſtopp'd; the Nobles with conſenting Voice</l>
               <l>Concur, and on <hi>Auguſtus</hi> fix their Choice.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>Britannia</hi> now exerts a ſplendid Scene,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Auguſtus</hi> King, and Fair <hi>Auguſta</hi> Queen.</l>
               <lg type="triplet">
                  <l>If ever Souls of pure Angelick Flames</l>
                  <l>Cou'd actuate below an Humane Frame,</l>
                  <l>They ſure are center'd here, and both the ſame.</l>
               </lg>
               <l>For ſure thoſe bleſs'd, unbody'd Minds above,</l>
               <l>Are not compos'd of ſofter Seeds of Love.</l>
               <l>Their Thoughts and their Intentions were but one,</l>
               <l>No jarring Feuds claſh or diſturb the Throne:</l>
               <l>Their mutual Sway extended o'er the Land,</l>
               <l>The People know in Both but one Command.</l>
               <l>But when rough Wars her <hi>Heroe</hi> calls to Arms,</l>
               <l>To meet, with equal Pow'rs, his Foes Alarms</l>
               <pb n="121" facs="tcp:46801:62"/>
               <l>At home <hi>Auguſta</hi> does alone reſide,</l>
               <l>And in her Conduct all ſecure, confide.</l>
               <l>She did the Glory of her Sex maintain,</l>
               <l>And ſhew'd a true Heroick Female Reign.</l>
               <l>What cou'd a Kingdom more of Fate deſire?</l>
               <l>Can they to greater Happineſs aſpire?</l>
               <l>Like <hi>Iſrael</hi>'s Sons, from <hi>Pagan</hi> Bondage free,</l>
               <l>They've paſs'd by Wonder thro' the Scarlet Sea:</l>
               <l>But ſure ſome angry Stars diſturb our Iſle,</l>
               <l>And in new Jars <hi>Britannia</hi>'s Race embroil;</l>
               <l>Some ſurly Comet hovers o'er our Shore,</l>
               <l>And ſtrives to dye the Plains again with Gore.</l>
               <l>In furious, moody Heats we now divide,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Auguſtus</hi> ſome, ſome for <hi>Caeſario</hi>'s Side:</l>
               <l>In Diſcontents new Factions they foment,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Albion</hi> of its own Woe th' eſtabliſh'd Inſtrument.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Let's dive, my Muſe, into this wild Abyſs,</l>
               <l>And ſearch where the contagious Venom lies;</l>
               <l>Doubtleſs the dark Retreats we may diſcloſe,</l>
               <l>And prove the Strength of our preſuming Foes:</l>
               <pb n="122" facs="tcp:46801:63"/>
               <l>Let's backwards look with an impartial Eye,</l>
               <l>T' unfold the Volumes of this Myſtery.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>In Times preceding theſe, when Winds blew high,</l>
               <l>And mounting Billows emulate the Sky,</l>
               <l>High on theſe Waves our Sacred <hi>Druids</hi> bore,</l>
               <l>Beyond the very Spheres of Reaſon ſoar;</l>
               <l>Upon theſe ſwelling Tides aloft they ride,</l>
               <l>The honeſt Layman's left without a Guide:</l>
               <l>Beyond his Sight to diſtant Orbs they go,</l>
               <l>And leave him grov'ling in ſtrange Paths below,</l>
               <l>This ſurely was the Error of the Times,</l>
               <l>It cannot wholly be alledg'd their Crimes:</l>
               <l>It's plain, Miſtakes on either Side are found;</l>
               <l>For many took it at the firſt Rebound,</l>
               <l>Eſpous'd the Words, and loſt the genuine Senſe</l>
               <l>Of what the Learned <hi>Druids</hi> did diſpenſe.</l>
               <l>'Twas certain ſome advanc'd too high the Theme,</l>
               <l>Preſs'd it indeed to an abus'd Extreme;</l>
               <l>But where a wilful Error was the Fault,</l>
               <l>Regard them now as Foes not worthy thought;</l>
               <pb n="123" facs="tcp:46801:63"/>
               <l>For by a ſtrict Implicite Awe is meant</l>
               <l>As far as Law, is known in juſt Extent;</l>
               <l>Or otherwiſe all Order we diſplace,</l>
               <l>And launch into a vaſt unbounded Space:</l>
               <l>We muſt our Reaſon and our Senſe let fly,</l>
               <l>Sink lower than a dull <hi>Democracy.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>If by <hi>Obedience Paſſive</hi> was deſign'd</l>
               <l>Each Subject to his Sovereign's Will to bind,</l>
               <l>And from his ſole Decrees to wait his Doom,</l>
               <l>Protection then by Law is overcome,</l>
               <l>Our very Fundamentals are o'erthrown,</l>
               <l>We ſtand like ſenſeleſs Herds around the Throne.</l>
               <l>And then allow our Prince wou'd <hi>Mahomet</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Adore, and <hi>Mecha</hi> make the Holy Seat;</l>
               <l>Or that he ſtrain'd ſo far Imperial Awe,</l>
               <l>As we to Monkeys, Onions, Calves muſt bow,</l>
               <l>Which blind Obedience diſtant Nations pay,</l>
               <l>We muſt ſubmit, or fall a ſuff'ring Prey.</l>
               <l>Suppoſe this true—</l>
               <pb n="124" facs="tcp:46801:64"/>
               <l>Why then we're conquer'd, at Diſcretion are,</l>
               <l>Like vanquiſh'd Soldiers, Priſoners of War;</l>
               <l>The boundleſs Sword becomes Coercive Law,</l>
               <l>To keep ſubmiſſive Slaves in ſervile awe.</l>
               <l>But they object,—</l>
               <l>Our Sacred Oaths to ſtrict Obſervance bind,</l>
               <l>An Oath is as a Sacrament deſign'd;</l>
               <l>And we this great Solemnity addreſs'd</l>
               <l>Unto the King, in artleſs Words expreſs'd.</l>
               <l>It's true: But unto <hi>Albion</hi>'s King we ſwore,</l>
               <l>King as the Laws had made him ſo before:</l>
               <l>If in another Senſe we take the Thing,</l>
               <l>We're Traytors, and erect another King;</l>
               <l>We ceaſe as Subjects, and we break the Law;</l>
               <l>Hence many fatal Conſequences draw.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>No more with weak Amuſements let our Foes</l>
               <l>Theſe Trifles, and their Impotence impoſe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Our Muſter'd Forces for the Field prepare,</l>
               <l>And Great <hi>Auguſtus</hi> Heads them on for War;</l>
               <pb n="125" facs="tcp:46801:64"/>
               <l>He, like an old experienc'd Lion, knows</l>
               <l>Each Gin, and ev'ry Covert of the Foes:</l>
               <l>They, in their Native Heat, and furious Rage,</l>
               <l>Like untaught Youth, precipitate, engage;</l>
               <l>He, like a Sun, thro' the whole Maſs does ſhine,</l>
               <l>Inſtructs them with unerring Diſcipline.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Diſtreſs'd <hi>Hybernia</hi> calls for ſpeedy Aid,</l>
               <l>A cruel Carnage there, and Ruine's made;</l>
               <l>The <hi>Britiſh</hi> Int'reſt all was overcome,</l>
               <l>It fell a plunder'd Sacrifice to <hi>Rome.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>To th'utmoſt North <hi>Caeſario</hi>'s Forces gone,</l>
               <l>All but one Corner of the Iſle's their own;</l>
               <l>Theſe ſervile Souls, that meer Obedience knew,</l>
               <l>Aſſume th' Aſcendant, and their Lords ſubdue;</l>
               <l>Like antick Mimicks clad in awkerd Dreſs,</l>
               <l>Their Pride, and Native Ignorance confeſs;</l>
               <l>The ſpurious Offspring of the God of War,</l>
               <l>They <hi>Gibeonites,</hi> and lab'ring Vaſſals are;</l>
               <l>They not for Empire faſhion'd, but the Spade,</l>
               <l>Shou'd ne'er attempt Fames Glories to invade.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb n="126" facs="tcp:46801:65"/>
               <l>A ſpeedy Succour is diſpatch'd away,</l>
               <l>The Tranſport-Veſſels, burden'd, croſs the Sea;</l>
               <l>At Anchor now within the <hi>Lough</hi> they ride,</l>
               <l>In ſpite of Forts, and Booms, the Tow'n ſupply'd:</l>
               <l>A Town, which in all Ages yet to come,</l>
               <l>In Fame's large Rolls may juſtly challenge room.</l>
               <l>This was the laſt Retreat the <hi>Britans</hi> held;</l>
               <l>The conqu'ring Foe had urg'd them from the Field:</l>
               <l>What weak Efforts they had eſſay'd before,</l>
               <l>Were but to fluſh the Enemy the more;</l>
               <l>Like Swarms of Bees, they cluſter in a Crowd,</l>
               <l>And here th'inſulting <hi>Teagues</hi> to wonder ſtood;</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Auguſtus</hi> Genius ſure did them inſpire,</l>
               <l>And kindl'd in their Breaſts this Martial Fire.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The Army breaks up Ground before the Town,</l>
               <l>Led by a <hi>Gallic</hi> Chief, hot for Renown;</l>
               <l>The Garriſon within was weak and raw,</l>
               <l>No Order they, no Diſcipline they know;</l>
               <pb n="127" facs="tcp:46801:65"/>
               <l>They practiſe not the uſeful Rules of War,</l>
               <l>But, like an Head-ſtrong Mob, unruly are;</l>
               <l>Commanders all, they act as they think fit,</l>
               <l>Scarce to a known Superior they ſubmit.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And now with Show'rs of Bombs the Town's oppreſs'd,</l>
               <l>Fatigu'd all Day, all Night they know no reſt:</l>
               <l>A riſing Mount there was o'er-look'd the Town,</l>
               <l>The Foe on this Advantage plants him down,</l>
               <l>And to erect their Batt'ries ſtreight prepare,</l>
               <l>There fix their murd'ring Inſtruments of War.</l>
               <l>The Garriſon knew how to prize this Poſt,</l>
               <l>If there the Foe entrench'd, the Town was loſt:</l>
               <l>They ſally like a wild, diſorder'd Crew,</l>
               <l>Not into Ranks, nor marſhall'd Order drew;</l>
               <l>Preſs'd forwards like an undigeſted Throng,</l>
               <l>And each one bids his Comerade <hi>March along.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>See what Deſpair, with Fury join'd, can do!</l>
               <l>Juſt like a Torrent, all they overthrow:</l>
               <pb n="128" facs="tcp:46801:66"/>
               <l>Well-order'd Files confuſed Numbers charge,</l>
               <l>And thro' their ſlaughter'd Lines their Way en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>large;</l>
               <l>They force the Works, all Oppoſition beat,</l>
               <l>And urge them backwards with a baſe Retreat;</l>
               <l>Stretch'd o nthe Field the haughty <hi>Franks</hi> they leave,</l>
               <l>Their <hi>Gallick</hi> Gen'ral there acquir'd a Grave.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The Foe by this Defeat more wary grown,</l>
               <l>Reſolves by Famine to reduce the Town;</l>
               <l>They all Things for a ling'ring Siege prepare,</l>
               <l>And by their dull Delays prolong the War:</l>
               <l>Yet dreadful Bombs from yauning Mortars fly,</l>
               <l>And with their fiery Trains aſpire the Sky,</l>
               <l>Then ſinking down with a reſiſtleſs Blow,</l>
               <l>In certain Ruine bury all below.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>It's now a meagre Foe aſſaults the Walls,</l>
               <l>And louder than their noiſie Mortars bawls;</l>
               <l>Deep diſmal Hollows in the Cheeks take place,</l>
               <l>Shrunk Eyes, and trembling Jaws diſguiſe the Face;</l>
               <pb n="129" facs="tcp:46801:66"/>
               <l>The Features all diſtorted did appear,</l>
               <l>And piteous Groans impending Fate declare;</l>
               <l>Sad woful Sights the Landskip ſtill maintain,</l>
               <l>Meer Skeletons compleat the ghaſtly Train:</l>
               <l>In ſhort, imperious Want diſtreſs'd them more</l>
               <l>Than all the horrid Shapes of Death before:</l>
               <l>Their Stores exhauſted, yield no more their Corn;</l>
               <l>They look on one another all forlorn;</l>
               <l>Their pinch'd Allowance now their Wants pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claim,</l>
               <l>They knew Proviſion only by a Name;</l>
               <l>Baſe Animals their Appetites entice,</l>
               <l>On ſlaughter'd Dogs they feed, on Rats and Mice;</l>
               <l>Thoſe very Brutes that eat their Crums before,</l>
               <l>Now in their Deaths diſcharge their treſpaſs'd Score:</l>
               <l>The Foe, the Famine, and Diſtempers join,</l>
               <l>And in a mortal Triple League combine;</l>
               <l>The Bloody Flux did in their Bowels rage,</l>
               <l>And horrid Gripes a dreadful Combate wage;</l>
               <pb n="130" facs="tcp:46801:67"/>
               <l>Life with ſuch loſs of Blood muſt ſurely fail,</l>
               <l>Soon o'er that ſhining Lamp it did prevail;</l>
               <l>Nor Food, nor Phyſick had they to give Eaſe,</l>
               <l>To comfort Life, and conquer the Diſeaſe:</l>
               <l>But yet to give theſe truſty Souls their Due,</l>
               <l>Thoſe Ills, united thus, cou'd not ſubdue;</l>
               <l>They'd hear no Proffers from the Enemy,</l>
               <l>Wou'd rather all Extremes of Suff'ring try:</l>
               <lg type="triplet">
                  <l>This reſcu'd Town preſents an hopeful Scene,</l>
                  <l>This Town, defended by ſuch wondrous Men,</l>
                  <l>Is the firſt Trophy of <hi>Auguſtus</hi> Reign.</l>
               </lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>Albania</hi> next provokes a quick Relief;</l>
               <l>Fierce Troops, commanded by a Warlike Chief,</l>
               <l>Like gathering Clouds that muſter in the Air,</l>
               <l>Were now juſt burſting into open War.</l>
               <l>This Province had endur'd <hi>Caeſario's</hi> Rage,</l>
               <l>Had felt the Sting and Laſh that gall'd the Age;</l>
               <l>Some Minds uneaſie, had diſturb'd the Throne,</l>
               <l>And ſet up ſtrange Inventions of their own;</l>
               <pb n="131" facs="tcp:46801:67"/>
               <l>All Laws Divine and Humane they diſdain,</l>
               <l>And faſhion'd impious Idols of the Brain;</l>
               <l>They often ſuffer'd in th' Efforts they made,</l>
               <l>Oft has their guilty Blood Atonement paid.</l>
               <l>Pity the firſt Reformers here did fail;</l>
               <l>They ſhou'd have better taught their early Zeal;</l>
               <l>A right Inſtruction then had ſtamp'd the Mind,</l>
               <l>To order all divinely had inclin'd;</l>
               <l>Like <hi>Albion</hi>'s Church, th' Apoſtles Forms they'd known,</l>
               <l>And not in theſe digreſſive By-ways gone:</l>
               <l>Howe'er, the People bold and martial are,</l>
               <l>Inur'd to Hardſhip, and the Toils of War.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>A Potent Aid is early ſent away,</l>
               <l>To put it to th' Deciſion of a Day;</l>
               <l>A brisk and hot Engagement does enſue,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Auguſtus</hi> Forces yield, the Foes purſue.</l>
               <l>Here <hi>Fortune</hi> her Inconſtancy diſplays,</l>
               <l>She's truly <hi>Fortune</hi> by ſuch Acts as theſe.</l>
               <pb n="132" facs="tcp:46801:68"/>
               <l>Howe'er, the Leader of the Foes is ſlain,</l>
               <l>We loſe the Field, but yet the Vict'ry gain;</l>
               <l>Headleſs, confus'd, they now diſperſe, and run,</l>
               <l>And quit whate'er Advantage they had won:</l>
               <l>Domeſtick Foes Diſturbance give no more,</l>
               <l>The War's tranſplanted foreign from their Shore.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>But Troubles thicken like a waving Sea,</l>
               <l>One ſtill purſues, as th' other leads the way;</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Gallia</hi> provokes us to an open War,</l>
               <l>And either Side Hoſtilities declare:</l>
               <l>The Sea with Fleets is cover'd, o'er the Land</l>
               <l>Fierce Squadrons march, and dreadfully extend;</l>
               <l>The Warriors take their Arms, long ſlighted, down,</l>
               <l>A pregnant Harveſt courts them of Renown.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The King freſh Forces to <hi>Hybernia</hi> ſends,</l>
               <l>T'invade his Foes, and to relieve his Friends;</l>
               <l>A Gen'ral leads them of unqueſtion'd Fame,</l>
               <l>In Foreign Fields he challeng'd long a Name;</l>
               <l>In <hi>Gallick</hi> Marches, and Campaigns in <hi>Spain,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>He verdant Laurels never fail'd to gain.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb n="133" facs="tcp:46801:68"/>
               <l>
                  <hi>Auguſtus</hi> knew his <hi>Britiſh</hi> Soldiers were</l>
               <l>Of Courage large, but unexpert in War;</l>
               <l>Some Veterane Troops to theirs he wiſely joins,</l>
               <l>His Followers all of old, and fills their Lines.</l>
               <l>The chearful Army leave their Native Shore,</l>
               <l>Eager the Foe thro' Perils to explore;</l>
               <l>Like their great Sires of old, they'll force the Tide,</l>
               <l>To overthrow <hi>Hybernia</hi>'s riſing Pride.</l>
               <l>The friendly Billows to the Fleet are kind,</l>
               <l>And <hi>Aeolus</hi> indulg'd them with a Wind;</l>
               <l>Their noiſie Terrors their Approach proclaim;</l>
               <l>They, <hi>Caeſar</hi>-like, but ſaw, and overcame.</l>
               <l>In Pannick Fright their Towns and Forts they yield,</l>
               <l>And their retreating Army quits the Field.</l>
               <l>So quick their Flight, like driving Clouds they flew,</l>
               <l>It was more hard to find 'em, than ſubdue.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Some warlike Troops were to <hi>Caeſario</hi> join'd,</l>
               <l>Of <hi>Britiſh</hi> Birth, but an Apoſtate Kind;</l>
               <pb n="134" facs="tcp:46801:69"/>
               <l>Theſe view'd this Flight, and burning with diſdain,</l>
               <l>Rally'd the ſcatter'd Men to Form again.</l>
               <l>A Plat convenient for an Army's found,</l>
               <l>By Nature ſtrong, an advantageous Ground;</l>
               <l>With deep Entrenchments they their Front de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend,</l>
               <l>In Length and large Circumference extend;</l>
               <l>Ramparts at equal Diſtance they prepare,</l>
               <l>And mount their Cannon ready for the War;</l>
               <l>Each Avenue into the Camp is barr'd,</l>
               <l>In each Deſile, and Paſs, there ſtands a Guard;</l>
               <l>Succeeding Watches all their Works ſurround,</l>
               <l>They're jealous of the leaſt approaching Sound.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Caeſario</hi>'s Army thus encamped lies,</l>
               <l>Deſies the Foe, and's fearleſs of Surprize:</l>
               <l>Numbers of Troops unto his Camp repair,</l>
               <l>From ev'ry Quarter, arm'd to meet the War.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Mean time, old <hi>Fabius</hi> marches ſlowly on,</l>
               <l>Each Motion of the Foe to him was known;</l>
               <pb n="135" facs="tcp:46801:69"/>
               <l>His active Spies their certain News relate,</l>
               <l>And give a true Account of ev'ry State;</l>
               <l>The Strength and Numbers of their Troops he knew,</l>
               <l>And of his own he takes exact Review:</l>
               <lg type="triplet">
                  <l>For open Fight they too unequal were,</l>
                  <l>Their Odds too diſproportionate appear;</l>
                  <l>So he reſolves on a Defenſive War.</l>
               </lg>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Within a League of them a <hi>Villa</hi> ſtood,</l>
               <l>And by it curles along a murm'ring Flood,</l>
               <l>A Paſs convenient to ſecure the Land</l>
               <l>Which his victorious Army did command;</l>
               <l>And near adjoining lies an uſeful Bay;</l>
               <l>Hither Proviſion's daily brought by Sea;</l>
               <l>The Tranſport-Veſſels here at Anchor ride,</l>
               <l>Await their Orders, and the Camp ſupply'd:</l>
               <l>He mounts of ſtrong Artillery a Train,</l>
               <l>And riſing Works that wou'd a Storm ſuſtain;</l>
               <l>His Engineers their num'rous Hands employ,</l>
               <l>They regularly entrench and fortifie;</l>
               <pb n="136" facs="tcp:46801:70"/>
               <l>Parties piqueering round for Forage go,</l>
               <l>And often meet, and bicker with the Foe:</l>
               <l>Lodg'd here ſecure, it's now reſolv'd to ſtay,</l>
               <l>Until the Foe to Quarters leads the Way.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Of all the num'rous Nations that await</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Auguſtus</hi> Arms, and tempt a Martial Fate,</l>
               <l>Some <hi>Gallic</hi> Subjects by a Prince ſevere</l>
               <l>Forc'd from their Homes, receive Protection here;</l>
               <l>Liſted in Forms of War, he entertains,</l>
               <l>They ſerve beneath his Standard this Campaign:</l>
               <l>With theſe diſtreſs'd Reform'd, ſome Natives come,</l>
               <l>Maſh'd cloſely all, true Votaries of <hi>Rome:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Theſe with the Foe compact a black Deſign,</l>
               <l>Confederate in the Treachery they join;</l>
               <l>In Dead of Night, when ſilent Sleep invades</l>
               <l>The drowſie Camp, and covers all with Shades,</l>
               <l>They, on the Out-guard poſted, wou'd receive</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Caeſario</hi>'s Troops, and all to Ruine give:</l>
               <l>Yet to diſguiſe and counterfeit it cloſe,</l>
               <l>They'd entertain them loud with Fire and Noiſe;</l>
               <pb n="137" facs="tcp:46801:70"/>
               <l>Safely they might approach, no Ball was there</l>
               <l>That wou'd a Death convey, all Smoak and Air.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>This Treaſon to the Gen'ral is diſclos'd,</l>
               <l>Their hated Corps on Gibbets are expos'd:</l>
               <l>This Project baffl'd, ſtartl'd high the Foes,</l>
               <l>And all their ſettl'd Meaſures overthrows;</l>
               <l>Howe'er, for once they draw out on the Hills,</l>
               <l>And ev'ry little Vale their Squadrons fills;</l>
               <l>Bravado all, it only threatn'd War,</l>
               <l>A Martial Landskip moving from afar.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>But now the Muſe muſt ſing a woful Scene,</l>
               <l>Of <hi>Britiſh Heroes</hi> that lay dead, not ſlain;</l>
               <l>Thoſe Men whom open Dangers ne'er deterr'd,</l>
               <l>Who Death above a Vaſſalage preferr'd,</l>
               <l>They now before a Foe reſiſtleſs fall,</l>
               <l>Without a Wound they find a Funeral.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>A Winters Camp, the Seaſon all ſevere,</l>
               <l>Clouds riſe aloft, and gather in the Air,</l>
               <l>On Points of Mountains burſt, and ſcatter wide</l>
               <l>In Deluges, and form a conſtant Tide;</l>
               <pb n="138" facs="tcp:46801:71"/>
               <l>Perpetual Showers the dying Men bemoan,</l>
               <l>From ev'ry Sphere there iſſu'd forth a Groan.</l>
               <l>This Execution's wondrous from the Skies,</l>
               <l>Like Crocodiles they weep, yet with their Tears deſtroy.</l>
               <l>Death made ſad Carnage, and a cruel Spoil;</l>
               <l>The ſick'ning Soldiers die in Rank and File,</l>
               <l>Their putrid Corps expos'd, offend the Eye,</l>
               <l>And ghaſtly Heaps in Tents entombed lie:</l>
               <l>Thoſe very Tents which late their Shelters were,</l>
               <l>Officiouſly become their Sepulchers;</l>
               <l>They fall in Numbers, and deform the Field;</l>
               <l>The Fields a ſad inhumane Harveſt yield:</l>
               <l>Death in its Slaughters no Diſtinction makes,</l>
               <l>The Soldier with his Officer it takes;</l>
               <l>From this Campaign they both together go,</l>
               <l>To take up Quarters in the Shades below.</l>
               <l>Proviſion fails, forbid by adverſe Winds;</l>
               <l>Sickneſs before, and Famine preſs'd behind;</l>
               <pb n="139" facs="tcp:46801:71"/>
               <l>Diſtempers rage beyond the Power of Art,</l>
               <l>No Drugs, no Compounds can Relief impart:</l>
               <l>Here no eſtabliſh'd Methods cou'd prevail;</l>
               <l>For what cou'd Phyſick do, where Life did fail?</l>
               <l>Where no Convenience for the Sick was found,</l>
               <l>But Millions of Diſaſters all ſurround?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>No Order here in Obſequies was ſhewn,</l>
               <l>Piles heap'd on Piles in hollow Caves were thrown,</l>
               <l>And many a Carcaſe ſcatter'd here and there,</l>
               <l>Was Food for Wolves, and Birds that wing in Air.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Thus Ruine reign'd with Arbitrary Pow'r,</l>
               <l>Theſe Wars of Heav'n, and not the Sword devour.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Ah! who can tell the Number of his Days?</hi>
               </l>
               <l>The Univerſe th' Almighty's Nod obeys:</l>
               <l>An armed Hoſt but ſlender Guard affords,</l>
               <l>When Heav'n, incens'd, draws its vindictive Sword.</l>
               <l>The Foe cou'd make no Market of our Ills,</l>
               <l>The ſame Deſtruction all his Quarters fills:</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>He firſt from Field removes, we next attend;</l>
               <l>And ſo this heavy, ſad Encampment ends.</l>
               <pb n="140" facs="tcp:46801:72"/>
               <l>Of all our Army, ſcarce one Third remains,</l>
               <l>Our Rolls cou'd ſcarce compleat Five thouſand Men;</l>
               <l>With theſe weak Pow'rs we all the North ſecure,</l>
               <l>And ev'ry hoſtile, bold Attack endure;</l>
               <l>Whate'er Aſſaults they make, are all in vain;</l>
               <l>They all the Toil, and all the Loſs ſuſtain.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Unto <hi>Auguſtus, Fabius</hi> ſends Expreſs,</l>
               <l>Acquaints him with his Loſs, and his Succeſs,</l>
               <l>How few his little Army did compoſe,</l>
               <l>And how he lay obnoxious to his Foes.</l>
               <l>Recruits were ſent his Army to relieve,</l>
               <l>Untill <hi>Auguſtus</hi> did himſelf arrive;</l>
               <l>He'd come, attended with a Warlike Train,</l>
               <l>And in <hi>Hybernia</hi> finiſh a Campaign.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Mean time <hi>Caeſario</hi> ſends to <hi>Gaul</hi> for Aid,</l>
               <l>Vaſt Stores prepar'd, and pow'rful Levies made:</l>
               <l>Some fam'd Commanders, that had won Renown</l>
               <l>In Wars, ſupported by the <hi>Gallick</hi> Crown,</l>
               <pb n="141" facs="tcp:46801:72"/>
               <l>Are hither ſent to manage this Affair,</l>
               <l>And Head <hi>Hybernia</hi>'s Natives to the War.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The Seaſon's come which <hi>Mars</hi>'s Off-ſpring warms,</l>
               <l>And calls the Valiant forth to ſhine in Arms:</l>
               <lg type="triplet">
                  <l>In verdant Fields when haughty Steeds can feed,</l>
                  <l>Their Strength renew'd, they're fiery to invade,</l>
                  <l>And bear their Riders on with rapid ſpeed.</l>
               </lg>
               <l>Two potent Armies Rival Kings lead on,</l>
               <l>One to regain, and one to keep a Throne.</l>
               <l>More glorious Scenes of War were ne'er diſplay'd,</l>
               <l>The Sword an ampler Harveſt never had:</l>
               <l>Not ſounding Fame has greater Actions told,</l>
               <l>Of Captains that ſurviv'd in Years of old;</l>
               <l>Not <hi>Caeſar</hi>'s War on large <hi>Pharſalia</hi>'s Plains,</l>
               <l>Which <hi>Lucan</hi> ſings in ſtrong and lofty Strains,</l>
               <l>Exceeds the Deeds of theſe two Rival-Foes,</l>
               <l>Nor more Heroick Enterprizes ſhows.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>One, with Revenge, and vaſt Ambition's Fire,</l>
               <l>His raviſh'd Crown and Scepter does aſpire;</l>
               <pb n="142" facs="tcp:46801:73"/>
               <l>Confederate with <hi>Gaul,</hi> eſpous'd by <hi>Rome,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>By Dint of War reſolves to overcome.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>A Train of Glories on this Side invite,</l>
               <l>And preſs <hi>Auguſtus</hi> forwards to the Fight;</l>
               <l>Religion, Laws, and wrong'd <hi>Britannia</hi>'s Cries,</l>
               <l>Inſpire the <hi>Heroe</hi> on to gain the Prize:</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Theſe pompous Sights the God of War beheld,</l>
               <l>And for a while ſtood Neuter in the Field.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>Caeſario</hi>'s Army by a Rivers ſide,</l>
               <l>Strongly entrench'd, <hi>Auguſtus</hi> does abide:</l>
               <l>Th' Aſſailant hazards when he ſtorms the Foe,</l>
               <l>Makes his Approach, and gives th'aſſaulting Blow.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>Caeſario</hi> at the Head of all his Men,</l>
               <l>A ſhort and pithy Harangue thus began:</l>
               <l>"You faithful Followers that eſpouſe my Side,</l>
               <l>"And hitherto an adverſe Fate have try'd,</l>
               <l>"Your Troubles all will center here this Day,</l>
               <l>"Purſue the Chace as Fortune leads the way:</l>
               <l>"Your Country long has been oppreſs'd by Fate,</l>
               <l>"Redreſs its Wrongs, its Freedoms vindicate;</l>
               <pb n="143" facs="tcp:46801:73"/>
               <l>"Once more a juſt Poſſeſſion ſtrive to take,</l>
               <l>"Remember this, for all your All's at ſtake.</l>
               <l>"Our ancient Forms of Worſhip we'll reſtore,</l>
               <l>"And Hereſie we'll baniſh from the Shore:</l>
               <l>"Your Courage only can Relief afford,</l>
               <l>"Your Safety is impendent on the Sword.</l>
               <l>Th' <hi>Hybernians</hi> ſhout, their moving Ranks prepare</l>
               <l>To Man their Works, and meet the Shock of War.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>Auguſtus</hi> mounted rides thro' all the Lines,</l>
               <l>A Martial Ardour in his Viſage ſhines;</l>
               <lg type="triplet">
                  <l>His ſparkling Eyes like darting Rays appear,</l>
                  <l>Diſpell whatever looks like Dread or Fear;</l>
                  <l>His Troops attentive, to theſe Words give Ear.</l>
               </lg>
               <l>"Come Fellow-Soldiers in ſo juſt a Cauſe,</l>
               <l>"You Champions for your Country, and its Laws,</l>
               <l>"Purſue the glorious Courſe you have begun,</l>
               <l>"And finiſh what's remaining to be done:</l>
               <l>"The Steps of your Great Predeceſſors tread;</l>
               <l>"Where-ever Danger does invite, I'll lead.</l>
               <pb n="144" facs="tcp:46801:74"/>
               <l>"All <hi>Europe</hi> waits the Iſſue of this Field,</l>
               <l>"The <hi>Britans</hi> cannot to <hi>Hybernians</hi> yield:</l>
               <l>"Behold the Foes that now in Arms appear,</l>
               <l>"They late your Vaſſals all, and Servants were:</l>
               <l>"Religion and your Rights provoke you on,</l>
               <l>"And Vict'ry waits with Laurels of Renown.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Now Trumpets Clangors, &amp; the Beat of Drums,</l>
               <l>All other little Noiſes overcome;</l>
               <l>In Intervals the Horſes Neighings far</l>
               <l>Proclaim the Muſick of approaching War:</l>
               <l>On either Side the teeming Cannon play,</l>
               <l>And diſmal Flaſhes unſeen Deaths convey:</l>
               <l>The ſpeaking Gaps in Squadrons tell the Fate</l>
               <l>Of ſlaughter'd Ranks, and the ſad Woe relate.</l>
               <l>Here Bodies piece-meal o'er the Field are ſtrew'd,</l>
               <l>And lie diſſected in a Sea of Blood;</l>
               <l>Arms, Legs, and Thighs, confus'd, in Heaps are found,</l>
               <l>And with diſhoneſt Burdens pave the Ground.</l>
               <pb n="145" facs="tcp:46801:74"/>
               <l>Here one disbowell'd gives an hideous Groan,</l>
               <l>And as he ſighs, Life thro' the Wound is gone;</l>
               <l>There ſcatter'd Brains with Blood polluted lie,</l>
               <l>And ſhatter'd Sculls around in pieces fly.</l>
               <l>The Cries and Groans of wounded, dying Men,</l>
               <l>Mix'd with the Claſh, ſad Harmony maintain;</l>
               <l>Whatever Tragick Fancies can ſuppoſe,</l>
               <l>Thoſe impious Scenes this Battel does diſcloſe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>To cloſer Fight <hi>Auguſtus</hi> leads them on,</l>
               <l>His awful Sword like diſtant Lightning ſhone;</l>
               <l>He on his Courſer plunges in the Flood,</l>
               <l>The Cryſtal Streams were ſoon diſtain'd with Blood;</l>
               <l>Cloſe by his Side his valiant Warriours fall,</l>
               <l>Yet others ſtill ſucceed, and fill the Wall.</l>
               <l>The <hi>Britans</hi> no Incitements need to move,</l>
               <l>They forward all to guard their Monarch ſtrove.</l>
               <l>In ſpite of Waves, and Banks, and armed Foes,</l>
               <l>He forward preſs'd, and plunges thro' the Ouze;</l>
               <pb n="146" facs="tcp:46801:75"/>
               <l>He gains the Shore, his waving Plumes appear,</l>
               <l>And ſtrike his Foes aghaſt with Pain and Fear.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The <hi>Macedonian</hi> thus the <hi>Granic</hi> paſs'd,</l>
               <l>Whilſt Vict'ry pearch'd upon his ſtreaming Creſt,</l>
               <l>Whilſt flying Nations quit th'ignoble Field,</l>
               <l>And to his Arms, prevailing, Homage yield.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>It's now the Tug of Battel but begins,</l>
               <l>Now claſhing Swords, and Peals of Volleys ring;</l>
               <l>Now Regiment with Regiment does meet,</l>
               <l>In uncouth, horrid Complements they greet;</l>
               <l>Granado Fuſes hiſs, and burn in Air,</l>
               <l>Then burſt, and ev'ry Piece a Ruine bears;</l>
               <l>The Sword, and ev'ry Inſtrument of War,</l>
               <l>Are fully gorg'd with Blood, and ſurfeit here.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>Auguſtus</hi> 'midſt this dang'rous Havock ſtands,</l>
               <l>And with a ſteady Conduct all commands;</l>
               <l>He waves his Sword, and leads them to the Charge,</l>
               <l>They thro' their broken Files their Way enlarge;</l>
               <l>Wheree'er he ſees recoiling Troops give way,</l>
               <l>He rallies them again, to ſtand the Day:</l>
               <pb n="147" facs="tcp:46801:75"/>
               <l>Rais'd by his Courage, new Aſſaults they dare,</l>
               <l>And alter ſtreight the pallid Face of War.</l>
               <l>Whilſt he in Heat of Battel thus proceeds,</l>
               <l>And ſtuns his frighted Foes with Martial Deeds,</l>
               <l>Upon his Shoulder he receives a Wound,</l>
               <l>The flowing Blood defiles him all around;</l>
               <l>Large was the Breach the miſſive Engine made;</l>
               <l>His faithful Guards till then were ne'er afraid;</l>
               <l>But now they fear, to ſee their Prince's Blood</l>
               <l>Deſcend in Streams, and form a Crimſon Flood.</l>
               <l>This Wound the more his Fury did excite,</l>
               <l>Fiercely he charges, and renews the Fight:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Caeſario</hi> ſaw the waning Field was loſt,</l>
               <l>His ſtaggering Troops, diſorder'd, quit their Poſts;</l>
               <l>The beſt, the braveſt of his Men lay ſlain,</l>
               <l>And faintly all the reſt the Fight maintain;</l>
               <l>Whilſt freſh Reſerves <hi>Auguſtus</hi> Forces join,</l>
               <l>But his ſpeak loud their Fears, and half decline;</l>
               <l>He ſounds Retreat, and his glad Troops obey,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Auguſtus</hi> claims the Trophies of the Day.</l>
               <pb n="148" facs="tcp:46801:76"/>
               <l>Here had he not reſtrain'd his Conqu'ring Pow'r,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Hybernian</hi> Brains had form'd a Bog all o'er.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The Plunder of the Field each Soldier ſhares,</l>
               <l>And Quarter's order'd to the Priſoners;</l>
               <l>The Wounded in the Hoſpitals they place,</l>
               <l>And <hi>Aeſculapius</hi> Sons afford them Eaſe;</l>
               <l>They in their Art as eminent appear,</l>
               <l>As the Battalions train'd in Rules of War;</l>
               <l>Balſamick Compounds in the Stores are found,</l>
               <l>To anſwer each Intention of a Wound.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Now all the Joys that Laurell'd Conqueſts yield,</l>
               <l>That <hi>Heroes</hi> gather in a Crimſon Field,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Auguſtus</hi> reaps from this ſucceſsful Day,</l>
               <l>And darting Glories thro' the Camp diſplays;</l>
               <l>When ſtreight he's told of an important Loſs,</l>
               <l>How 'mongſt the Slain was found Great <hi>Fabius,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Diſguis'd with Wounds and Blood, extended dead,</l>
               <l>With Piles of ſlaughter'd Foes around him ſpread,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Auguſtue</hi> with a Sigh his Fate bemoans,</l>
               <l>For ne'er had Soul been form'd ſo like his own,</l>
               <pb n="149" facs="tcp:46801:76"/>
               <l>The Pompous Rites of Fun'ral they prepare,</l>
               <l>Wreath him in Laurel, and the Spoils of War.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Streight to <hi>Auguſtus</hi> Court Expreſſes came,</l>
               <l>This grateful News of Victory proclaim;</l>
               <l>The joyful Youth with Bonfires warm the Skie,</l>
               <l>And fiery Rockets mount and burſt on high:</l>
               <l>Theſe Tidings ſtunn'd the Malecontents at home,</l>
               <l>In this Defeat too clear they ſaw their Doom.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>To cloſe Cabals they're ſummon'd all to meet,</l>
               <l>Of new Deſigns, and Enterprizes treat;</l>
               <l>Their hopeful Int'reſt in <hi>Hybernia</hi>'s loſt,</l>
               <l>Their Projects all in that Affair were croſs'd:</l>
               <l>They ſend Diſpatches ſtreight to <hi>Gaul</hi> away,</l>
               <l>To court their Navy to diſpute the Sea;</l>
               <l>If by Surprize they cou'd our Fleet deſtroy,</l>
               <l>No Tranſports then the Army cou'd ſupply,</l>
               <l>Their <hi>Riſing Sun</hi> might brave it o'er the Main,</l>
               <l>And they'd retrieve all they had loſt again.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Mean time <hi>Auguſtus</hi> Army marches on,</l>
               <l>And all our Cities the Great Conqu'ror own,</l>
               <pb n="150" facs="tcp:46801:77"/>
               <l>The Brave Deliv'rer's Praiſes celebrate,</l>
               <l>And each again poſſeſs'd his Ancient Seat;</l>
               <l>Thus far his baniſh'd Subjects are reſtor'd,</l>
               <l>And owe their Safeties to their Leading Lord.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>Caeſario</hi> routed, quits <hi>Hybernia</hi>'s Land,</l>
               <l>But to his Gen'rals leaves his laſt Commands,</l>
               <l>To make the War defenſive at their Home,</l>
               <l>Till large Supplies did to their Succour come;</l>
               <l>But if the Foe by freſh Attempts preſs'd on,</l>
               <l>To Man their Strong Holds, &amp; defend each Town;</l>
               <l>That thus they might the Enemy ſuſtain,</l>
               <l>And try once more their Fate the next Campaign.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>One Garriſon they held, well mann'd, &amp; ſtrong,</l>
               <l>Where <hi>Shannon</hi>'s Streams in Murmurs lave along;</l>
               <l>The ſtrongeſt that <hi>Hybernia</hi>'s Kingdom knows,</l>
               <l>And bold Reſiſtance oft had ſhewn the Foes;</l>
               <l>Its Works employ'd each skilful Engineer,</l>
               <l>All Sons of Art, expert in Rules of War.</l>
               <l>Thick Walls the Cities Circuits round command,</l>
               <l>And Baſtions at convenient Diſtance ſtand;</l>
               <pb n="151" facs="tcp:46801:77"/>
               <l>Deep Trenches Pales of ſharpn'd Wood ſecur'd,</l>
               <l>That Men on Duty ſeem'd to be Immur'd;</l>
               <l>Their mounted Guns diſmaying Proſpects yield,</l>
               <l>And ſcour around the low adjoining Fields.</l>
               <l>No ancient Forts cou'd with this Strength compare,</l>
               <l>So much they have improv'd the Art of War:</l>
               <l>But as in Herbs which noxious Juices fill,</l>
               <l>A Counter-poyſon ſtill the Venom kills,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Auguſtus</hi> by a Train as dreadful knows</l>
               <l>To make Approaches, and reduce his Foes.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>They had conſider'd where their Weakneſs lay,</l>
               <l>And on what Side they were expos'd a Prey;</l>
               <lg type="triplet">
                  <l>Too well the Strength of our Artill'ry's known,</l>
                  <l>If we before this Garriſon ſat down,</l>
                  <l>No Humane Pow'r cou'd ſave the ſinking Town.</l>
               </lg>
               <l>Our Conqu'ring Army now the Place ſurround,</l>
               <l>The chearful Pioneers break up the Ground;</l>
               <l>Our Batt'ring Pieces on the March were near,</l>
               <l>With plenteous Stores, and Tools adapt for War;</l>
               <pb n="152" facs="tcp:46801:78"/>
               <l>Security had lull'd us ſure aſleep,</l>
               <l>We'd ſurely drank of <hi>Lethe</hi>'s Fluid deep;</l>
               <l>Neglect there was that ſpoil'd this great Deſign,</l>
               <l>One Riſing Sun had brought them to our Lines;</l>
               <l>I'th' midſt of Shades, when Slumbers clos'd each Eye,</l>
               <l>And Thought lay bury'd in Obſcurity,</l>
               <l>Or Memory it ſelf cou'd not retain</l>
               <l>The Products of a wild prolifick Brain,</l>
               <l>An Ambuſh of the Foes our Guards ſurprize,</l>
               <l>Fill all with Blood, Confuſion, Wounds, &amp; Noiſe;</l>
               <l>The Powder-Stores flaſh bright, and ſound in Air,</l>
               <l>So near the Camp, they told aloud the War:</l>
               <l>They nail the Guns, the Carriages deſtroy,</l>
               <l>And all the needful Tools we ſhou'd employ.</l>
               <l>This Fact accompliſh'd, joyful, they retire,</l>
               <l>And leave whate'er's Combuſtible on fire.</l>
               <l>From neighb'ring Garriſons we draw Supplies,</l>
               <l>The Soldiers quick erect their Batteries,</l>
               <l>The Cannon play ſevere to force a Breach,</l>
               <l>And Bombs from Air an hideous Language teach:</l>
               <pb n="153" facs="tcp:46801:78"/>
               <l>Sure liſping Infants that eſcape the Doom,</l>
               <l>Will ne'er admire that Speech in Years to come;</l>
               <l>The Roofs of Houſes levell'd, ſtoop to Ground,</l>
               <l>The Bombs in deepeſt Cells and Caverns wound;</l>
               <l>Carcaſſes ſet the Buildings all on Fire,</l>
               <l>The Flame and Smoke the Firmament aſpire;</l>
               <l>New Lights were kindl'd in the ambient Air,</l>
               <l>And ſhone as bright as glaring <hi>Phaebus</hi> there.</l>
               <l>What cou'd they in this Exigency do?</l>
               <l>Fatigu'd with Toil, no Reſt their Eye-lids know;</l>
               <l>Diſturb'd by Night, and all diſtreſs'd by Day,</l>
               <l>Inceſſant ſtill the Guns and Mortars play:</l>
               <l>Their frequent Sallies no Advantage gain,</l>
               <l>They loſt their Youth, and dar'd Efforts in vain;</l>
               <l>Their laſt Defence depended on their Mines,</l>
               <l>The Ultimate of all their form'd Deſigns.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Auguſtus</hi> for a gen'ral Storm prepares,</l>
               <l>With one Aſſault to finiſh all the War;</l>
               <l>Appoints Detachments for this Enterprize,</l>
               <l>Back'd with Reſerves to yield their tim'd Supplies;</l>
               <pb n="154" facs="tcp:46801:79"/>
               <l>The Signal to advance they only wait,</l>
               <l>To force the Town, or tempt a Noble Fate.</l>
               <l>Here all the Scenes of Horror might be ſeen,</l>
               <l>That can deſtructive Fancies entertain.</l>
               <l>If e'er Contempt of Death poſſeſs'd the Mind,</l>
               <l>If that's imputed Brave in Humane Kind,</l>
               <l>The Soldiers here that Quality diſplay,</l>
               <l>On this remarkable, unhappy Day;</l>
               <l>In Order cloſe they enter on the Storm,</l>
               <l>And die in Ranks, e'er any Feats perform;</l>
               <l>Now to the Forts and Palliſades they come,</l>
               <l>Here either Side diſpenſe alike their Dooms;</l>
               <l>Granadoes in their deep Entrenchments fly,</l>
               <l>And force from thence the wounded Enemy.</l>
               <l>Theſe Out-works gain'd, a near Approach they make,</l>
               <l>The cloſe Beſieg'd this tim'd Advantage take,</l>
               <l>They fire their Mines, and Flames, like moving Spheres,</l>
               <l>Scatter Battalions up in ſcorching Air,</l>
               <pb n="155" facs="tcp:46801:79"/>
               <l>Stifl'd in Smoke, or elſe conſum'd in Fire,</l>
               <l>Sad Choice inevitable! they expire.</l>
               <l>Some thro' the Breach advance within the Town,</l>
               <l>They're Pris'ners made, or ſlain they tumble down.</l>
               <l>What Men cou'd act, theſe valiant Minds perform,</l>
               <l>And to the laſt Extreme purſu'd the Storm.</l>
               <l>The thin Remains <hi>Auguſtus</hi> calls away,</l>
               <l>Chears them with Praiſes, and augments their Pay,</l>
               <l>Draws off his Troops, and waits the next Campaign</l>
               <l>His diſappointed Laurels to regain.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>'Midſt theſe Misfortunes, theſe confus'd Affairs,</l>
               <l>Out from their Ports the <hi>Gallick</hi> Navy ſteers:</l>
               <l>Too ſure our Friendly Foes at home betray</l>
               <l>Our Weakneſs, and a certain Liſt convey</l>
               <l>Of all our Fleet, our want of Stores make known.</l>
               <l>Now was the Time —</l>
               <l>We muſt or burn, or in th' Abyſs ſink down.</l>
               <lg type="triplet">
                  <l>Too true it was, we unprovided were</l>
                  <l>Of Neceſſaries, and Supplies for War;</l>
                  <l>Nor cou'd our numbers with their Fleet compare.</l>
               </lg>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb n="156" facs="tcp:46801:80"/>
               <l>The <hi>Franks</hi> preſs fiercely forward to aſſail,</l>
               <l>Eager to ſeize the Game, and to prevail;</l>
               <l>Our Admiral ſaw it was in vain to fight,</l>
               <l>Loth to retire, to ſave his Ships by flight;</l>
               <l>Our hardy Seamen knew not to retreat,</l>
               <l>Knew not to yield to be unfortunate;</l>
               <l>They who had oft the <hi>Gallick</hi> Pow'r withſtood,</l>
               <l>And writ their Dooms in Characters of Blood;</l>
               <l>The <hi>Royal Sovereign</hi> daſh'd its angry Planks</l>
               <l>On foaming Waves, to be thus brav'd by <hi>Franks.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The Signal hois'd, commands our Fleet to veer</l>
               <l>Away, and to their Harbours ſtreight to ſteer;</l>
               <l>Juſt like fierce Lions chas'd on <hi>Libya</hi>'s Plains,</l>
               <l>Where Monarchs o'er ſubmiſſive Herds they reign,</l>
               <lg type="triplet">
                  <l>When Hunters, Dogs, and Toils, and Arms aſſail,</l>
                  <l>They move Majeſtick, laſhing with the Tail,</l>
                  <l>And leave the Field, not knowing to prevail:</l>
               </lg>
               <l>So with Diſdain th' unequal War we quit,</l>
               <l>Reſign the Ocean to the <hi>Gallick</hi> Fleet.</l>
               <pb n="157" facs="tcp:46801:80"/>
               <l>What preſent Loſs of Fame we did ſuſtain,</l>
               <l>Succeeding Years with Int'reſt will regain;</l>
               <l>A future Navy will in Strength appear</l>
               <l>T' eclipſe their <hi>Sun,</hi> and <hi>Mighty Thunderer.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>What Joy can this create to <hi>Albion</hi>'s Sons,</l>
               <l>To ſee themſelves by haughty <hi>Gauls</hi> outdone?</l>
               <l>By thoſe who e'rſt were Vaſſals to our Fame,</l>
               <l>We in our Arms their raviſh'd Enſigns claim.</l>
               <l>Were they the Sons of <hi>Rome</hi> that did conſpire</l>
               <l>To form our Woe, and ſet the Land on Fire?</l>
               <l>It was the beſt we cou'd expect from them;</l>
               <l>We're on our Guard, &amp; knew to quench the Flame.</l>
               <l>But this degen'rate Brood, this Vip'rous Race,</l>
               <l>The Stamps of all Morality deface;</l>
               <l>Divinity is made a meer Pretence</l>
               <l>To chequer their unbounded Inſolence;</l>
               <l>Their Conſciences they impiouſly debaſe,</l>
               <l>T' indulge their Humours, and diſturb the Peace:</l>
               <l>It's certain then, that <hi>Bedlam,</hi> or the Bar,</l>
               <l>Beſt ſuited to their Conſtitutions are.</l>
               <pb n="158" facs="tcp:46801:81"/>
               <l>This Year with various Turns of Fortune ends;</l>
               <l>Succeſs and Loſs ſucceſſively attend:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Janus</hi> revers'd, now turns a youthful Face;</l>
               <l>Old <hi>Time</hi> renew'd, ſtarts forth to run his Race;</l>
               <l>The Sun, the Planets, and revolving Spheres,</l>
               <l>Begin afreſh, and date a future Year;</l>
               <l>Their Influences variouſly inclin'd</l>
               <l>The diff'rent Diſpoſitions of Mankind:</l>
               <l>But <hi>Europe</hi> chiefly their Conjunctions warm</l>
               <l>With Martial Heat, and ſpur it on to arm.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The awful Senate of our Nation meets,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Auguſtus</hi> for <hi>Hybernian</hi> Conqueſts greets;</l>
               <l>That Senate which contending Monarchs awes,</l>
               <l>That to the ſtubborn Univerſe gives Laws;</l>
               <l>Awful as once the ancient <hi>Romans</hi> were,</l>
               <l>Supreme in Peace, commanding all in War;</l>
               <l>That Senate which compells from <hi>Gaul</hi> a Dread,</l>
               <l>She bluſhing, ſilent, owns her ſelf afraid;</l>
               <l>This Senate freely do their Treaſures give,</l>
               <l>T' aſſert <hi>Britannia</hi>'s Great Prerogative.</l>
               <pb n="159" facs="tcp:46801:81"/>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Drums thro' our Towns the Young and Valiant warm,</l>
               <l>Their Courage rowz'd, undaunted now they arm;</l>
               <l>Some to reduce <hi>Hybernia</hi>'s Iſland ſent,</l>
               <l>And others to th' Confederate Continent:</l>
               <l>Marines are liſted, and detach'd on Board,</l>
               <l>Theſe to the active Crews their Aids afford.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And now to lead the <hi>Riſing Sun</hi> a Dance,</l>
               <l>And introduce a <hi>Chorus</hi> worthy <hi>France,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Strong Machins fix'd in Veſſels on the Sea,</l>
               <l>Thro' yielding Air their dreadful Balls convey;</l>
               <l>Their Maritime Towns with Ruine we invade,</l>
               <l>And level them as low as <hi>Troy</hi> was laid;</l>
               <l>Their kindl'd Cities high in <hi>Aether</hi> blaze,</l>
               <l>And frighted <hi>Paris,</hi> and <hi>Verſailes</hi> amaze:</l>
               <l>We now defie the Pow'rs of <hi>Gaul</hi> and <hi>Rome,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>'Gainſt all our Foes we're fenc'd, but thoſe at home.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Of all the deep Projections they laid down,</l>
               <l>Chief of the num'rous reſt, take this for one:</l>
               <pb n="160" facs="tcp:46801:82"/>
               <l>This true, this ſure <hi>Hypotheſis</hi> they laid,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>To quell our Arms, is to eclipſe our Trade:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Our Force by Land and Sea too expert grown,</l>
               <l>In Arms have all Corrivals quite out-done:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Auguſtus</hi> yet eſcap'd their dated Day,</l>
               <l>They'll now deſtroy him in <hi>Effigie.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Swarms of a miſcreant Generation join</l>
               <l>T' adult'rate, and diminiſh <hi>Albion</hi>'s Coin;</l>
               <l>You might diſtinguiſh here a Copper Head,</l>
               <l>With a thin Sheet of <hi>Sterling</hi> nicely ſpread;</l>
               <l>The Subject thus, by hoarding Heaps of Coin,</l>
               <l>Bankrupts himſelf, and is by 's Caſh undone.</l>
               <lg type="triplet">
                  <l>The rav'nous Sheers had ſuch ſtrange Havock made,</l>
                  <l>The Royal Charm protected not the Head,</l>
                  <l>They pierc'd the Circle, and cut off the Beard.</l>
               </lg>
               <l>Theſe, like <hi>Prometheus</hi> Vultures, with their Art</l>
               <l>Deſtroy'd the Whole, by preying on a Part.</l>
               <l>Yet 'midſt theſe Troubles, maſſie Sums muſt go</l>
               <l>To Foreign Lands, to check the ſpreading Foe.</l>
               <pb n="161" facs="tcp:46801:82"/>
               <lg type="triplet">
                  <l>No Art but Fire this Miſchief cou'd redreſs;</l>
                  <l>It's order'd to run down th' infected Maſs,</l>
                  <l>And ſeparate the Tin, and Lead, and Braſs.</l>
               </lg>
               <l>And now it's glowing in the <hi>Cupulo,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Here floats <hi>Peru,</hi> there richer <hi>Mexico.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>This Turn of Treaſure has their Plots out done,</l>
               <l>We now proceed to finiſh what's begun.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Our Fleet was fitting ready for the Main,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Hybernia</hi> early opens the Campaign;</l>
               <l>The Gen'rals there have a Supreme Command;</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Auguſtus</hi> ſtays <hi>Britannia</hi> to defend:</l>
               <l>The Soldiers all invoke his <hi>Genius</hi> there,</l>
               <l>By that inſpir'd, they proſecute the War;</l>
               <l>They force each Paſs that did obſtruct their Way,</l>
               <l>And in a well fought Battel gain'd the Day:</l>
               <l>The Garriſons at their Approach are quell'd,</l>
               <l>And all <hi>Hybernia</hi> to <hi>Auguſtus</hi> yields.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The Conqu'ring Army croſs the hilly Main,</l>
               <l>And into <hi>Flanders</hi> carry the Campaign,</l>
               <pb n="162" facs="tcp:46801:83"/>
               <l>Th' injurious <hi>Franks</hi> at their own Doors to meet,</l>
               <l>And to their very Gates convey their Fate.</l>
               <l>Thus <hi>Scipio</hi> reliev'd his Native <hi>Rome,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>When <hi>Hannibal</hi> had <hi>Italy</hi> o'ercome,</l>
               <l>Tranſports the Face of War to <hi>Carthage</hi> Walls,</l>
               <l>Whilſt <hi>Africk</hi> all before his Conduct falls.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Now bounding Waves our Royal Navy bear,</l>
               <l>With all the Strength and Pomp that graces War:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Neptune</hi> ne'er ſaw the like upon the Main;</l>
               <l>It pleas'd, yet did ſurprize the Sea-born Train;</l>
               <l>The <hi>Nymphs,</hi> and <hi>Nereids,</hi> and the <hi>Syrens</hi> come,</l>
               <l>And with ecſtatick Wonder are ſtruck dumb;</l>
               <l>Our Martial Muſick echo'd on the Sea,</l>
               <l>And made a Warlike pleaſing Harmony.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The <hi>Gallick</hi> Prince well-woven Plots had laid,</l>
               <l>This Summer the great Game of <hi>France</hi> was plaid;</l>
               <l>By Land <hi>Auguſtus</hi> muſt by Ruffians die,</l>
               <l>He's on the Sea ſecure of Victory;</l>
               <l>He'd then conduct <hi>Caeſario</hi> to the Throne,</l>
               <l>Or for himſelf claim conquer'd <hi>Albion.</hi>
               </l>
               <pb n="163" facs="tcp:46801:83"/>
               <l>How Man projects! But Fate directs his Road,</l>
               <l>And baffles his Endeavours with a Nod.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Our Men of War in proper Stations ſtood,</l>
               <l>And forwards lave, and ſpoom it o'er the Flood;</l>
               <l>The frisking Winds veer oft, and change the Gale;</l>
               <l>Our chearful Seamen know to hand each Sail:</l>
               <l>The Soldiers, all in Heart, all Things prepare,</l>
               <l>Or for Offenſive, or Defenſive War.</l>
               <l>Upon the Top-maſt-head aloft they ſpy,</l>
               <l>If Fortune offer'd yet an Enemy:</l>
               <l>And now they ſee the <hi>Gallick</hi> Fleet draw near,</l>
               <l>With chearful Shouts they rend the very Air;</l>
               <l>No Muſe their eager Strains of Joy can tell,</l>
               <l>Their Raptures all were inexpreſſible;</l>
               <l>Revenge with Courage join, and brave Diſdain,</l>
               <l>Now to retrieve their tarniſh'd Fame again.</l>
               <l>The other, haughty with Succeſs, bear down,</l>
               <l>Inſultingly conclude the Day their own.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Our Gunners all in readineſs prepare,</l>
               <l>Th' incumber'd Decks, and ev'ry Gun they clear;</l>
               <pb n="164" facs="tcp:46801:84"/>
               <l>Their Cabins and their Hammocks level laid,</l>
               <l>They no Repoſe expected now in Bed.</l>
               <l>Here Stores of miſſive Shot and Cartridge lie,</l>
               <l>The Guns of large and ſmaller Size ſupply;</l>
               <l>Red Waſte-clothes ev'ry Ship encompaſs round,</l>
               <l>To skreen the Men and Boys, and ſave a Wound;</l>
               <l>The Bloody Flag and Pendent they diſplay,</l>
               <l>And Drums and Trumpets make a noiſie Day.</l>
               <l>The <hi>Franks</hi> diſmiſs their murd'ring Balls from far,</l>
               <l>And at a diſtance proſecute the War;</l>
               <l>But our bold <hi>Britans</hi> other Orders know,</l>
               <l>To th' Windward urge, and near approach the Foe;</l>
               <l>They ſlight their pelting Shot, and ſtrive to gain</l>
               <l>So cloſe, as not t' expend one Ball in vain.</l>
               <l>And now their fiery Sides each other meet,</l>
               <l>In Flame and Smoke alternately they greet;</l>
               <l>Betwixt their Decks we rake them thro' and thro',</l>
               <l>Our Croſs-bar Shots burſt in, and all deſtroy;</l>
               <l>The wreſted Splinters with wild Ruine rake,</l>
               <l>Wheree'er they touch vaſt hideous Wounds they make;</l>
               <pb n="165" facs="tcp:46801:84"/>
               <l>Limbleſs their Bodies on the Decks are thrown,</l>
               <l>Or in the very midſt aſunder torn.</l>
               <l>The <hi>Gallick</hi> Ships with guſhing Blood run o'er,</l>
               <l>And the green Sea's diſguis'd with Crimſon Gore;</l>
               <l>Here ſcatter'd Brains and Members lie around,</l>
               <l>And gaſping Corps deform'd with many a Wound</l>
               <l>Old hoary <hi>Neptune</hi> ſhook his Ouzy Head,</l>
               <l>And with his frighted Nymphs agaſt, he fled,</l>
               <l>Div'd to the bottom of the tinctur'd Main,</l>
               <l>And there ſecur'd himſelf and all his Train.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>This Bloody Carnage neither Side diſmay'd;</l>
               <l>Each Broad-ſide by another is repaid:</l>
               <l>They tack about, and pour in large Replies,</l>
               <l>Loud as tumultuous Thunder in the Skies;</l>
               <l>Their Small-ſhot thick as falling Hail does fly,</l>
               <l>Now Board to Board contending Squadrons ply;</l>
               <l>Each grapples cloſe, and laſh themſelves ſecure,</l>
               <l>And all Extreams of Service now endure:</l>
               <l>Burning Granadoes thrown ſcour all the Decks,</l>
               <l>Men fall, and hear each others rueful Shricks;</l>
               <pb n="166" facs="tcp:46801:85"/>
               <l>With reeking Swords upon the Deck they come,</l>
               <l>And, ſure of Conqueſt, meet untimely Doom;</l>
               <l>The Powder-Cheſts by fatal Trains take Fire,</l>
               <l>Blown up, they mount in Air, and there expire.</l>
               <l>Their Bodies ſcorch'd, in horrid Show'rs deſcend,</l>
               <l>Hiſs in the cooler Waves, and gaſp their End;</l>
               <l>Others to ſhun the Flames, eſpouſe the Sea,</l>
               <l>Float there a while, then ſink, and loſe the Day.</l>
               <l>Here by a thouſand Wounds ſome Ships you'll ſee</l>
               <l>Boar'd thro', let in whole Deluges of Sea,</l>
               <l>Sinking with Weight, to <hi>Neptune</hi>'s Courts they go,</l>
               <l>And fathom Eddies in th' Abyſs below.</l>
               <l>Here kindl'd Fire-ſhips, like <hi>Vulcano's,</hi> ride,</l>
               <l>Diſpenſe their curling Flames, reſiſtleſs, wide;</l>
               <l>Hiſſing they roll upon the heated Flood,</l>
               <l>And ſcatter an infectious Neighbourhood.</l>
               <l>Their Veſſels burn in Lines, and from afar</l>
               <l>Appear like Beacons that proclaim a War;</l>
               <l>Here blaz'd their <hi>Second,</hi> and their <hi>Riſing Sun</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Finds equal Fate with daring <hi>Phaeton;</hi>
               </l>
               <pb n="167" facs="tcp:46801:85"/>
               <l>Their Hulls in Flames diſcloſe a diſmal Sea,</l>
               <l>Where ſhatter'd Wrecks, and floating Bodies lay.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>A num'rous Liſt of Ships their Navy loſt;</l>
               <l>Some few eſcape with Tidings to their Coaſts;</l>
               <l>Diſabl'd ſome, they float, and make no Way,</l>
               <l>They've not a Prow, nor Helm, nor Shrowd to play;</l>
               <l>Their Maſts all levell'd on the Decks fall down,</l>
               <l>And they muſt chuſe their Fate, to burn, or drown.</l>
               <l>Not longer able to ſuſtain the Fight,</l>
               <l>They fly, and we purſue them by their Light;</l>
               <l>Ruine and Death we to their Shores convey,</l>
               <l>The Fame we loſt before, we win this Day;</l>
               <l>Teach the preſumptuous <hi>Gauls</hi> our Rule to know,</l>
               <l>And force them to <hi>Britannia</hi>'s Pow'r to bow.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>If Humane Joys cou'd claim a larger Date,</l>
               <l>Not be precarious to the Frowns of Fate,</l>
               <l>Mortality wou'd then aſpire too high,</l>
               <l>Twou'd Rival ev'n our Kindred in the Sky:</l>
               <pb n="168" facs="tcp:46801:86"/>
               <l>If Royalty and Greatneſs cou'd deterr</l>
               <l>Misfortunes from a bold Approach too near;</l>
               <l>Princes above a common Level grown,</l>
               <l>Might always ſit ſerene, and fill the Throne.</l>
               <l>But Man's obnoxious all to Good and Ill,</l>
               <l>Fortune and Death alike diſturb and kill;</l>
               <l>A ſad Decree on <hi>Fame</hi>'s ill Wings did fly,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Now muſt the Fair, the Great</hi> Auguſta <hi>die.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Too true, too ſure the heavy Tidings prove,</l>
               <l>Her Royal Soul leaves Earth, and ſoars above:</l>
               <l>Too near Perfection her Great Mind was grown,</l>
               <l>Refin'd from Droſs, diſdain'd a Preſſure down;</l>
               <l>It mounted, like Aethereal Matter, high,</l>
               <l>To viſit, and inhabit in the Sky.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>Auguſtus</hi> almoſt had with Grief expir'd,</l>
               <l>Yea, for a while his mighty Soul retir'd,</l>
               <l>And on the wing with hers was half ways gone,</l>
               <l>So everlaſting was the Union:</l>
               <l>Fate interpos'd, and urg'd it down below,</l>
               <l>To finiſh its Illuſtrious Stages thro'.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb n="169" facs="tcp:46801:86"/>
               <l>Who rightly can this Publick Loſs diſcloſe,</l>
               <l>Too vaſt for Verſe, and too ſublime for Proſe?</l>
               <l>Yet <hi>Burnet</hi>'s Pen her wondrous Vertues told,</l>
               <l>In his immortal Lines her deathleſs Fame's enroll'd.</l>
               <l>'Twas ſure to puniſh murm'ring <hi>Albion</hi>'s Land,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Albion</hi> that's cloy'd with Manna that deſcends,</l>
               <l>That Heav'n this Star from our Horizon calls,</l>
               <l>And leaves no Copy of th' Original;</l>
               <l>Or that ſhe was a Maſter-piece Divine,</l>
               <l>And Nature muſt fall ſhort, or end the Line.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Auguſtus</hi> ſtill his Warlike Race purſues,</l>
               <l>In Foreign Fields ſeeks out, and meets his Foes;</l>
               <l>No Plots Domeſtick cou'd his Life invade,</l>
               <l>Th' Aſſaſſines all, and their Deſigns betray'd.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>Gallia</hi> at length fatigu'd, does Peace implore,</l>
               <l>And to the World its raviſh'd Spoils reſtores</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Auguſtus</hi> rides in Triumph o'er the Main,</l>
               <l>And ſees <hi>Britannia</hi> bleſs'd with Peace again.</l>
            </lg>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:46801:87"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:46801:87"/>
            <head>
               <hi>Books printed for and ſold by</hi> J. Sprint, <hi>at the</hi> Bell <hi>in</hi> Little Britain.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>SYnopſis Medicinae:</hi> Or, A <hi>Compendium</hi> of the Theory and Practice of Phyſick. In Seven Books. Containing, I. The Elements or Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of the Art. II. The Cure of Infants Diſeaſes. III. The Cure of Diſeaſes in the Head. IV. The Cure of Diſeaſes in the Breaſt. V. The Cure of Diſeaſes in the Belly. VI. The Cure of Diſeaſes Univerſal. VII. The Cure of all ſorts of Fevers. Shewing the Names, Signs, Cauſes, Differences, Prognoſticks, and various Intentions of Curing all kinds of Diſeaſes from Head to Foot, hapning to Humane Bodies. <hi>Galenically</hi> and <hi>Chymically</hi> per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed. The like never publiſhed before in any Language whatſoever. <hi>The Fourth Edition.</hi> Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, beſides the Addition of nearly the whole Firſt Book, there are ſeveral Hundreds of other Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions, Alterations, and Amendments, through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the whole Work. By <hi>William Salmon,</hi> Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſor of Phyſick.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Trades-man's Calling.</hi> Being a Diſcourſe concerning the Nature, Neceſſity, Choice, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> of a <hi>Calling</hi> in general: And, Directions for the right managing of the <hi>Trades-men's Calling</hi> in particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar. By <hi>Richard Steele,</hi> M. A. and Miniſter of the Goſpel. <hi>The Second Edition.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>De Quatuor Summis Imperiis.</hi> An Hiſtorical Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of the Four Chief Monarchies or Empires of the World: <hi>Viz.</hi> I. The <hi>Aſſyrian,</hi> or <hi>Babylo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nian.</hi> II. The <hi>Perſian.</hi> III. The <hi>Grecian.</hi> IV. The
<pb facs="tcp:46801:88"/>
               <hi>Roman,</hi> continued down to the Beginning of the Reign of the Emperor <hi>Charles</hi> the Fifth. Being a Relation of the moſt conſiderable Occurrences that have hapned in the World from <hi>Noah</hi>'s Flood to the Year of our Lord <hi>J. C.</hi> 1520. Written in <hi>Latin</hi> by <hi>John Sleidan,</hi> ſometime Ambaſſador in <hi>England</hi> from the Proteſtant States of <hi>Germany,</hi> Deputy for the City of <hi>Strasburgh</hi> in the Council of <hi>Trent,</hi> and Author of <hi>The Hiſtory of the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation of Religion in</hi> Germany. Now newly <hi>Engliſhed:</hi> With his Life.</p>
            <p>Innocent Diverſion for the Ladies, Gentlewo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, and Maidens, Being a Looking-glaſs for the Fair Sex; wherein, by a curious Book of <hi>For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune,</hi> they may find out Anſwers to their moſt doubtful Queſtions which can be propoſed. With a large Interpretation of Dreams and Viſions, incident to the Fair Sex. Tranſlated from the <hi>French.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Pious Man's Directions: Shewing how to walk with God all his Days. By a Well-wiſher of the <hi>Whole Duty of Man. The Third Edition.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>An Explicatory Catechiſm: Or, An Explana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Aſſemblies Shorter Catechiſm. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in all the Anſwers in the Aſſemblies Catechiſm are taken abroad in Under-Queſtions and Anſwers, the Truths explained, and proved by Reaſon and Scripture; ſeveral Caſes of Conſcience reſolved; ſome chief Controverſies in Religion ſtated, with Arguments againſt divers Errors: Uſeful to be read in Private Families, after Examination in the Catechiſm it ſelf; for the more clear and thorow underſtanding of what is therein learned. By <hi>Thomas Vincent,</hi> ſometimes Miniſter of <hi>Maud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lin Milk-ſtreet</hi> in <hi>London.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:46801:88"/>
            <p>A Treatiſe concerning the Lord's Supper: With Three Dialogues for the more full Infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation of the Weak, in the Nature and Uſe of this Sacrament. By <hi>Tho. Doolittle. The Nineteenth Edition.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Time, and the End of Time: In Two Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſes. The Firſt about <hi>Redemption of Time:</hi> The Second about <hi>Conſideration of our Latter End.</hi> By <hi>John Fox.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A Spark from the Altar:</hi> Or, A Sure Guide to Communicants, before, at, and after Receiving the Lord's Supper. Conſiſting of Meditations, Hymns, and Prayers for every Day in the Week. To which is added, Directions for Holy Living and Dying. With a Pathetick Diſcourſe on <hi>Death, Judgment, Heaven,</hi> and <hi>Hell.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Cookery Refin'd:</hi> Or, The Lady, Gentlewoman, and Servant-Maids uſeful Companion. I. Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining the curious Arts of Dreſſing all ſorts of Fleſh, Fiſh, and Fowl, various Ways, after the neweſt Mode; with their proper Seaſonings, Sauces, Garniſhes, Serving up, and Carving. II. The Experienced Paſtry Cook, in all Parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culars. To which is added, The Art of Pickling Fruits, Buds, Herbs, Flowers, Roots, Stalks, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> By Mrs. <hi>A. M.</hi> a long Practiſer in this Curious Art.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Arts Maſter-piece:</hi> Or, A Companion for the Ingenious of either Sex. Containing, I. The Art of Limning and Painting in Oil, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> in all Particulars, <hi>viz.</hi> Drawing and Painting Faces, Bodies, Garments, Landskip, Preparing and Lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing on Colours; alſo Colouring Mezzotinto Prints, Gilding on Wood, Metals, and Leather.
<pb facs="tcp:46801:89"/>II. The neweſt Experiment in Japanning, to imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate the <hi>Indian</hi> Way, Plain and in Speckles, Rock<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>work, Figures, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Receipts for making the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral ſorts of Varniſhes, Colours, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> III. To make Artificial Tortoiſe-ſhell; to Dye or Stain Ivory, Horn, Stone, Briſtles, Feathers, and ſundry ſorts of Woods for Cabinets. IV. The Myſtery of Dying Silks, Stuffs, Woollen and Linnen Cloth. V. To take Spots, Stains, Pitch, Tar, and Iron-Molds, out of Silks, Stuffs, Linnen, and Woollen, and to recover Faded Silks, Linnen, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> VI. The Art of Perfuming and Beautifying. VII. Divers Phyſical and Chirurgical Receipts. VIII. To make <hi>London</hi> Powder-Ink, other Powder-Inks, and the ſhining <hi>Japan</hi>-Ink. With many other notable Things. By <hi>C. K.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Experienc'd Fowler:</hi> Or, The Gentleman, Citizen, and Country-man's pleaſant and profita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Recreation. Containing, I. The true Art of Taking Water and Land-Fowl, with divers kinds of Nets, Lime-Twigs, Lime-Buſhes, and how to make the beſt Bird Lime. II. Directions for Bat-Fowling, Lowbelling, Tramelling, and Driving Fowl; how to find their Haunts, and take them with Springes, Snares, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> III. An exact Method for uſing the Fowling-piece at a true Level, to ſhoot at the Water, Ground, Buſh, or Flying. IV. How to make Shot, proportion the Charge, and know good Powder; with the proper Uſe of the Stalking-Horſe, Buſh, Hedge, and how to manage them. V. Of Singing-Birds, their Diſeaſes and Cure. VI. How to diſtinguiſh all ſorts of Poulterers Ware, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> VII. To which is added, Directions for deſtroying all manner of Vermine.</p>
            <p>The true Art of <hi>Angling, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:46801:89"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
